<catalog><body>
 <sections>From the editors</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 
 <hedline>Locked down and loaded policy doesn&rsquo;t add up</hedline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_EDIT02.jpg"></photo>
 
<photo.caption>Newtown, Conn.</photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Carlo Allegri/Reuters</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 
 <p>Canada is not the United States. </p>
 
 <p>It shouldn&rsquo;t be necessary to make such an obvious observation. But with the premier of Canada&rsquo;s largest province apparently overlooking this fact, it seems worth repeating. </p>
 
 <p>In one of his final policy moves before retiring later this month, Ontario Premier Dalton McGuinty recently announced a &ldquo;locked-door policy&rdquo; for all 4,000 publicly funded elementary schools in the province; and a $10-million fund to pay for new security systems so school visitors can be &ldquo;buzzed in.&rdquo; This in response to the horrific shooting of 20 children and six adults at the Sandy Hook Elementary School in Newtown, Conn., last December. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;In the aftermath of that tragic event that unfolded in the U.S., I think there&rsquo;s an important question that we need to ask ourselves: are we taking all reasonable steps to ensure the safety of our kids at school?&rdquo; McGuinty said in making the announcement. </p>
 
 <p>It is a move with possible national significance. As the largest education system in the country, policies implemented in Ontario&rsquo;s schools are often adopted across Canada. And school safety is certainly a hot topic among parents everywhere. </p>
 
 <p>And yet while horror at the massacre in Newtown may be universal, locking every school door is not the appropriate response for Canada. </p>
 
 <p>McGuinty&rsquo;s policy mistakenly proposes to solve another country&rsquo;s problems. As terrifying as the thought of a public school shooting may be, it is important to recognize that it&rsquo;s entirely a U.S. phenomenon, arising from centuries of unique political circumstances. </p>
 
 <p>The facts tell the tale: in the past 20 years there have been five shootings inside a Canadian elementary or secondary school, resulting in two deaths. (And in neither case did a stranger enter a school and start shooting.) Over the same time period the U.S. has endured more than 70 school shootings with a death toll exceeding 230. If we restrict ourselves to elementary schools alone, which is the focus of Ontario&rsquo;s new proposal, the difference is even starker. No shootings and no deaths in Canada. </p>
 
 <p>The proper Canadian response to Newtown should be to express shock and offer assistance, as any good neighbour would. But no other action is warranted because school shootings are simply not a Canadian issue. In fact, deaths at Canadian schools arising from anaphylaxis or other medical emergencies far outweigh death by gunshot, suggesting Ontario&rsquo;s extra $10 million would be much better spent training teachers in first aid. And locking every door will inevitably delay response times when such regular health emergencies occur. </p>
 
 <p>Even if we accept McGuinty&rsquo;s flawed logic that &ldquo;all reasonable steps&rdquo; are in order when the issue is child safety, nothing learned from the Connecticut massacre leads to the conclusion that locking doors is beneficial. Sandy Hook Elementary already had a locked door and buzzer system in place. Adam Lanza, armed with two pistols and an assault rifle, simply shot or smashed his way in. </p>
 
 <p>Further, that U.S. lawyers have been mulling a class action lawsuit based on the assumption that the school&rsquo;s locked doors should have been constructed with bulletproof glass suggests where a mindless preoccupation with safety can lead: to policies that are unnecessarily expensive, overly dramatic and patently absurd. </p>
 
 <p>Children still spend recess outside. Should we install security fences as well? Gates? Metal detectors? Keep in mind the Ontario government previously offered schools funding for security buzzers on a voluntary basis; less than one-quarter of all elementary schools took the money. The vast majority of schools presumably felt their existing procedures were sufficient. </p>
 
 <p>Beyond the sheer waste of $10 million on a pointless door-locking exercise, McGuinty&rsquo;s move is equally lamentable for what it says to and about Canadian society. </p>
 
 <p>Stoking fears of non-existent security threats and then implementing sweeping procedures in response simply ratchets up the needless anxiety that already infects modern life. Despite widespread evidence that life today is considerably safer than ever before, irrational fears of such things as playground equipment, sexual predators, water bottles and boisterous play have turned us into a society afraid to send our kids outdoors. Now we&rsquo;re going so far as to lock them inside. </p>
 
 <p>And it has become almost impossible to argue against such fear-mongering, at the risk of appearing callous or uncaring. Significantly, opposition parties in Ontario agreed with McGuinty&rsquo;s locked-door policy. No one wants to speak up for common sense when the topic is child safety. But there is clearly a balance to be found between showing appropriate concern for the security of our children and preserving the essence of Canadian society. </p>
 
 <p>Elementary schools ought to be the beating heart of every Canadian neighbourhood. We should keep them open and welcoming to visitors and comforting and familiar to children. Turning them into locked bunkers does neither.</p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Letters</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 
 <hedline>Letters</hedline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_LETTERS01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.byline>Adrian Wyld/CP</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 
 <p>Scarcity of smart things </p>
 
 <p>I read with interest and alarm the article about the &ldquo;99 stupid things the government did with your money&rdquo; (National, Jan. 14) last year. Next month, could you please do the 99 <em>smart</em> things the government did last year? Or would they be too hard to find? </p>
 
 <p><em>Ghislaine Dean, Burlington, Ont. </em></p>
 
 
 
 <p>The 99 stupid things governments do with our money reinforces my opinion that something is built into government facilities that prevents entry of common sense. Very few successful business people enter politics. Our public administration tends to be made up of unsuccessful businesspeople, lifelong civil servants and others who feed at the public trough. If you have never had to struggle to meet a payroll, or mortgage your house to raise funds, it is easy to spend without regard to where it came from. </p>
 
 <p><em>Bernie Cusack, Port Colborne, Ont. </em></p>
 
 
 <p>As usual, your annual stupid things that governments spend money on was funny and infuriating at the same time. The 99 things seem to fall into two broad camps: general bureaucratic foul-ups and individual ethical lapses. The pettiness of the latter never ceases to amaze me. It might be fun to put out a call for anonymous whistleblower tales of corporate boondoggles. Who knows, you might get 999 good stories out of that. I have worked in both the private and public sectors, and when I hear about the efficiency of the private sector, I just laugh out loud.</p>
 
 <p><em>Robert Roaldi, Ottawa </em></p>
 
 
 <p>What Harper can learn from Lincoln </p>
 
 <p>Preston Manning muses about the United States following Abraham Lincoln&rsquo;s strategy as laid out in the new biopic (&ldquo;Lessons from <em>Lincoln</em>,&rdquo; International, Dec. 24), suggesting that Barack Obama build a coalition with rivals, pursue reconciliation and keep a sense of humour. These strategies are sadly lacking here in Canada within Stephen Harper&rsquo;s government. We need Conservatives like Manning to make this government listen to the &ldquo;better angels of their nature,&rdquo; as it has demonstrated time and time again that it has no interest in listening to anyone else. Fellow Conservatives are the only people who have any chance of reining in a government that refuses to conciliate or to compromise. Having been involved in the struggle to change the &ldquo;tough on crime&rdquo; laws and being currently involved in trying to convince the government to change its mind about closing the Experimental Lakes Area, I know this government&rsquo;s rhinoceros hide well. </p>
 
 <p><em>Peter Kirby, Kenora, Ont. </em></p>
 
 
 
 <p>Really appreciated Preston Manning&rsquo;s take on reconciliation, which he urges U.S. politicians to pursue &ldquo;at its most profound level.&rdquo; The writer, a <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> lifetime-achieving parliamentarian, is an unapologetic admirer of Abraham Lincoln&rsquo;s belief that reconciliation is &ldquo;as much spiritual as it is political.&rdquo; But never mind offering such sage advice to American politicos, Preston. How about telling Stephen Harper to stop stonewalling Canada&rsquo;s Truth and Reconciliation Commission by withholding millions of documents related to its inquiry into Indian residential schools? Please convince your protege that &ldquo;if you must change your position in order to resolve the crisis that is tearing your country apart, regard these changes not as compromises, but as self-sacrificial acts that are part of the price of reconciliation.&rdquo; Amen, Mr. Manning. Would you be interested in joining the Idle No More movement? </p>
 
 <p><em>Maurice Switzer, Director of Communications, Union of Ontario Indians, North Bay, Ont.</em></p>
 
  <p>Human intrusion </p>
 
 <p>Jim Sterba, author of <em>Nature Wars</em> (Interview, Dec. 24), justifies the culling&mdash;or killing&mdash;of wildlife by conveniently ignoring the fundamental cause of the problem: our incessant encroaching upon wildlife&rsquo;s natural habitat. Overabundant animal populations? Human population has grown from four billion in 1974 to seven billion in 2011. We are the invasive species, but according to Sterba, wildlife is to be blamed&mdash;and eventually punished&mdash;for the ensuing cohabitation problems. Sterba&rsquo;s views illustrate the profound disconnect that exists between man and nature, a disconnect that will persist and deepen as long as we see nature as something to be used solely or principally for our consumption, comfort and entertainment. Isn&rsquo;t it time we rethink our relation to nature, including wildlife? </p>
 
 <p><em>Gilles Gamas, Hinton, Alta. </em></p>
 
 
 
 <p>I strongly disagree with the notion John Sterba puts forth: that nature will not balance itself. It has been doing so for millennia. He also claims &ldquo;we are living in closer proximity to more wild birds, animals and trees than anywhere on the planet at any time in history.&rdquo; While we do live in a fantastic part of the world well-endowed with natural riches, I find it hard to compare the scant flocks of Canada Geese I see today with stories of our country&rsquo;s natural past. For instance, one flock of passenger pigeons (now extinct) in southern Ontario in 1866 was described as being 1.5 km wide and 500 km long, taking 14 hours to pass and holding in excess of 3.5 billion birds. That, sir, is natural abundance. </p>
 
 <p><em>Chris Heywood, Toronto </em></p>
 
 <p>Canadian portrait </p>
 
 <p>I know <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> gives news on world affairs, but how embarrassing for Canada that you could not come up with a better cover for your 2012 Year in Pictures issue (Jan. 7). Barack Obama and his wife? Really? Did Canada not produce anything worthy enough to get the front page on this Canadian publication?	 </p>
 
 <p><em>Frances Beaudoin, Sanibel, Fla. </em></p>
 
 
 
 <p>Monkey business </p>
 
 <p>Although I realize Barbara Amiel&rsquo;s rant concerning Darwin the rhesus macaque monkey (&ldquo;Let the monkey go home,&rdquo; Opinion, Jan. 14) is at least in part tongue in cheek, her contention that Toronto city officials crossed the double yellow line by confiscating the animal demonstrates an appalling lack of knowledge regarding the keeping of monkeys as pets. She says &ldquo;restrictions should be limited to ones necessary for the safety, comfort and enjoyment of all.&rdquo;&nbsp;That cute baby monkey will, when he reaches sexual maturity, be a danger to all who come in contact with him. Pet monkeys&mdash;especially small monkeys, capuchins and macaques just like Darwin&mdash; have inflicted vicious bites to the faces, hands, arms and legs of monkey &ldquo;parents,&rdquo; requiring costly surgeries to repair often permanent nerve damage. The saddest part? In most cases, the monkeys are euthanized. If we accept Amiel&rsquo;s&nbsp;argument&nbsp;and let the monkey go home, his adult life will probably be brutal and short. </p>
 
 <p><em>Lesley English, West Guilford, Ont. </em></p>
 
 <p>Songs in space </p>
 
 <p>You mention that space station commander Chris Hadfield made the first song recorded in space (&ldquo;Out of this world,&rdquo; Newsmakers, Jan. 14). But Irish-American Cady Coleman was first: you can listen to it on the Chieftains&rsquo; 50th anniversary CD, <em>Voice of Ages</em>, from last year; she recorded her flute part on the song <em>The Chieftains in Orbit</em> while on the International Space Station. </p>
 
 <p><em>Stefan Hofbauer, B&ouml;heimkirchen, Austria </em></p>
 
 <p>Piping it in </p>
 
 <p>The two young pipe organists of Organized Crime Duo are superb solo players, including of music by Buxtehude, Bach, Franck, Dupr&eacute;, Reger, Laurin, etc. on their programs (&ldquo;The key to survival,&rdquo; Music, Jan. 7). By including transcriptions of <em>Star Wars</em> and Beatles songs, they are following a tradition of centuries, as organists long have played opera overtures and other orchestral works. The organ is both a liturgical instrument and an entertainment instrument. </p>
 
 <p><em>Patricia Wright, Toronto </em></p>
 
 
 
 <p>CLARIFICATION </p>
 
 <p>Some of the information in the obituary of Albert Lisacek (The End, Jan. 7) drew from a piece on <em>BestStory.ca</em> by editor Warren Perley, who was interviewed for and quoted in the obituary. The site also provided <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> with the photo on the same page.</p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>This week</sections>
 
<body.head>

 <hedline>Good News</hedline>
 
</body.head>

 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_WEEK_GOOD01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_WEEK_BAD01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Pakistani schoolgirl Malala Yousafzai was released from a U.K. hospital</photo.caption>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Record high temperatures in Tasmania sparked numerous brush fires</photo.caption>
 
 
 <photo.byline>Reuters; Kevin Winter/Getty Images</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Asian awakening </p>
 
 <p>In a country still haunted by Tiananmen Square, demonstrations are a rare sight. But a newspaper office in southern China was ground zero for a daring protest over free speech this week, as hundreds gathered to voice their anger at the rewriting of an editorial by government censors. The local protest spread online and quickly turned viral as academics, celebrities and countless others joined in an unprecedented call for reform. The backlash represents a massive test for Xi Jinping, the new Communist Party chief, who has recently mused about the &ldquo;great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.&rdquo; Listening to the protesters would be a gigantic first step. </p>
 
 <p>Apply within </p>
 
 <p>Controversial changes to Canada&rsquo;s Employment Insurance are now in effect, and despite some inevitable backlash, the new rules are completely reasonable. Out-of-work Canadians collecting EI benefits are now expected to put together resum&eacute;s, attend job fairs and actually apply for &ldquo;suitable jobs.&rdquo; A new alert system will send out two daily notifications about employment postings. Our advice? Consider becoming a seamstress, jeweller or dietitian. A new U.S. study says all three professions are among the least stressful. </p>
 
 <p>Tear down this mall </p>
 
 <p>More than six months after a chunk of its roof caved in, killing two people and injuring 20 more, the rest of the mall in Elliot Lake, Ont., is finally coming down. Demolition crews have begun to dismantle what&rsquo;s left of the doomed structure, which will be completely levelled by the end of February. Meanwhile, another northern Ontario community is saying goodbye to another unwanted building: Timmins is selling the Shania Twain Centre to a buyer who is widely expected to use the facility for something else. So much for &ldquo;forever and for always.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Maybe we aren&rsquo;t alone </p>
 
 <p>It was a promising week in the endless search for faraway life. A prominent group of astronomers said the Milky Way is home to at least 17 billion Earth-sized planets, while NASA announced it has detected 461 new potential alien planets, including four that may be capable of supporting life. The bigger question still lingers: has anyone discovered us yet?</p>
 

 <hedline>Good News</hedline>


 <p>Bin Laden&rsquo;s hit list </p>
 
 <p>A heavily censored report prepared by federal security officials says documents recovered from Osama bin Laden&rsquo;s Pakistani compound specifically name Canada as a worthy target for terrorism. The report, released after an Access to Information request, is further confirmation that the late al-Qaeda leader considered us a sworn enemy deserving of attack, along with the U.S., Britain, Israel, Germany and Spain. &ldquo;Canada&rsquo;s international profile as a potential terrorist target has been confirmed,&rdquo; the analysis reads. &ldquo;Canada remains a viable target of Islamist terrorism.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Out of hiding, still in denial </p>
 
 <p>Defiant until the end, Syrian dictator Bashar al-Assad delivered a rare public speech last week, laying out a so-called &ldquo;peace plan&rdquo; that would include a national reconciliation conference, a new constitution and free elections&mdash;but no role for those &ldquo;who have betrayed Syria.&rdquo; Not surprisingly, his proposal was promptly rejected by Western leaders and UN Secretary-General Ban Ki-moon. The U.S. State Department dismissed the speech as &ldquo;yet another attempt by the regime to cling to power.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Bush league </p>
 
 <p>Canadian hockey fans may be celebrating the return of the NHL, but it was a forgettable week for our men&rsquo;s national junior team. For the first time in 14 years, Team Canada did not capture a medal at the world junior championships after losing in overtime to Russia in the bronze-medal game. Ironically, expectations were extra high this year because the Canuck roster was loaded with locked-out players who, if the NHL season had started on time, would have been playing for their pro teams, not the national squad. </p>
 
 <p>(Face)booked </p>
 
 <p>According to a new study out of Berlin, the simple act of posting a status update on Facebook can make people feel less lonely&mdash;even if nobody responds to it. But be careful what you write. Jacob Cox-Brown, an 18-year-old Oregon man, was arrested after typing this on his Facebook page: &ldquo;Drivin drunk &hellip; classsic ;) But to whoever&rsquo;s vehicle i hit i am sorry.&rdquo; And in Thunder Bay, Ont., police used the social networking site to track down a suspect of their own, a 19-year-old who allegedly boasted online about robbing a Mac&rsquo;s convenience store.</p>
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Newsmakers</hedline>
 <abstract>Chris Hadfield&rsquo;s homage to Star Trek, Justin Bieber&rsquo;s homage to Stratford, and Prince Charles opens up</abstract>
 
 <byline>Jaime J. Weinman, Jonathon Gatehouse, Ken Macqueen, Patricia Treble</byline>

 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_NEWSMAKERS02.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Justin Bieber</photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Indigo/Getty Images</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Talking back to the crowd </p>
 
 <p>AC Milan midfielder Kevin-Prince Boateng has inspired a spirited debate over how to deal with the growing problem of racist taunts by soccer fans. Boateng, a German-born Ghanaian, led his visiting team off the field during a &ldquo;friendly&rdquo; match last week with Pro Patria in northern Italy, to protest racist epithets being hurled from a group of home-team supporters. His decision to &ldquo;run away&rdquo; was criticized by Sepp Blatter, president of FIFA, the sport&rsquo;s governing body. But Boateng was applauded by his coach, many fellow players and by AC Milan president and former Italian prime minister Silvio Berlusconi. &ldquo;This is an uncivilized problem that needs to be stopped,&rdquo; said Berlusconi, enjoying a rare moment on moral high ground. Such boorish behaviour is &ldquo;giving Italy a negative image,&rdquo; he said. </p>
 
 <p>Who&rsquo;re you calling minor? </p>
 
 <p>Emma Watson may be known for her youthful good looks, but this is a bit much. The <em>Harry Potter</em> star was singled out at New York&rsquo;s JFK airport where officials, thinking she was under 12, told her she should be in the company of an adult. The actor&rsquo;s tweet about the incident had the hashtag: &ldquo;#neverwearingbackpackagain.&rdquo; Watson was returning to the U.S. to continue studies at Brown University after a stint in Zambia with the British charity Camfed. &ldquo;The really sad thing is that this is not the first time this has happened,&rdquo; she added. </p>
 
 <p>Welcome to Clowntown </p>
 
 <p>How low have things sunk in Toronto the good? Low enough for the city to get momentarily excited last week at the idea of mayor Jos&eacute; Canseco. Like most absurdities these days it started on Twitter, with the 48-year-old former baseball slugger&mdash;now better known for his reality TV appearances and train-wreck personal life&mdash;listing a run for elected office as a goal for 2013. When someone pointed out that current Mayor Rob Ford may soon be forced by the courts to step down, Canseco declared an immediate interest. After all, he enjoyed one pretty decent (if steroid-fuelled) season with the Blue Jays back in 1998. Sadly, the fantasy didn&rsquo;t even last a full news cycle. Turns out you actually have to be a Canadian citizen to run the country&rsquo;s biggest city, a no-way-Jos&eacute; hurdle for the Cuban-born American. </p>
 
 <p>Courting controversy </p>
 
 <p>After being awarded two Purple Hearts during the Vietnam War and surviving a dozen years in the U.S. Senate, Republican Chuck Hagel is girding for what could be his biggest battle yet: being confirmed as the next U.S. secretary of defence. Politicians on the left have attacked him for controversial comments about gays, while the right believes he&rsquo;s anti-Israel. His fellow nominee, counterterrorism adviser John Brennan, will likely have an equally tough fight to be approved as the new CIA chief. Brennan, a 25-year CIA veteran, is the key architect of the U.S.&rsquo;s precision drone strategy, which has transformed counterterrorism&mdash;and attracted plenty of controversy. </p>
 
 <p>Millionaire street cleaner </p>
 
 <p>After scores of stories of China&rsquo;s elite blowing fortunes on fast cars and parties comes a tale almost too good to be true. Yu Youzhen, 53, is a millionaire who prefers rags to riches. Though she&rsquo;s amassed a $1.5-million property portfolio, Yu still works six days a week as a sanitation worker, earning $225 a month. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t want to sit around idly and eat away my fortune,&rdquo; Yu told the local <em>Wuhan Evening News</em>. &ldquo;I want to be a role model for my son and daughter.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>New ink </p>
 
 <p>Days after being photographed smoking something that looked suspiciously like a joint, Justin Bieber got another tattoo, this time a profile of an Aboriginal in headdress. It&rsquo;s the logo of the junior hockey team in his hometown of Stratford, Ont. While detractors believe such depictions are racist, the pop star showed no qualms, sharing the picture on social media with an explanation: &ldquo;My grandfather always took me to the stratford culliton every friday night this is for u Grampa.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Have Kreek, will paddle</p>
 
 <p>After being part of the Canadian men&rsquo;s eight rowing crew that won Olympic gold in Beijing in 2008, the question arose for Victoria&rsquo;s Adam Kreek: what to do for an encore? Kreek, a self-confessed &ldquo;type A&rdquo; personality, decided to row some 6,800 km across the Atlantic. He and three crewmates&mdash;Markus Pukonen of Tofino, B.C., and Jordan Hanssen and Pat Fleming, both of Seattle&mdash;depart in mid-January from Senegal, weather permitting. The row to Miami is expected to take 60 to 100 days, and test the endurance and camaraderie of four big men jammed into the 8.8-metre boat. They&rsquo;ll row 24/7, sleeping in shifts and blogging. The crew and their lead sponsor, the Canadian Wildlife Federation, hope to raise awareness about the state of the world&rsquo;s oceans. Kreek calls rowing a lifelong passion. &ldquo;This is something that I can actually do until I croak,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve known countless people who&rsquo;ve died on the water, it&rsquo;s kind of a romantic way to go&mdash;not that I want to do that on this ocean row certainly.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 <p>Gramps takes the long view </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m feeling very old,&rdquo; joked Prince Charles at the notion of becoming a grandfather. The prospect also has the outspoken environmentalist worried about the health of the world the child of William and Kate may inherit, he told ITV&rsquo;s<em> This Morning</em>. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t want to be confronted by my future grandchild and [have] them say: &lsquo;Why didn&rsquo;t you do something?&rsquo; &rdquo; he said. &ldquo;It makes it ever more obvious to try and make sure we leave them something that isn&rsquo;t a total poisoned chalice.&rdquo; He also worries about his other son, Prince Harry, an Apache helicopter pilot serving in Afghanistan. &ldquo;If you are a parent or relation to a loved one and that person is away in these incredibly dangerous and challenging circumstances I know you worry all the time,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;But he loves doing what he&rsquo;s doing and he&rsquo;s brilliant at it.&rdquo;</p>
 
  <p>Trekkies delight </p>
 
 <p>William Shatner has never actually been to space, but he&rsquo;s friendly to those who have: the legendary actor struck up a conversation on Twitter with fellow Canadian Chris Hadfield, an astronaut on the International Space Station. In response to Shatner&rsquo;s question &ldquo;are you tweeting from space?&rdquo; Hadfield responded by imitating Scotty from Star Trek&mdash;&ldquo;Standard orbit, Captain,&rdquo; to the delight of Shatner and Trek fans, who celebrated the melding of a fake spaceman and a real one. The next day, though, Hadfield had second thoughts about his new-found connection with <em>Star Trek.</em> Pointing to a picture of himself in the space station, he wrote that he was &ldquo;starting to question wearing this red shirt.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 <p>Polley takes the prize </p>
 
 <p>It takes courage to uproot the accepted &ldquo;truths&rdquo; and mysteries of your own family, but Canadian filmmaker Sarah Polley&rsquo;s documentary inquiry into the tangled secrets of her home life&mdash;<em>Stories We Tell</em>&mdash;is a triumph of the form. On Jan. 8, the toughest audience in any theatre&mdash;the Toronto Film Critics Association&mdash;awarded her the Rogers Best Canadian Film Award. The $100,000 prize, newly endowed by Rogers Communications Inc., is the richest arts award in Canada. Runners up were Denis C&ocirc;t&eacute;, who directed <em>Bestiaire,</em> and Michael Dowse, for <em>Goon</em>. <em>Phil Lind</em>, vice-chairman of Rogers Communications, called Polley&rsquo;s film &ldquo;a thoroughly engaging and interesting depiction of her own family and its stories.&rdquo;</p>
 
  <p>Less than 10 years</p>
  
  <p>With hockey&rsquo;s return, two of Canada&rsquo;s biggest NHL markets are fixating on one man: Roberto Luongo. The Vancouver goaltender won gold for Canada, but has a nasty habit of choking under the pressure of the NHL playoffs. Last year, the former Canuck captain lost his starting job to backup Cory Schneider, and has 10 years left on his US$64-million contract. Rumours that a trade to Toronto is close have been brewing since fall. On hearing about the end to the NHL lockout, Luongo tweeted, &ldquo;So WTF do we do now?&rdquo; Luongo, who has a no-trade clause on his contract, told the <em>Toronto Sun </em>this week that he has given Vancouver Canucks GM Mike Gillis the green light to trade him, adding that the Leafs are &ldquo;obviously part of the equation.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 <p>Pretty convenient, actually </p>
 <p>Al Gore couldn&rsquo;t get anyone to watch his Current TV channel, but when it comes to getting cable companies to buy and carry it, he&rsquo;s a master. The former U.S. VP sold his struggling cable channel to Al Jazeera for a reported $500 million last week, and then personally went to cable providers to inform them their contract called for carrying a &ldquo;news channel,&rdquo; and that they&rsquo;re still on the hook even though the owner changed. One person not impressed is Glenn Beck, whose bid for Current was shot down. Beck&rsquo;s website, <em>The Blaze,</em> announced this was proof Gore&rsquo;s organization &ldquo;aligns itself with Al Jazeera.&rdquo; 
</p>
 
 
 
 <p>Saying a prayer for him As Hugo Ch&aacute;vez battles a severe respiratory infection after cancer surgery, Venezuelans recite the rosary in front of his picture, worried about the political fallout if he can&rsquo;t continue as president.</p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Opinion</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 
 <slug>Math Phobia </slug>
 <hedline>the tyrrany of the mad minute</hedline>
 
  <byline>Emma Teitel</byline>

 </body.head>
 
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_TEITEL01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Call me a &lsquo;word person&rsquo;: Old-time, hard-core math drills and testing are still revered</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Stockbyte/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Tori Spelling&rsquo;s resolution for 2013 is to get back into her skinny jeans. Wyclef Jean&rsquo;s is to never again remain silent in the face of violence because it&rsquo;s &ldquo;a scar on the world&rsquo;s cheek.&rdquo; Mine might be more ambitious than both: I am going to learn how to add. In my life, this is anything but a trivial endeavour. I happen to be innumerate&mdash;which means I do not, and cannot, do simple math. In fact, I avoid it at all costs. Literally. I&rsquo;d rather pay the whole dinner bill than try to calculate the tip. </p>
 
 <p>There are many people like me, some of whom may be reading this column: otherwise seemingly well-adjusted members of society who hand the cashier a $20 bill for a coffee when they have exact change, or never bother to count the change when the cashier hands it back because they doubt they&rsquo;d be able to determine if there was an error. And besides, it would take so long that everyone in line behind them would probably leave the store. (For innumerates, the fear of attempting math is compounded by the fear they&rsquo;ll hold up the line indefinitely if they do attempt it.) </p>
 
 <p>One recent American study found that for math-phobic people, the anticipation of numerical computation actually triggers a brain reflex commonly associated with pain. According to a recent report in Britain&rsquo;s Independent, &ldquo;the number of [British] adults who have numeracy skills no better than those expected of an 11-year-old has shot up from 15 million to 17 million&mdash;49 per cent of the adult population&mdash;in the last eight years.&rdquo; That&rsquo;s a lot of pain, and a lot of self-defeating, ironic surrender. The last time I took math was in the 10th grade. It was a remedial class called personal finance, where the only reason anyone touched a calculator was to steal the batteries. </p>
 
 <p>But the black humour hides the true trauma and stigma of math phobia. For some reason, illiteracy is considered a legitimate deficit, while innumeracy is seen as a punchline condition, the kind of gap girls develop because they can&rsquo;t be bothered to be logical. &nbsp;Not only is this nonsense, it obscures the thing that for me was the root of math phobia: the idea that the best way to teach someone something that has concrete right and wrong answers is to make a &ldquo;game&rdquo; of it. My first (and fatal) brush with this theory came in the second grade during a drill called &ldquo;Mad Minute&rdquo;&mdash;also a pre-First World War phrase used, fittingly, by British riflemen to describe the attempt to hit a 12-inch target 15 times in 60 seconds. It was a class-wide competition in mathematical speed and ability. Every student got a sheet of paper with a series of problems on it. The object was to answer as many problems as you could in one minute: one deafeningly silent and scary minute, monitored by a stopwatch on the teacher&rsquo;s desk. I cheated every single time, because I was so anxious, I could barely think&mdash;so I&rsquo;d look over Marley&rsquo;s shoulder (thank you, Marley, wherever you are) and write down her subtraction answers. Marley was smart. I got by. But Marley was more than smart; she enjoyed Mad Minute. Not me. Why? </p>
 
 <p>There&rsquo;s a common misconception, from academia to action movies, that stress breeds success; that you&rsquo;ll be a better problem-solver if you know an asteroid is heading straight for Earth or, in my case, you only have one minute to prove that you don&rsquo;t suck at long division. The problem is, however, that when you do suck at long division, pressure doesn&rsquo;t help your performance. It hinders it, to a point of near paralysis. Yet the Mad Minute approach to math, old-time, hard-core drills and testing, is still very much revered. According to a 2009 academic evaluation of 15-year-old students called the Programme for International Student Assessment, Canada ranks 10th worldwide in math, and many people assume the countries that outrank us&mdash;China is one&mdash;do so because they use the traditional, high-intensity drill method. People forget, though, that in some cases, these countries remove &ldquo;unessential&rdquo; programming from school curriculae, like sports and theatre, in order to focus entirely on academics&mdash;math, in particular. They also gloss over the fact that Finland, a country that also outranks us in math, doesn&rsquo;t put its students through standardized tests until they hit high school, and is significantly lighter on homework. </p>
 
 <p>Myself, I pretty much decided, from the day of my first Mad Minute onward, that I was a word person, not a math person, and word people just aren&rsquo;t good at math. But I decided I was a &ldquo;word person,&rdquo; not so much because I loved to read and write, but because, in English and history class, I didn&rsquo;t feel pressure to perform. There were no one-minute intelligence contests in English class. There were only open-ended questions, sometimes with more than one right answer.&nbsp;I could play the game of sentences and stories, but no one taught me how to navigate the game with sums and remainders. Which is how I stand before you today, a 23-year-old woman who finds herself determined to learn how to count her change before the store closes.</p>
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Interview</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Social Anthropology </slug>
 <hedline>Traditional societies&mdash;good and bad&mdash;and what we might learn about conflict resolution </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Jared Diamond in conversation with Brian Bethune</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC53_INTERVIEW02.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.byline>photographs by Roman Cho/Getty Images</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>The eminent American geographer Jared Diamond, 75, has spent two decades exploring the question of how human societies have interacted with their environments and resources. His Pulitzer prize-winning <em>Guns, Germs and Steel</em> (1997) discussed the natural advantages available to the cultures that arose on the Eurasian land mass, while <em>Collapse</em> examined how various societies&mdash;which may yet include our own&mdash;made bad decisions in response to the environmental hands they were dealt. Now, in his newly published <em>The World Until Yesterday</em>, Diamond considers whether the practices derived from the way all humans once lived still provide valuable lessons for the modern world. </p>
 
 <em>Q: Are you arguing that humans have not yet adjusted to the way we now live, emotionally, psychologically and physically? </em>
 <p>A: Physically, it&rsquo;s clear: we have not. Differences to which we have not adjusted include the fact our bodies still have a metabolism appropriate to a binge-and-bust diet, where often you don&rsquo;t get enough food and then when you get a feast you release lots of insulin and you store the calories as fat. That was fine for the spartan living styles of our past, but now we end up with diabetes. That&rsquo;s the clearest example of our not being adjusted physically to our current circumstances. As for emotional and psychological lags, there is speculation, but it&rsquo;s chronically difficult to separate genetic from cultural factors in human attitudes and behaviours. So I personally would not assert anything in those areas. I wouldn&rsquo;t deny the possibility, I would just say that it&rsquo;s not established. </p>
 
 <em>Q: For many people in the First World, the phrase &ldquo;traditional society&rdquo; may conjure up cows in fields and village churches. What do you mean by it? </em>
 <p>A: I mean small-scale, politically independent societies with a few hundred or at most a few thousand people, even if they are farmers rather than strictly hunters and gatherers&mdash;cultures such as existed throughout human history before the rise of states about 5,400 years ago. You still have traditional societies today in New Guinea and the Amazon, but there are also elements of those ways of life even in modern America and Canada. </p>
 
 <em>Q: These would be aspects of life in which social rules trump the letter of the law? </em>
 <p>A: My wife and kids and I spend our summers in Montana, in a sparsely populated area a few hundred miles south of the Canadian border. The largest town is a few hundred people, and if you have an argument with the neighbouring rancher, the last thing you want to do is to call on the police or the courts. It&rsquo;s not just a question of your legal rights; you&rsquo;re going to be living next door to that rancher for the next 50 years, and you&rsquo;d better get along with him. That&rsquo;s one example of traditional societies existing within our modern states. Another example that I noticed when I first visited Europe in 1950 was that rural areas of Britain and Germany were still very traditional in that people didn&rsquo;t move out of them very much, and disputes were settled privately rather than by bringing in police and lawyers. </p>
 
 <em>Q: You find much to admire in traditional dispute resolution, especially the emotional closure you described in the New Guinea case where a man accidentally ran over a boy. </em>
 <p>A: Yes and no. Sorry&mdash;people, when they ask me questions, frequently end up with the impression that whatever you ask Jared, his answer will be &ldquo;Yes and no.&rdquo; In the case of Mallow and Billy, for the individuals involved, yes, there was satisfactory emotional closure, which there certainly is not if you have a fatal traffic accident in the United States. But there are also advantages to state justice in establishing precedents and increasing safety that cannot come from an individual case. </p>
 
 <em>Q: But the delays inherent in state justice and its indifference to the feelings of the people involved are avoided. </em>
 <p>A: One can debate&mdash;because there are numerous bad features to our justice system&mdash;which is the worst. When I point out the advantages of the quick resolution in Billy and Mallow&rsquo;s case, lawyers come back to me and say, &ldquo;Yeah, but if it had not been successfully resolved it would have gone to war between the families, and in traditional societies wars can go on for generations,&rdquo; which is true. Yet the emotional closure is so important to us. One of my high school classmates lost his sister to murderers 50 years ago. The murderers were sent to prison, but my friend still harbours anger at them&mdash;there was no emotional closure. I&rsquo;m not saying one system is entirely better than the other, just that there are traditional elements&mdash;restorative justice, so to speak&mdash;that we should look at now. </p>
 
 <em>Q: That&rsquo;s not the case, though, with many aspects of traditional life. </em>
 <p>A: Absolutely. A prime example of that is that traditionally, throughout human history, women were bought. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s a good idea today. People waged war because there wasn&rsquo;t a centralized government to end the violence. That isn&rsquo;t a good idea. A mother, after giving birth, would inspect her baby, and if the baby had problems at birth she was expected to kill the baby. Well, if that was the case, my children would not have survived. I don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s a good idea. Yet in most situations it was so difficult&mdash;verging on impossible&mdash;to rear a sickly child or even twins. </p>
 
 <em>Q: You are sometimes accused of being an environmental determinist, as Mitt Romney suggested on his ill-fated tour of the world. How do you respond? </em>
 <p>A: I get it fairly often as a one-liner. Some anthropologists and historians bristle at environmental explanations of any sort, because they seem to diminish human agency. That seems to me a poor formulation. There can be no doubt that the environment has some big effects on human societies, even though there are things other than the environment in play. The cultural difference between Canadian and U.S. society today can&rsquo;t be interpreted in terms of the lower temperatures in Canada. But at the same time, I&rsquo;m sure Canadians in Nunavut don&rsquo;t go around naked. Is it environmental determinism to say that people have to wear clothes in cold climates, or make hard decisions about who gets what in resource-poor areas, or is the claim just a refusal to engage with the complexity of the situation? </p>
 
 <em>Q: It&rsquo;s impossible to ignore the environmental factors involved in the ruthless population control that marks most traditional cultures. Among the !Kung people, for example, it was entirely up to the mother whether her newborn would live or die, a parallel of a sort to modern abortion rules. </em>
 <p>A: That&rsquo;s a good example of something that horrifies us today, but in traditional situations, what on Earth are they supposed to do when they&rsquo;re not going to succeed in bringing up a damaged child or two babies? There isn&rsquo;t surplus food, and there aren&rsquo;t doctors who can help. It&rsquo;s the same situation with the elderly, which also shows immense variation, and is also tied to the resources available. There are societies where adult children will pre-chew food for the old, but I also related that gripping story among the Siriono Indians, of the old woman who was left behind when the group went on, and her husband didn&rsquo;t even say goodbye to her, and it feels just horrible. Well, what are you supposed to do if you&rsquo;re a nomadic hunter-gatherer and you&rsquo;ve got other stuff to carry and you simply can&rsquo;t bring along an old person unable to walk? There just isn&rsquo;t the choice. That&rsquo;s an interesting example because many of us&mdash;maybe most of us today&mdash;are going to find ourselves in similar circumstances when our own parents get frail, and if they don&rsquo;t have the good fortune suddenly to keel over with a heart attack, it&rsquo;s the adult children who are going to be asked by the doctor, &ldquo;Well, do you want me to resort to all measures possible, or should I just give palliative care, or take your old mother off life support?&rdquo; </p>
 
 <em>Q: Yet, on the whole, once children were accepted into their groups, did you find evidence of their greater emotional security and social confidence in traditional societies? </em>
 <p>A: That&rsquo;s been my impression, and something I frequently hear from anthropologists. There is enormous variation in attitudes, of course, with some cultures far stricter than modern America, and some&mdash;I&rsquo;d say the majority&mdash;far more laissez-faire. One factor is what is around for kids to harm: if a child, by mistake, can leave open a pasture gate and valuable cows wander away, then you want to be really sure that the kid is not going to make that mistake. In New Guinea I&rsquo;ve always been struck by the fact that the children are more self-assured and self-con&#64257;dent than modern American children, and, as children, make their own decisions at a younger age. </p>
 
 <em>Q: Humans are social creatures and bonds are tight in traditional societies. You also quoted a New Guinean professional woman saying the greatest thing about America was the anonymity. </em>
 <p>A: Yeah, she appreciated the fact that she could read a newspaper in a caf&eacute; and not be bothered by relatives and clanspeople asking for help. </p>
 
 <em>Q: So loneliness is also solitude and privacy. We&rsquo;re complicated creatures, we want both. </em>
 <p>A: That&rsquo;s right. And that illustrates that we should neither despise nor idealize traditional societies. </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>National</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 
 <slug>Politics </slug>
 
 <hedline>Idol no More?</hedline>
 <abstract>Little is known about Chief Spence, which suits her supporters and critics just fine</abstract>
 
 <byline>Nick Taylor-Vaisey</byline>
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_SPENCE01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Hunger strike: Spence&rsquo;s protest began on Dec. 11 in order to force a meeting with Harper</photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Chris Wattie/Reuters</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Until a few weeks ago Theresa Spence was the chief of a remote, impoverished reserve called Attawapiskat. At 49, Spence had a history in child care work, and briefly made headlines last year when her community faced a housing crisis as winter beckoned. Beyond these few details, though, little was known, which ultimately didn&rsquo;t matter when the hunger-striking chief emerged slowly from her teepee on an island in the middle of the Ottawa River, tired and somewhat stooped, to deliver a shocking statement to the outside world about how far she was prepared to take her protest: &ldquo;I&rsquo;ll die for my people.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Spence&rsquo;s protest on Victoria Island has galvanized activists, scored points with opposition politicians, not to mention a pair of former prime ministers, and forced Aboriginal issues into the headlines almost every day since she stopped eating on Dec. 11. </p>
 
 <p>But the woman widely credited by supporters and critics alike for securing a meeting between the government and Aboriginal leaders&mdash;a gathering set to take place Friday&mdash;remains, for the most part, a mystery. Few outside those immediately close to her know much about her past, and her record as Attawapiskat&rsquo;s chief is spotty. In the absence of a clearer picture of her background, flaws and accomplishments, this has allowed supporters and critics to read what they want into her personal history to support their positions in the passionate, often inflamed debate over Canada&rsquo;s relationship with its Aboriginals. She&rsquo;s praised by those agitating for change under the Idle No More banner as something of a spiritual leader, a fearless campaigner who has stared down a hostile federal government, while her critics deride Spence as an incompetent administrator who has used her hunger strike to deflect attention from financial mismanagement on her reserve. </p>
 
 <p>Most of what is known of Spence can be traced to the intense media coverage of the tiny reserve she administers. She was elected chief of the Attawapiskat band on Aug. 27, 2010, after stints as deputy chief, councillor, a member of the local development corporation, and manager of local daycare. Few could find Attawapiskat on a map before Oct. 28, 2011. That was the day Spence called on the Ontario government to declare a state of emergency in her community of 1,800&mdash;a plea that prompted dozens of reporters to helicopter in from southern locales. Deplorable housing had made the reserve virtually unlivable for many of its residents, Spence said at the time. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re in a Third World situation. It&rsquo;s not improving, so it&rsquo;s time for both [federal and provincial] governments to recognize and work with us,&rdquo; she said. NDP MP Charlie Angus, who represents the area, didn&rsquo;t mince words: &ldquo;If something doesn&rsquo;t happen, someone will die.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The federal government did step in, of course. Aboriginal Affairs Minister John Duncan ordered two dozen modular homes to Attawapiskat, along with a third-party manager to ensure funds were properly administered. Spence fought the move, arguing the band could manage its own spending, and by the time Duncan announced he was &ldquo;very pleased&rdquo; with the results and withdrew the outside manager last April, the band had already challenged him in court&mdash;a case the band won. But for the most part, this round of the standoff between Spence and Ottawa played out away from the cameras. That would soon change. </p>
 
 <p>The rapid spread of Idle No More, starting in early December, provided an opportunity for Spence to once again grab the spotlight. The movement, kicked off by four Aboriginal women in Saskatchewan, was ostensibly over the federal government&rsquo;s omnibus budget legislation Bill C-45, and its changes to rules governing environmental assessments of waterways and the leasing of Aboriginal lands, but by the time a Day of Action was declared for Dec. 10, its goals had grown amorphous. On that day, Spence told reporters on Parliament Hill she would not wait a day longer for federal action in Attawapiskat and was resorting to desperate measures. The next day, she began her hunger strike. </p>
 
 <p>The chief&rsquo;s month without food has been de&#64257;ned as much by the &#64258;urry of activity and comments made outside Spence&rsquo;s teepee as anything she&rsquo;s done within. As if by script, stories have abounded of people travelling from afar to meet Spence&mdash;one couple from Cape Breton drove through a crippling snowstorm for a mere 20-minute audience. Carolyn Buffalo, a former chief of Montana First Nation in Alberta, has even compared Spence to Mahatma Gandhi. </p>
 
 <p>Spence&rsquo;s ordeal presented too valuable an opportunity for critics of Stephen Harper&rsquo;s government to pass up. She&rsquo;s counted among her visitors a pair of Liberal leadership candidates, Justin Trudeau and Marc Garneau, and a long list of NDP MPs that&rsquo;s perhaps most notable for the absence of leader Thomas Mulcair. She also found former prime ministers Joe Clark and Paul Martin at her door. Over the Christmas holidays, she even lured a taste of Hollywood star power when actor Adam Beach, who once starred in Clint Eastwood&rsquo;s <em>Flags of our Fathers</em> and now fronts CBC&rsquo;s <em>Arctic Air</em>, spent some time in Spence&rsquo;s teepee. </p>
 
 <p>In every case, her political guests have been deferential, despite their lack of any real knowledge about her background and circumstances. Veteran Liberal MP John McCallum joined a group of Liberal and NDP colleagues who met the chief on Dec. 30. When he walked out of the teepee, reporters asked what his message was to Spence. &ldquo;We come in solidarity and in support,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;We don&rsquo;t tell her what to do.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>There have been critical questions put to her visitors&mdash;was her protest an attempt to blackmail the Prime Minister? Was it really wise to sacrifice her own health?&mdash;but opposition politicians and the rest of her supporters have continued to treat her as beyond reproach. </p>
 
 <p>For this reason, Spence has proved a powerful and elusive target for the Harper government throughout her hunger strike. On the one hand, he couldn&rsquo;t grant a meeting directly between himself and Spence&mdash;though she later backed away from that demand and instead called for a meeting between the Prime Minister, the Governor General and Aboriginal leaders. Even this posed a problem, because of the precedent it set for copycats. On the other hand, what if Spence actually followed through on her threat, and died in her teepee? </p>
 
 <p>Harper&rsquo;s way out emerged when Shawn Atleo, the Assembly of First Nations national chief, called for a meeting of his own with Harper for the end of January, the anniversary of last year&rsquo;s Crown-First Nations gathering. Harper, who was at the Ford plant in Oakville, Ont., for an auto funding announcement, agreed to the meeting and while moving up the date, he presented it as a follow-up meeting without making any mention of Attawapiskat&rsquo;s chief. </p>
 
 <p>To Spence&rsquo;s supporters, the very fact she was able to force Harper to attend any meeting with Aboriginal leaders has been framed as a victory, though she has refrained from calling it that herself. Instead, Spence has vowed to continue her hunger strike until it is clear what the outcome of Friday&rsquo;s meeting will have been. </p>
 
 <p>But Harper&rsquo;s reversal on the issue also brought with it an opportunity Spence&rsquo;s critics were waiting for&mdash;and they have quickly moved to fill in the gaps in her narrative. Some have bluntly questioned the threat posed by Spence&rsquo;s hunger strike, with the <em>National Post</em>&rsquo;s Barbara Kay calling her survival on fish broth more a &ldquo;detox diet&rdquo; that wouldn&rsquo;t do much to harm her health. More crucial to Spence&rsquo;s continued influence, critics have painted her at best as a native leader overwhelmed by her job&rsquo;s demands, while raising serious questions about her decision to hire her partner, Clayton Kennedy, to be Attawapisakt&rsquo;s co-manager. Ironically, the social media tools like Twitter that enabled the Idle No More movement to spread so quickly have also proved potentially lethal to her reputation. A year-old CBC report resurfaced online just days before the meeting with Harper in which Spence appears both evasive and defensive when probed about brand new houses sitting empty on her reserve while donated supplies piled up in storage. By the time the results of a damning audit into Attawapiskat&rsquo;s books were leaked to journalists earlier this week, showing the band had not properly accounted for millions of dollars in federal spending dating back to 2005, it was Spence&rsquo;s critics who were claiming victory. </p>
 
 <p>Even after the meeting between Harper and Aboriginal leaders&mdash;as well as Spence if she chooses to attend&mdash;wraps up, it&rsquo;s a safe bet the Attawapiskat chief will remain Idle No More&rsquo;s most divisive figure. How she fares in the weeks to come is unclear. That her biography remains mostly blank after so much scrutiny means the meeting could define her time in the national spotlight. Whether it&rsquo;s as revered heroine or forgotten hunger striker, though, depends largely on forces beyond her control. </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>National</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>British Columbia </slug>
 <hedline>And how will you be paying? </hedline>
 
 <abstract>When skiers get in trouble, everyone wants to bill them for their rescue. Everyone, that is, except the rescuers.</abstract>
 
  <byline>Charlie Gillis</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_BCRESCUE01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Expensive rescue: Helicopters can cost up to $3,000 an hour</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>JOHN LEHMANN/CP</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>The snowboarder was suitably chastened when he returned to warmth and safety. He thanked his rescuers, and voiced remorse for straying out of bounds on Cypress Mountain, forcing crews to pluck him from a snowy ravine near North Vancouver, B.C. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ll never do it again,&rdquo; said the 30-year-old, whose name the rescue team tactfully withheld. &ldquo;Nobody should.&rdquo; But for some, the apology didn&rsquo;t cut it. After three high-risk rescues in the area in three weeks, the familiar demand that wayward adventurers start paying the cost of their own salvation gained renewed traction in B.C., where more than half of Canada&rsquo;s emergency searches take place each year. </p>
 
 <p>Make that four rescues. On Sunday, volunteers with the North Shore Search and Rescue team were back among the firs&mdash;this time to save a snowshoer who had fallen and suffered a head injury on nearby Hollyburn Mountain. All three of the previous rescuees were people who had deliberately strayed from delineated ski zones&mdash;a fact that further stoked public ire. Angry citizens lit up the lines on call-in shows, while the <em>Vancouver Sun</em> published an editorial decrying the &ldquo;cost and risk to the brave volunteers who donate their time and expertise to help people in trouble.&rdquo; Operators of the Cypress Mountain ski resort actually billed one of the snowboarders, 33-year-old Sebastien Boucher, $10,000 for its part in a three-day search that ended with his miraculous rescue. </p>
 
 <p>But generally, the big-ticket expenses don&rsquo;t fall to the adventurers, or to the rescue teams themselves, which are staffed mainly by well-trained volunteers. Those bills are forwarded to the provincial government, which treats them as the price of B.C.&rsquo;s thriving trade in outdoor recreation. But the price can be dear. Helicopters alone can cost about $3,000 per hour, and it&rsquo;s not uncommon for a single search to run more than $100,000. </p>
 
 <p>Still, rescue organizations oppose the idea of billing or fining those who require their services. Don Bindon, president of the B.C. Search and Rescue Association, worries that fear of a hefty fine would discourage people from calling for help. Worse still, he says, is the prospect of family members or friends trying to rescue loved ones in order to avoid a punishing bill: &ldquo;Then we&rsquo;ve got a whole pile of amateurs up on a hill. We want people to phone us. We don&rsquo;t want them to wait, and we don&rsquo;t want their friends to go get them.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Invoicing rescuees could also place safety organizations in the awkward position of providing evidence against thrill-seekers who defy public warnings, says Mary Clayton, spokeswoman for the Canadian Avalanche Centre in Revelstoke, B.C. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re wary of pointing fingers, except in cases where people are clearly unprepared and negligent,&rdquo; she says. Instead, the group advocates for better education about avalanche risk, and the need to take proper equipment into the back country. That might not save the worst risk-takers from their own stupidity. But it would cut down on the workload for rescue crews. And that, presumably, would free up time and resources to help those who&rsquo;ve done nothing worse than make an honest mistake. </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>National</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>profile </slug>
 <hedline>Going on the offensive </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Why, oh why does <em>he</em> have to keep winning?</abstract>
 
 <byline>Jonathon Gatehouse</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_EZRALEVANT02.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Blunt talk: Levant&rsquo;s on-air diatribes have forced his bosses to apologize more than once</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Photograph by Christopher Wahl</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Ezra Levant is retelling his favourite story: the one where he&rsquo;s the hero. However, the hour-long monologue about the plucky kid from Alberta who dares to speak truth to power is really more of a dramatic performance. Pacing the stage of a community theatre north of Toronto, the 40-year-old broadcaster, author and columnist darts and cringes, waving his arms and pulling faces as he unspools a tale of fascist clerics, zombie bureaucrats and holy free-speech warriors. Levant&rsquo;s version of his battle with the Alberta Human Rights Commission over his 2006 decision to publish controversial drawings of the Prophet Muhammad in his now-defunct <em>Western Standard</em> magazine is epic stuff, filled with references to his &ldquo;ordeal,&rdquo; &ldquo;interrogation&rdquo; and &ldquo;900-day trial.&rdquo; And more than enough broadsides to satisfy an audience of 200 who have paid $25 per grey head to hear the closest thing that Canada has to Glenn Beck or Rush Limbaugh lecture on &ldquo;Political correctness and the rise of Islamism.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;I showed the cartoons like a prosecutor would present evidence, so people could make up their own minds. We&rsquo;re all adults in this country,&rdquo; he proclaims, voice rising to an excited register that makes him sound uncannily like Shaggy from<em> Scooby Doo</em>. But somehow, he says, that was all lost on the Calgary imam, who took offence to seeing the founder of his religion depicted wearing a bomb as a turban, and filed a formal complaint. &ldquo;He was <em>madrasa</em>-educated. He came from Pakistan, with those medieval values, those censorship values, those burn-it-down values.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>There are murmurs and nods of agreement in the house. Then comes the bait-and-switch moment. Speaking at an event sponsored by the Jewish women&rsquo;s group Hadassah, where the evening&rsquo;s proceeds are all going to fund relief work in Israel, Levant suddenly rounds and bites the hand that has laid out the impressive dessert table that waits in lobby. The people to blame for the &ldquo;illiberal and un-Canadian&rdquo; human rights laws and tribunals he&rsquo;s been crusading against for the past seven years are well-represented in the theatre. &ldquo;It came from us. I mean the Jews, my friends.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The temperature of the room immediately drops a few degrees, but the sweating man on stage doesn&rsquo;t seem too concerned. After all, causing offence is his calling card. For 20 years&mdash;first as a political operative, then editorialist, publisher, and now as what he calls an &ldquo;activist journalist&rdquo;&mdash;Levant has been a purveyor of strong, sometimes objectionable opinions, most often delivered in windy torrents where the invective falls like rain. Relentless, full-frontal assaults that are &ldquo;so obsessional,&rdquo; a former colleague recently noted in the pages of the <em>National Post</em>, &ldquo;that it sometimes seems like a manifestation of clinical mental illness.&rdquo; A lawyer by training, he displays none of the caution of the trade, attracting defamation and libel suits like a magnet, and frequently responding in kind. (He says he has lost track of how many his legal representatives are currently fighting.) And even when he is forced to apologize, it&rsquo;s hard to detect any real regret or contrition. </p>
 
 <p>But what really drives his opponents&mdash;or if you prefer, victims&mdash;wild is how often he achieves his goals. Even though the Calgary imam eventually withdrew his complaint, and the Alberta body dismissed another similar case against him, Levant refused to let the matter drop. He turned his experiences into a successful 2009 book, <em>Shakedown: How Our Government is Undermining Democracy in the Name of Human Rights</em>, and then took the show on the road, forcing the discussion. And now that Ottawa and the provinces are slowly backing away from legal limits on free expression, he is loudly proclaiming victory. His spirited 2010 defence of Alberta&rsquo;s oil sands, <em>Ethical Oil</em>, became a national best-seller and provided a blueprint that federal bureaucrats, diplomats and even the Prime Minister have been following to counter pressure campaigns from environmental groups. And the broadcaster also claims to have had a direct hand in the foreign policy shift that has seen Canada abandon its fence-straddling role in the Middle East in favour of full-throated support of Israel. He&rsquo;s in increasing demand as a speaker, whether it&rsquo;s the free talks for community groups or the corporate gigs that net him between $5,000 and $10,000 a pop. There&rsquo;s another book, <em>Groundswell</em>&mdash;he refuses to discuss what it&rsquo;s about&mdash;coming this fall. And his daily one-hour rant-fest on Sun TV provides a bigger platform than he&rsquo;s ever enjoyed before. </p>
 
 <p>Some of that surely impresses the crowd he&rsquo;s haranguing this cool November night, but Levant is more interested in making his point than making friends. As the audience fidgets, he careens down yet another verbal alley, pulling the names of ancient neo-Nazis and details of their street-corner anti-Semitism from memory. In the years after the Holocaust, it was the Jewish community&rsquo;s obsession with creating a legal framework to punish these &ldquo;schmucks and losers&rdquo; that has led Canada to where it is today. A place, Levant contends, where fundamental freedoms are under attack from waves of newer immigrants with less tolerant outlooks who use publicly funded bodies and the courts to wage their own &ldquo;soft jihad.&rdquo; The solution he offers is simple: dismantle it all, and let everyone have their say, no matter how hurtful or offensive. &ldquo;You cannot pass a law just for your own team,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;If we want freedom of speech, it&rsquo;s the one gift that we have to give to our opponents.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Or as much as it might pain so many Canadians, even to Ezra Levant. </p>
 
 <p>IT&rsquo;S A BREAK period for <em>The Source,</em> the five-day-a-week, hour-long opinion and interview show he hosts for Sun News Network, so Levant has ditched the suit and tie in favour of jeans and a bright orange hoodie. He flops into a chair in the patriotically themed Juno Beach boardroom at the channel&rsquo;s downtown Toronto headquarters, and cracks a sugar-free Red Bull. Energy drinks are his vice of choice. &ldquo;I try to limit myself to a litre a day.&rdquo; Fuel for a show where his self-penned opening monologues&mdash;just Levant smirking at the camera and mocking whatever left-wing politician or government bureaucrat has raised his ire&mdash;sometimes last as long as 30 minutes. They&rsquo;re also a vestige of a travel schedule that might best be described as masochistic. </p>
 
 <p>When he signed on for Quebecor Media&rsquo;s Fox News facsimile in the spring of 2010, doubling down with a column for the <em>Sun </em>newspaper chain, Levant wasn&rsquo;t convinced the gig would last, so his wife and three young children stayed in Calgary. For more than a year, he would red-eye to Toronto on Sunday nights, then catch a 4 p.m. flight home on Wednesdays. After tucking the kids into bed and eating dinner with his wife, he&rsquo;d return to the airport that same evening and fly back. Then on Fridays, it was off to Calgary again for the weekend. &ldquo;I was trying to get the highest carbon footprint in the country,&rdquo; he jokes. But his days of sleeping in airplane seats are over. Feeling more secure in the job, he moved his family to Toronto last summer&mdash;although it&rsquo;s not clear whether he&rsquo;ll ever feel at home in a city that represents so much of the lefty, urban ethos he loves to rail against. </p>
 
 <p>Raised in a Calgary suburb, the second-eldest of four children born to a teacher mother and doctor father, Levant comes from a deeply conservative family. Marvin, his dad, was a member of the National Citizens&rsquo; Coalition and one of the first to hop on the Reform party bandwagon in the mid-1980s. And even as kids on the commute into the city for school each morning, he would have them listen to the CBC news and critique its bias. &ldquo;In his family, there was a good deal of attention put on politics,&rdquo; recalls Kevin Libin, a friend since childhood who later edited the <em>Western Standard</em>, and is now in charge of the <em>National Post</em>&rsquo;s news section. &ldquo;He was more attuned to what Pierre Trudeau was up to than most eight-year-olds.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>In high school, Levant wrote admiringly about Preston Manning for the student newspaper. And when he moved on to the University of Calgary in 1989 to study business, the Reform Party Club was the first organization he joined. (He also became a champion debater, partnering for a while with Naheed Nenshi, now the mayor of Calgary&mdash;although whatever friendship they had seems to be gone since Levant began denouncing him on air as &ldquo;an anti-Christian bigot.&rdquo;) He was in the grips of a profound political crush. &ldquo;Everything Preston said rang true with me. It felt like we were building something from scratch that was so noble and ideal.&rdquo; And the start-up party was more than open to letting young believers like Levant, his schoolmate Rob Anders, and friends Jason Kenney and Rahim Jaffer pitch in on the real political work. </p>
 
 <p>After graduating from the University of Alberta&rsquo;s law school in 1997, he headed to Ottawa to work for Manning, directing Reform&rsquo;s question-period strategy. Although Levant&rsquo;s in-your-face style drew media attention&mdash;he once hired a mariachi band for a protest against a Liberal senator who spent most of his time in Mexico&mdash;it also raised the ire of many of his colleagues, who quickly tired of a brash, unelected twentysomething ordering them around. There was a brief interregnum where Levant joined the editorial board of the <em>Post </em>before he returned to Ottawa in the winter of 2001 to take on the job as communications director for Stockwell Day, who had defeated Manning to take the helm of the newly formed Canadian Alliance. </p>
 
 <p>What they were looking for was someone to help them grab the headlines. &ldquo;Ezra&rsquo;s amazing. His mind works like a computer on adrenalin,&rdquo; says Logan Day, a close friend, former Hill staffer and Stockwell&rsquo;s son. But it turned out to be a little too much media attention. Day&rsquo;s leadership performance, already weak, became downright erratic as Levant, a self-confessed &ldquo;Stockaholic,&rdquo; struggled with his spin. And when Levant threatened to sue Chuck Strahl&mdash;one of his boss&rsquo;s chief critics within the party&mdash;there was open revolt. Levant was reduced to running away from TV crews, and resigned after just three months on the job. </p>
 
 <p>He returned to Calgary to lick his wounds and plan a comeback, this time as a member of Parliament. Levant captured the Alliance nomination for Calgary Southwest&mdash;Preston Manning&rsquo;s old riding&mdash;and then embarked on a jazzy billboard, radio and TV campaign targeting his Progressive Conservative opponent, Jim Prentice. But when Stephen Harper wrested the leadership away from Day in early 2002, he came looking for a safe seat. Levant, who had reportedly spent upwards of $200,000 in his bid for office, was openly hostile. And although a deal was eventually struck that allowed Harper to take his place, the spat created a lot of bad blood and negative press. </p>
 
 <p>Levant&rsquo;s rehabilitation within the movement he is so devoted to started with the creation of the <em>Western Standard</em> in 2004. Meant to fill the gap left by the demise of the right-wing journal <em>Alberta Report&mdash;</em>Levant began by purchasing their subscription list&mdash;the new magazine also harboured national ambitions. To be &ldquo;a counterweight to Canada&rsquo;s mushy, left-wing, politically correct media&mdash;the CBC and <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> magazine being the two most obvious offenders,&rdquo; he wrote at the time. </p>
 
 <p>In reality, the publication struggled to attract advertisers and expand beyond its provincial base. The controversy over the Muhammad cartoons&mdash;and the plentiful, free coverage in the rest of the media&mdash;helped, bringing in around 1,000 new subscribers, but it wasn&rsquo;t enough. In the fall of 2007, after three years of losses, he was forced to shutter its print operation. </p>
 
 <p>And if not for the Alberta Human Rights Commission, that&rsquo;s probably where the story would have ended. When formal proceedings finally got under way in January 2008, Levant was suddenly gifted with the kind of issue he had been searching for his entire political life. A video he posted on the Internet of his &ldquo;interrogation&rdquo;&mdash;in truth, a rather sedate interview by a bored-looking bureaucrat, in which Levant spent 90 minutes ridiculing her and the commission&mdash;became the conservative equivalent of the Korean parody song <em>Gangnam Style</em>. Within weeks, he was a featured guest on Glenn Beck. &ldquo;It did change his role,&rdquo; says his former <em>Standard</em> colleague Libin. &ldquo;He was sort of a conservative Turk, but there was no shortage of those. I think the cartoons made him into something different. Suddenly, he was no longer an activist. He was a man of principle.&rdquo; And after his <em>Shakedown</em> book and then his <em>Ethical Oil</em> follow-up became Canadian bestsellers, there was no denying that Levant had become a brand. And Quebecor&rsquo;s decision to make him one of their new network&rsquo;s central stars has only cemented that success. But the real question with Levant is whether his penchant for blunt talk is ultimately a talent or a curse. In his two years of employment with the <em>Sun </em>papers and network, his corporate masters have frequently been forced to apologize for his excesses. In September 2010&mdash;when the channel was still getting ready to launch&mdash;it was to American billionaire George Soros, a Holocaust survivor, for &ldquo;false statements&rdquo; Levant made in a column concerning his conduct as a teenager in Nazi-occupied Hungary. (Since then, each column has been fact-checked and lawyered before publication.) A series of December 2011 on-air attacks on the Chiquita banana company&mdash;the firm had announced it would avoid using fuel derived from the Alberta oil sands over environmental concerns&mdash;required several on-air <em>mea culpas</em>. (Levant used a coarse Spanish slur to suggest a company executive get intimate with his mother. ) And most recently, there have been regrets for a diatribe against Roma refugees&mdash;accusing them of being a &ldquo;culture synonymous with swindlers&rdquo; whose &ldquo;chief economy is theft and begging&rdquo;&mdash;that not only sparked widespread condemnation, but also a hate crime investigation by Toronto police. (Levant says police have yet to contact him.) </p>
 
 <p>And while <em>The Source</em> is the network&rsquo;s second-highest rated show, that&rsquo;s not saying much. The average fall 2012 audience for its first national airing at 5 p.m. Eastern was 4,300, and then 17,000 more for a 10 p.m. rebroadcast. <em>Power and Politics</em>, the CBC News Network show that Levant competes directly against, drew 75,500. And <em>Powerplay</em>, which occupies the same slot for CTV News Channel, captured 40,600 viewers. And with Quebecor now pressing the CRTC for &ldquo;mandatory carriage&rdquo; status for the Sun News Network&mdash;meaning cable suscribers would have to pay for it, whether they want it or not&mdash;one wonders if having such a big troublemaker on staff is a help or a hindrance. </p>
 
 <p>Ask Levant if he&rsquo;s actually sorry for saying the things his bosses have apologized for, and he chooses his words with uncharacteristic care. The opening monologue he writes for every one of his 200 shows a year runs somewhere between 2,000 and 4,000 words each, he notes. Add the on-air interviews, radio appearances, public speeches, books and columns, and his annual word count is easily in the millions. &ldquo;I regard the occasional error as a natural side effect of me generally flooring it all the time,&rdquo; he says. Press him on whether there are any such &ldquo;mistakes&rdquo; he wishes he hadn&rsquo;t made, and the contrition becomes even harder to detect. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m sure there are hundreds of things,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;But none of them weigh heavily on my mind.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Watching the obvious glee that Levant takes in causing offence&mdash;whether it&rsquo;s dressing up in costume as an Occupy protester, tangling on tape with bureaucrats, or even pricking the conceits of members of his own ethnic community from a stage&mdash;it&rsquo;s tempting to think it&rsquo;s all an act. That, like Don Cherry and his loud sportcoats, underneath it all, there lurks a more reasonable man. </p>
 
 <p>That&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m searching for as we sit in the Sun TV boardroom on a Friday afternoon. Levant is returning, yet again, to his well-worn speech on the virtues of free expression, when his cellphone rings. It&rsquo;s his wife. He tries to quickly shut down the conversation, but she has something she wants to talk about. He listens impatiently and makes a couple of distracted &ldquo;hmmm&rdquo; sounds. &ldquo;Well, that&rsquo;s why I always say security guards should be armed,&rdquo; he says, promising to call back later. It&rsquo;s only when I get outside and turn on my own phone that I realize the call was about the killings in Newtown, Conn. </p>
 
 <p>In the days that follow, it&rsquo;s a theme he takes up with vigour on his Twitter feed: how the response to 20 dead kids (who are roughly the same age as his own children) should be more, not fewer guns. It&rsquo;s not a popular position. And to many Canadians, it might be as objectionable as anything he has ever said. But being offensive is Ezra Levant&rsquo;s right&mdash;one that he has fought hard for. The thing to remember is that it&rsquo;s his business, too. </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>National</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>politics </slug>
 <hedline>Roses are orange </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Relationships between politicians and staffers used to be frowned on. A young crop of MPs is changing that.</abstract>
 
 <byline>Julie Smyth </byline>
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_NDP01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Together: Soule and NDP MP Dor&eacute; Lefebvre sought the party&rsquo;s blessing </photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Photograph by Ashley Fraser</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>It has always been taboo for MPs to date staff, but the orange wave that brought a slate of young female politicians to Ottawa has changed the dating dynamic on Parliament Hill. </p>
 
 <p>Rosane Dor&eacute; Lefebvre, a 28-year-old Quebec NDP MP, is expecting a baby with her partner, George Soule, 32, a press secretary in the Opposition leader&rsquo;s office. They kept the relationship quiet for a while, then got the party&rsquo;s blessing for their continued romance&mdash;even though there are no specific rules mandating political staff or MPs seek approval to date within the NDP, or any other party for that matter. &ldquo;Initially it was, &lsquo;Okay, this thing happened,&rsquo; and then it became more serious. I spoke to the chief of staff. We wanted this to be more than just something that we hid and I didn&rsquo;t want to do anything that would be a problem for the party,&rdquo; Soule said during an interview in Dor&eacute; Lefebvre&rsquo;s office. &ldquo;I think at the beginning I was a little bit nervous just in general about even dating an MP and what that would mean.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Such relationships have been discouraged in the past because Parliament Hill has traditionally been dominated by older male MPs and young female staff members. </p>
 
 <p>Soule and Dor&eacute; Lefebvre said they have opened the floodgates in their party and joked that an orange baby wave could be next. &ldquo;We were the trailblazers&mdash;people felt it was more comfortable: &lsquo;Well if George and Rosane could do it, then, fine, we&rsquo;re going for it,&rsquo; &rdquo; said Soule. </p>
 
 <p>Soule and Dor&eacute; Lefebvre began dating shortly after the 2011 election. They met when he helped her write her first statement in the House of Commons. Her due date is April 19, within days of the NDP convention. </p>
 
 <p>The couple found out they were having a girl in early December, the same day the government approved the Nexen deal. Soule tweeted that the most important news that day was that they were expecting a daughter. </p>
 
 <p>They have bought a house near her riding office in Laval but have no marriage plans at this stage. &ldquo;There are no rings,&rdquo; she laughed. &ldquo;So many things happened since my election. I met George. I&rsquo;m so lucky and so happy right now.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>She plans on returning to work a few weeks after giving birth so she can be in the House of Commons for spring votes. She is also restricted in the time she takes off: MPs do not pay Employment Insurance so they do not get maternity or paternity benefits. Soule will take paternity leave and will bring their baby to the House of Commons lobby so Lefebvre can breastfeed. </p>
 
 <p>Dating between staff and MPs is &ldquo;a whole new thing,&rdquo; said Soule. There are romances in other parties but they are rare. James Moore, the thirtysomething Conservative MP and cabinet minister, married Courtney Payne, a communications specialist for the Prime Minister, last December. Moore&rsquo;s announcement was greeted with congratulations from his caucus but it is understood the Prime Minister is not a fan of MPs dating staff members or MPs dating other MPs (see Peter Mackay and Belinda Stronach, or Helena Guergis and Rahim Jaffer). One party insider said: &ldquo;But not unlike many a parent, you can&rsquo;t choose who your kids date.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Tim Powers, a lobbyist in Ottawa, said relationships on the Hill are inevitably a matter of proximity, and the new crop of young MPs will result in more dating between politicians and staff. &ldquo;Given the nature of the Ottawa political life, the people it attracts, throw in a bit of human nature, and one of its natural extensions is younger MPs dating staff members of a similar age. It gives a parliamentary filibuster new meaning.&rdquo;  
 </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>National</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Heritage </slug>
 <hedline>The grave state of a PM&rsquo;s digs</hedline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 
 
 <body.content>
 <p>John Diefenbaker&rsquo;s house has a crack in its foundation. The sunroom paint is peeling away, while the house itself lists northward. For the Prince Albert Historical Society, which maintains the home where Canada&rsquo;s 13th prime minister lived from 1947 to 1975, that means a grant-writing marathon in the hopes the Saskatchewan or federal governments will cough up some of the estimated $400,000 needed to keep a piece of Canadian history in good repair. The society shouldn&rsquo;t hold its breath, though. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s a very negative period&rdquo; for heritage funding in Canada, says Christina Cameron, the former head of national historic sites at Parks Canada and now a professor at the Universit&eacute; de Montr&eacute;al&rsquo;s school of architecture. The high value that Canadian politicians profess to put on our history, she says, &ldquo;doesn&rsquo;t seem to translate into money.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Dief&rsquo;s old digs are far from the only historic site in need of TLC. Last summer reports revealed the dilapidated state of graves belonging to several former prime ministers, including deteriorating marble on Sir John A. Macdonald&rsquo;s family plot and rust on Sir Wilfrid Laurier&rsquo;s grave. Parks Canada, tasked with maintaining prime ministerial resting places and 167 other historic sites, saw its budget slashed by $29 million. For now, the city of Prince Albert, which owns the Diefenbaker home, is chipping in for the repairs. So too is a non-profit architecture society. The non-profit model has worked well in the U.S., where despite the American obsession with all things George Washington, donations and ticket sales&mdash;not tax dollars&mdash;provide upkeep for his estate and grave. A solution perhaps, to straighten up the Chief&rsquo;s old house.</p>
 
  <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
 


 <slug>Winnipeg </slug>
 <hedline>An extra-large sized order of generosity </hedline>


 <p>On a brisk December morning, as customers at a Tim Hortons drive-through in southeast Winnipeg waited to pay for their orders, a strange thing happened: the driver in the car ahead of them picked up their tab. That simple act of generosity wasn&rsquo;t unheard of in the Prairie city. Last fall, <em>Maclean&rsquo;s </em>revealed that customers at various coffee shops across the city were being surprised by random acts of coffee charity&mdash;a story that quickly went viral and was picked up by news sites worldwide. </p>
 
 <p>Only this time, the generosity became infectious. Car after car, customers kept pouring it forward, and what might normally involve one or two free beverages became a three-hour phenomenon. By the time it was over, 228 patrons had paid for a stranger&rsquo;s double-double or Timbits. </p>
 
 <p>The seemingly endless &#64258;ow of freebies initially caught restaurant staff off-guard. Then, as the chain grew longer, a drive-through manager kept shouting out random numbers as the tally reached into the dozens, then hundreds. &ldquo;This sort of thing happens quite frequently where one of our guests will buy a coffee for another,&rdquo; says Tim Hortons spokesperson Michelle Robichaud. &ldquo;But we&rsquo;ve never seen something of this magnitude.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>It&rsquo;s still not entirely clear why this wave of generosity has caught on so strongly in Winnipeg, though, as <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> did point out in our original story, the province enjoys the nickname &ldquo;Friendly Manitoba.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Of course, all good things must come to an end. Attempts were made by local reporters to figure out the identity of customer number 229&mdash;the individual who &#64257;nally broke the chain. All that&rsquo;s known is that he took off with four cups of coffee&mdash;paid for by the person in front of him&mdash;and left the person behind him to pick up his or her own three-coffee tab.</p>
 
 
  <byline>Ryan Mallough</byline>
 



 <slug>Capital Diary </slug>
 <hedline>Mitchel Raphael on tips from politicians for hunger strikes</hedline>


 <p>A strawberry never tasted so good </p>
 
 <p>On Dec 11, <em>Theresa Spence</em> began her hunger strike with only water, medicinal tea and fish broth as sustenance. Many opposition MPs spent time with the Attawapiskat chief to offer support. Some have had &#64257;rst-hand experience with hunger strikes and fasts. </p>
 
 <p>In 2001, Green leader <em>Elizabeth May</em>, then executive director of the Sierra Club of Canada, went on a 17-day hunger strike. She was demanding the Liberal government relocate families living near the Sydney Tar Ponds toxic waste site in Cape Breton. Once health minister <em>Allan Rock</em> agreed to meet her demands, she ate a strawberry. Her choice of what to eat first came from a friend who said it was a First Nations tradition. </p>
 
 <p>For her hunger strike May drank only water and Gatorade. The sport drink was on the recommendation of former MP <em>Keith Martin</em>, who is also a medical doctor. Martin said Gatorade would replace May&rsquo;s electrolytes, something she needed to do if she did not want to permanently damage her organs. &ldquo;After a couple of days, you don&rsquo;t feel hungry,&rdquo; says May. &ldquo;You feel an extraordinary level of intellectual clarity. I never had clearer thoughts. The endorphins kick in so you can survive until the food comes.&rdquo; In December, Liberal MP and Aboriginal affairs critic <em>Carolyn Bennett</em>, who is also a medical doctor, had intended to go to New Zealand to study how that country has integrated the culture of its indigenous Maori people. But once Chief Spence began her hunger strike, Bennett chose to stay home and has met with Spence several times. The MP says the recommended way to go off a hunger strike is to eat rice, bananas, apple sauce, Gatorade and Jell-O, noting the body needs glucose and carbs. </p>
 
 <p>May&rsquo;s hunger strike was in the month of May, so the weather was fairly good and she was allowed to stay right outside the members&rsquo; door of Centre Block. This wouldn&rsquo;t be possible in the post-9/11 era, she notes. Former NDP leader <em>Alexa McDonough</em> stored a chair and placards for May in her office. May would sit from about 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. each day, then return home. Her daughter would mark off each day on a board with a magic marker. On the 17th day, May&rsquo;s daughter told her she had to end her strike because the marker had run out. Coincidentally, later that day, Rock met her demands. May had lost 25 lb. </p>
 
 <p>She says it took her five days to resume normal eating. After the hunger strike, she says diets that had worked for her before were no longer effective because her body was always on guard for famine. Around a decade later, May, who had protested in front of the members&rsquo; door, walked through it as an MP. &ldquo;It felt really damn cool.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Before the Vancouver 2010 Winter Olympics, NDP deputy leader <em>Libby Davies</em> went on a one-week fast to raise awareness for homelessness and hunger in Canada, particularly in her riding of Vancouver East. She sustained herself on tea, juices and V8. &ldquo;I felt pretty good, actually. It took this pressure off. It really helped me focus.&rdquo; Each day she stood at the busy corner of Main and Hastings with a flip chart, on which people could write comments about the homeless. Some are &ldquo;unprintable,&rdquo; she says. The fast, after it was over, also led Davies to start eating healthier, something she says she&rsquo;s been able to maintain. </p>
 
 
 <p>One of the longer hunger strikes by a Canadian politician was in 1986, when Liberal senator <em>Jacques H&eacute;bert</em> planted himself in the Senate lobby and refused to eat for 21 days. He opposed a move by <em>Brian Mulroney</em>&rsquo;s Progressive Conservative government to kill the Katimavik youth program, which H&eacute;bert had founded in 1977. With the help of <em>Jean Chr&eacute;tien</em>, a non-profit foundation was founded to save the program. H&eacute;bert ended his hunger strike with a glass of grape juice. Katimavik&rsquo;s funding was restored by the Chr&eacute;tien government, until <em>Stephen Harper</em>&rsquo;s Conservatives cancelled it last year. </p>
 


 <slug> Studies say </slug>
 <hedline>Dirty money and TV time togetherness </hedline>


 <p>British Columbia: Note to Liberal leadership candidates&mdash;it takes just 120 seconds for a person to spot a future leader in a crowded room. Researchers at the University of British Columbia found people are drawn to leaders who exhibit signs of prestige and dominance. The team used eye-tracking technology and found that being well-liked attracted less attention than exuding authority and skill. </p>
 
 <p>Alberta: Whether you get the stink eye for cutting in line may depend on whether your fellow shoppers feel sorry for you. A University of Alberta study found consumers want to punish others who break social norms, like cutting in line. But they will go easy if a perpetrator suffers a physical ailment or has already been seen to be punished. </p>
 
 <p>Ontario: When is a $20 bill not a $20 bill? Apparently when it&rsquo;s crumpled and dirty, which leads people to view it as less valuable, according to researchers at the University of Guelph. They found Canadians with dirty money are more likely to spend it and take greater chances than if their money was clean and new. Researchers also found people are more likely to hand over a grimy bill before a clean one in order to get rid of it&mdash;unless they&rsquo;re trying to make a good impression. </p>
 
 <p>Quebec: The family that watches TV together, sticks together. And you can forget about the &ldquo;death of the small screen.&rdquo; Those are the conclusions of a study from the Universit&eacute; de Montr&eacute;al. It shows families in five major Canadian cities still find valuable bonding time in gathering around the TV, despite competition from computers and tablets. </p>
 
 <p>Newfoundland: Canadian police officers lack basic interviewing skills, says a new study from Memorial University. Researchers pored over 80 police interview transcripts and found investigators talked too much, didn&rsquo;t listen to suspects&rsquo; answers, and asked closed- instead of open-ended questions. It blamed the results on insufficient interview training within police forces.</p>
 
 <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
 
 
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>International</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Europe </slug>
 <hedline>An army for Europe? </hedline>
 
 <abstract>EU leaders, facing the threat of financial collapse in Spain, Italy and Portugal, have somehow concluded now is the time to mount a European army</abstract>
 
 <byline>Katie Engelhart</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_EUROPEANARMY01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.byline>Marcel van den Bergh/Hollandse Hoogte/Redux</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>later this year, the leaders of European Union nations will meet in Brussels for their annual European council. On the agenda: a discussion of Europe&rsquo;s military might. At the summit, it&rsquo;s likely that two equally bold visions for European defence will be put forward. One would see the union&rsquo;s 27 member states pool military resources as never before&mdash;with an eye to eventually building a bona fide EU army. The other would see the union member with the strongest military, Britain, withdraw from the EU&mdash;leaving the Continent sputtering. </p>
 
 <p>In London, it is talk of a potential pullout from the EU that dominates. But elsewhere, calls for a pan-European military are growing&mdash;with France and Germany leading the charge. In September, a group of EU foreign ministers spelled it out directly, weighing, in a controversial report, the possibility of a European army. </p>
 
 <p>How exactly that army would function has yet to be decided&mdash;or even sketched out in much detail. In the event of another Iraq war, would the EU commit troops as a block? In the case of a major terrorist attack in Paris, would EU troops be called in? What seems unlikely is the prospect of EU leaders disbanding their own militaries. For that reason, a viable EU army would have to accommodate coexisting national forces&mdash;and leave room for individual opt-outs. But the question is: should the balance between national and continental defence be shifted? And how far? Last fall, EU defence ministers agreed to develop what sounds an awful lot like a kindergarten rulebook: a voluntary code of conduct on pooling and sharing. </p>
 
 <p>But if Europe is a kindergarten, then one of the children is not playing nicely. &ldquo;The Brits will resist this enormously,&rdquo; warns Nick Witney, a senior policy fellow at the European Council on Foreign Relations, in London. Even as many EU states are calling for a &ldquo;more Europe&rdquo; defence policy, some in Britain want to bow out of the union entirely, in part due to disagreements about the future of European defence. </p>
 
 <p>In response to December&rsquo;s Brussels summit, members of Britain&rsquo;s Conservative Party lashed out at Prime Minister David Cameron. &ldquo;If anyone seriously believes that it is in our national interest to hand over our defence to people running the euro, then we would need our heads examined,&rdquo; scoffed MP Douglas Carswell. </p>
 
 <p>But there is a sense that something must be done. That Europe&rsquo;s military strength should be cause for concern is not entirely obvious. Together, the EU&rsquo;s 27 members have half a million more men and women on active service than Americans do. But the spectre of Europe&rsquo;s military unpreparedness looms&mdash;and has ever since the hundreds of thousands of U.S. troops patrolling Cold War Europe returned home. It looms all the larger as cash-strapped Euro states slash defence spending. Between 2009 and 2011, NATO&rsquo;s European members cut defence expenditures by $45 billion (the equivalent of Germany&rsquo;s entire annual defence budget). </p>
 
 <p>That has left its American ally feeling less than charitable about partnering with EU states through NATO. In 2011, then-U.S. defence secretary Robert Gates warned that if &ldquo;current trends in the decline of European defence capabilities are not halted and reversed, future U.S. political leaders may not consider America&rsquo;s investment in NATO worth the risk.&rdquo; Dwindling European financing, Gates added, lent NATO &ldquo;the very real possibility of collective military irrelevance.&rdquo; At the same time, the United States has historically been prickly about European military integration, for fear it could weaken NATO. Right now t</p>
 
 <p>here are only national armies that sometimes co-operate. In 2010, Britain and France&mdash;long skeptical of each other&rsquo;s battlefield prowess&mdash;sealed a 50-year deal on sharing military equipment. An EU army would be another matter, though. </p>
 
 <p>These discussions are not new. In 1946, former British prime minister Winston Churchill spoke of building a &ldquo;United States of Europe.&rdquo; In 1950, there was a proposal to build a European defence community, in part to flex some muscle before the Soviets. Those plans crumbled. A united Europe was relegated to the world of fiction, appearing in plenty of dystopian novels, and several episodes of <em>Star Trek: The Next Generation</em>. But the idea of a European military was never wholly abandoned. For some European leaders, the time for the expensive new armed force is apparently now&mdash;as eurozone leaders pass yet another round of bank bailouts, and face the threat of &#64257;nancial collapse in Spain, Italy and Portugal. </p>
 
 <p>Today, supporters of the still-elusive EU army insist that pooling military might is the only way for the Continent to keep its fists up. For the first time in modern history, Asia is forecast to outspend Europe on defence. Russia has just surpassed Britain and France on arms spending. </p>
 
 <p>And they argue there are already precursors to an EU army. In the late &rsquo;90s, European countries developed a Common Security and Defence Policy to oversee armed collaborations. In 2003, a rapid-reaction European Union Force (EUFOR) was established; it has been deployed five times, including in Macedonia and Bosnia. Since 2007, a number of EU Battlegroups&mdash;comprised of 1,500 troops each from member nations&mdash;were formed on the Continent, with one or two ready at all times for emergency deployment. </p>
 
 <p>Traditionally, Britain has been reluctant to embrace any of this. Last year, the country quashed a proposal (backed by France and Germany) to build an EU operational military headquarters in Brussels. &ldquo;We will not agree to it now and we will not agree to it in the future,&rdquo; bristled British Foreign Secretary William Hague. &ldquo;That is a red line.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Most often, Britain even opposes the idea of a common EU foreign policy. &ldquo;The pretense that the EU has common defence interests is absurd,&rdquo; said U.K. Independence Party spokesman Lord Alexander Hesketh in December. &ldquo;There are no European interests; there are national interests that sometimes coincide.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Take Libya. In 2011, Britain and France were key agents behind the intervention to strip power from strongman Moammar Gadhafi. Germany refused to lend a hand militarily. What would have happened, some Brits ask, if Berlin had been able to veto the operation? </p>
 
 <p>In September, there was discussion about whether the national veto&mdash;which currently lets nations refuse to commit troops to EU projects&mdash;could be overridden, using a mechanism created by the 2007 Lisbon treaty. </p>
 
 <p>Witney, of the European Council on Foreign Relations, thinks Britain&rsquo;s Euro-skeptics have constructed a strawman in public debates: a woefully discombobulated Euro force that is a slave to German caprice&mdash;and probably commanded by the likes of the French. </p>
 
 <p>If so, politically it seems to be working. Witney believes a fully fledged EU army will never pass muster in Britain. He hopes for a ramped-up pooling of resources, with targets set for the 15- to 25-year range. </p>
 
 <p>On Dec. 14, the same day that Eurocrats were waxing philosophic on EU defence, the viability of the new force was put to a new test. David Cameron and French President Fran&ccedil;ois Hollande turned their attention to a most pressing concern: an existing ban on military supplies to Syrian opposition groups. Speaking before EU leaders, Cameron and Hollande urged their partners to relax the EU arms embargo. But several EU states, including Germany, said no. </p>
 
 <p>As is the EU way, politicians have pledged to &ldquo;work on this issue further,&rdquo; at a future date.  </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>International</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Iran </slug>
 <hedline>Bringing Torture to light </hedline>
 
 <abstract>For the first time, a tribunal has found Iran guilty of the murder and torture of thousands of political prisoners</abstract>
 
  <byline>Michael Petrou</byline>

 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC01_IRAN01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Judgment: Survivors of the massacre had to create their own forum for justice </photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Patrick Chauvel/Corbis</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Nina Toobaei last saw her younger brother, Siamak, in an Iranian prison in 1987. She kissed her hand and placed it against the glass dividing them. He did the same. Then she left Iran for a new life as a refugee in Canada. </p>
 
 <p>Two years later, Siamak was given a day pass to visit family. On a trip to the market, he slipped away. Toobaei and her mother and father allowed themselves to believe he had escaped for good, and that one day they would hear his voice on the phone, or he would show up in person. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Our eyes were on the door for 18 years,&rdquo; she says. Her brother never came. </p>
 
 <p>It wasn&rsquo;t until one of Siamak&rsquo;s friends and fellow prisoners wrote a memoir in exile that his family learned he had been recaptured and executed&mdash;one of perhaps 20,000 political prisoners killed by the Islamic Republic during the 1980s. Many, such as Toobaei&rsquo;s uncle Bahman Nayeri, were leftists; others, including Siamak and another uncle, Bijan Nayeri, belonged to the People&rsquo;s Mujahedeen of Iran, whose members actively fought the Iranian regime, including with bombings and assassinations. </p>
 
 <p>No one has ever been held to account for the mass murder of prisoners during the 10 years that followed the Islamic revolution. Some of the perpetrators now occupy leading positions within the Islamic Republic&mdash;while the mothers of executed prisoners are harassed and abused when they mourn their children at an unmarked mass grave in Tehran&rsquo;s Khavaran cemetery, where many of them are buried. </p>
 
 <p>Toobaei and her mother and father are denied even this meagre comfort. They don&rsquo;t know where Siamak&rsquo;s body is. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Once, my mom told me that she wishes he was also in Khavaran, so that she could go sometimes and be where his bones are,&rdquo; Toobaei says, her voice breaking. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;When you have a grave, sometimes you go there and you talk to him. When you don&rsquo;t, it hurts.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>For decades, relatives of victims and survivors of Iran&rsquo;s bloody decade felt silenced and forgotten, cut off from any means of seeking justice. The International Criminal Court cannot prosecute crimes committed before July 1, 2002; and even if it could, Iran does not accept the court&rsquo;s jurisdiction. </p>
 
 <p>The United Nations might establish a tribunal, as it did for crimes committed in Rwanda and the former Yugoslavia, but Iran has powerful friends on the Security Council and this is unlikely. And the West has always been more concerned with Iranian terrorism and its nuclear program than the savagery the state visits on its citizens. </p>
 
 <p>This led survivors of the massacres to create their own forum for justice. The Iran tribunal, established in 2007, has no legal standing. Its creators, however, modelled it on other international legal tribunals. Steering committee members Sir Geoffrey Nice, a British barrister, and Payam Akhavan, a professor of international law at McGill University, both worked on the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia. Akhavan also advised the prosecutor&rsquo;s of&#64257;ce at the International Criminal Tribunal for Rwanda. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;We took great care to have a credible process, which would be perceived by the Iranian public and the wider international community as at least a quasi-judicial process. And that meant that it not be seen as a politicized process, but as a historical record and a judgment based on international law,&rdquo; says Akhavan. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;At least half of justice, if not the greater half, in the context of crimes against humanity, is to expose the public to historical truth. It&rsquo;s not just about arresting someone and putting them in prison, as important as that may be.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The tribunal, which was funded through donations and is independent of any government, heard from almost 100 witnesses who testi&#64257;ed in two phases this year. In June, a truth commission took place in London. The primary purpose of this stage was to allow victims to tell their stories in a formal setting. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;The Iranian government has committed two crimes against these people,&rdquo; says Kaveh Shahrooz, a Toronto lawyer and a prosecutor on the tribunal. &ldquo;One is to imprison, torture, or kill their loved ones. And the second crime is to deny what happened to them and to prevent them from speaking about it.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The second phase took place in The Hague in October. This phase more closely mirrored a formal legal tribunal. The prosecution argued that the Iranian regime is guilty of crimes against humanity. Iran was asked to take part, but did not acknowledge or respond to the invitation. </p>
 
 <p>In an interim judgment, issued in late October, the tribunal&rsquo;s judges wrote: &ldquo;The evidence speaks for itself. It constitutes overwhelming proof that systemic, systematic and widespread abuses of human rights were committed by and on behalf of the Islamic Republic of Iran.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;There are six forms of gross human rights abuses to which the evidence presented to the Truth Commission and this tribunal point incontrovertibly: murder; torture; unjust imprisonment; sexual violence; persecution and enforced disappearance.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The judges recommended that the United Nations establish a commission of inquiry to investigate these atrocities. Regardless of whether this occurs, those involved in the tribunal say it has already been a success. Its proceedings were &#64257;lmed and broadcast on Persian satellite channels that are surreptitiously watched inside Iran. </p>
 
 <p>McGill&rsquo;s Akhavan believes the regime itself has been forced to respond. A recent news story on the Baztab news site, thought to have ties to conservative politicians in Iran, claimed that Iran&rsquo;s current supreme leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, intervened to spare leftist political prisoners from likely execution in 1988, when thousands of leftists and People&rsquo;s Mujahedeen were killed in a particularly bloody massacre. </p>
 
 <p>The story isn&rsquo;t credible, says Akhavan, but he argues it would not have been published unless those close to Khamenei wanted to shield him from public anger. &ldquo;This is a turning point in the culture of accountability in Iran,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;The most untouchable leaders are realizing that they&rsquo;re answerable to the people, that people will not forget.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Survivors have never forgotten. One victim, who now lives in Canada and asked not to be named, spent eight years in prison. A leftist, he was arrested for possessing posters and distributing lea&#64258;ets. Hundreds of prisoners were executed one week during his incarceration. The killing began at dinnertime. He and the other inmates were forced to listen to the gun&#64257;re just beyond one of the walls enclosing them. Nobody could eat. They just counted the shots. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;This is not for revenge at all,&rdquo; he says, explaining why he testi&#64257;ed. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t believe in the death penalty. We have to stop this circle of bloodshed in Iran.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Instead, he says he wanted to help document what happened. &ldquo;I have to testify because of the people in those mass graves. I know many of them. This shouldn&rsquo;t happen in the future. That was the reason&mdash;so it wouldn&rsquo;t happen to our people again.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Nina Toobaei says testifying helped her begin to heal. When she returned to Canada, some of her family members had changed, too. &ldquo;My mom was happy. Her voice was more alive. You&rsquo;re doing something. You&rsquo;re taking one step, and that makes you happy. Because we could raise our voice.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>International</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Afghanistan </slug>
 <hedline>Send in the clowns </hedline>
 
 <abstract>After years working in war zones, <em>Maclean&rsquo;s </em>correspondent Adnan R. Khan joins a circus</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC53_CIRCUS01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Make &rsquo;em laugh: The writer and his circus crew perform at a community centre in Pakistan</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>PHOTOGRAPHs BY ADNAN R. KHAN</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>In the long and colourful history of wacky ideas, this one ranks somewhere near the top: buy a three-wheeled, motorized rickshaw from Afghanistan, paint it in wild colours, and drive it 8,000 km through Pakistan and Iran to Istanbul, putting on a circus for children along the way. </p>
 
 <p>When my partner, Annika Schmeding, a petite, blond German and I&mdash;Pakistani by birth, but as Canadian as they come&mdash;came up with the plan, most people in Kabul looked at us as if we were from a planet populated by insane clowns. &ldquo;Are you nuts?&rdquo; asked a former Australian soldier turned freelance security adviser. &ldquo;You&rsquo;ll never make it alive.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Others wrote us off as dreamers who, after many months in the pressure-cooker environment of the Afghan capital, had perhaps become a little unhinged. They weren&rsquo;t entirely wrong. After so much time dealing with the dysfunction and greed of the international development community, where schools are built without teachers to fill them, proposals written not to address Afghan needs but simply to cater to donors, madness can be a refuge for the sane. </p>
 
 <p>What drove us was a firm belief in the therapeutic value of the so-called social circus, a global movement of circus practitioners who work with marginalized youth and traumatized children. </p>
 
 <p>When we began volunteering at the Afghan Mobile Mini-Circus for Children, we saw first-hand the creativity and confidence the circus helped develop, the psychological wounds it helped heal, and most importantly the smiles it brought to kids suffocating under the burden of poverty and hardship. </p>
 
 <p>So, against the advice of the naysayers, we bought that motorized rickshaw, bigger than the tuk-tuks of Thailand, more ornate than India&rsquo;s three-wheeled taxis, with enough room in its spacious interior to comfortably seat eight (comfortable in Afghan terms, that is). We recruited a third performer, Peter Gatehouse, a six-foot-seven-inch Brit with shoulder-length hair, and put a hold on our careers. </p>
 
 <p>Between us, we would travel through some of the world&rsquo;s most hostile territory: eastern Afghanistan, where a burgeoning Taliban controls all but the most heavily populated cities, the Pakistani Tribal Areas, at any time a no-go zone for foreigners, and Baluchistan province in Pakistan&rsquo;s southeast, at various points ruled by bandits, separatist Baloch guerrillas and jihadists, or some combination of the three. And next, the paranoid Iranian police state, where circuses are officially banned and three clowns making fools of themselves in public (throwing the ruling mullahs&rsquo; rigorous piety in their faces) could be an indictable offence. </p>
 
 <p>Crossing the Afghan-Pakistani border at Torkham&mdash;a journey I made alone because non-Pakistanis are banned from entering Pakistan&rsquo;s Tribal Areas; my companions took a different route&mdash;was the first of many hurdles. No tourist vehicle, let alone a rickshaw, had crossed the Torkham border in decades. Suspicious tribesmen glare at anything that doesn&rsquo;t seem to belong in the mad jumble of transport trucks and migrating poor that Torkham has become. And the rickshaw, quite plainly, did not belong. </p>
 
 <p>It took most of three hours for the Afghan customs officials to let me through, after browsing through a tome of customs laws. In Islamabad, I reconnected with the crew, who had flown directly there, and we put on our first performance, a love story where a beautiful, fire-spinning princess (Annika) falls in love with a peace-loving prince (yours truly) as a freakishly tall, fire-eating demon (Peter) jealously tries to break them up. The show was a smash hit. From there, we would exclusively visit Pakistan&rsquo;s most marginalized: street kids in Rawalpindi, the persecuted Hindu community in Quetta. We ran workshops for the kids, teaching them the basics of juggling and how to build juggling tools. </p>
 
 <p>It was exhausting. We drove 10 to 12 hours per day in searing summer heat, performing wherever we stopped for the curious crowds that would inevitably gather around us. And our timing couldn&rsquo;t be worse: we launched our journey at the beginning of Ramadan, the Islamic month of fasting. Even drinking water is prohibited during the day. Whatever food we stored sizzled in the heat. We lost weight rapidly. </p>
 
 <p>Despite the hardships, it was the moments of pure joy that stand out. Working in Iran with orphans in Esfahan, children suffering cancer in Tehran, and displaced children in earthquake-hit Tabriz, infused us with energy and a sense of purpose. Even crossing Baluchistan, where shattered roads threatened to tear the rickshaw apart and leave us stranded in the barren desert, easy picking for bandits and kidnappers, feels less painful in retrospect. What I remember best is watching children undergoing chemotherapy laugh for the first time in months, lift themselves up from their wheelchairs and juggle clubs. </p>
 
 <p>After a decade of covering war zones, I&rsquo;ve seen all too often the effects of violence on children. I remember a group of boys in Pakistan&rsquo;s Swat Valley walking in military lockstep with the Taliban along a busy road. All had plastic replica AK-47s slung over their shoulders. The lead boy, the eldest, carried a plastic replica rocket launcher. They appeared as happy as any 10-year-olds could be, smiling and laughing. </p>
 
 <p>In that image is a sad truth: in places contaminated by war, violence is a game, the objects of violence are toys and the playground a training space for future warriors. Afghanistan is perhaps the world&rsquo;s best example of how violence shapes a culture&rsquo;s children, instigating a cycle of violence with no apparent end. </p>
 
 <p>In this environment, the social circus movement is gaining traction. Much of its success is due to Montreal-based Cirque du Soleil, which operates the world&rsquo;s largest such program, the Cirque du Monde, in 80 communities in five continents. </p>
 
 <p>The Rickshaw Circus is a drop in the bucket compared to that, but every drop counts. All over the world, there are wacky people coming up with wacky ideas based on the basic principle that happy childhoods produce happy adults. And that a little creativity just might make the impossible possible. </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>International</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>africa </slug>
 <hedline>An ounce of prevention </hedline>
 
 <abstract>The HPV vaccine is a bombshell in North America but is gaining acceptance in sub-Saharan Africa</abstract>
 
 <byline>Stephanie Findlay</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC53_HPV01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>A question of branding: The vaccine is no longer primarily associated with preventing STDs </photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>MAURICIO DUENAS/EPA/KEYSTONE PRESS</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Death by cervical cancer is &ldquo;horrible,&rdquo; says Leon Snyman. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not a disease that kills you quickly.&rdquo; For the past two years, Snyman, an adjunct professor of gynecology at South Africa&rsquo;s University of Pretoria, has been inoculating adolescent girls with the human papilloma virus (HPV) vaccine, a preventative treatment for cervical cancer. Snyman says the vaccine has been greeted with enthusiasm: roughly 70 per cent of girls are choosing to be vaccinated. &ldquo;People are not afraid of vaccines,&rdquo; he says. </p>
 
 <p>He&rsquo;s having a far easier time than Juliet Guichon is. For the past four years, the University of Calgary bioethicist has been fighting to overturn the Calgary Catholic School Board&rsquo;s ban on the vaccine, which targets strains of the virus most often contracted from sex. In November, the ban was overturned. But Guichon has found victory &ldquo;sort of bittersweet,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;Although we&rsquo;ve succeeded in opening the door to the vaccine, it&rsquo;s a shame it had to take this long.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>As many Catholic school boards in Alberta, Ontario and the Northwest Territories continue to ban the HPV vaccine, the Canadian government is helping fund what could be one of the largest rollouts of the vaccine in the world. Canada has committed $225 million to the Global Alliance for Vaccines and Immunisation (GAVI); in Tanzania last month, it announced the launch of a pilot run of the vaccine in sub-Saharan Africa with a goal of vaccinating more than 30 million girls. </p>
 
 <p>In Africa, unlike the U.S.&mdash;where any discussions of premarital sex or sexually transmitted diseases have been opposed by conservatives pushing &ldquo;abstinence-only&rdquo; policies&mdash;the vaccine has been embraced by politicians and high-profile celebrities, including the first ladies of Tanzania and Zambia and the popular Tanzanian MTV host Vanessa Mdee. </p>
 
 <p>In sub-Saharan Africa, the vaccine has faced little opposition or backlash, says GAVI CEO Seth Berkley. In Europe and North America, &ldquo;Whole Food moms,&rdquo; as he calls them&mdash;parents skeptical of the benefits of vaccines and fearful of their side effects&mdash;are &ldquo;leading the charge&rdquo; against a range of vaccines, notably those for measles, flus and whooping cough. (In 2011, the World Health Organization actually issued a measles warning for Europe after 26,000 cases were reported. Public health officials blamed parents who had neglected to give their children the vaccine.) </p>
 
 <p>In the developing world, the story is different. The value of vaccines is obvious to more people, says Hennie Botha, head of the department of obstetrics and gynecology at Stellenbosch University in South Africa. Cervical cancer is the leading cause of cancer deaths in women in that country. In contrast, cervical cancer rarely kills in Canada, where women have access to screening measures such as Pap smears and regular checkups. &ldquo;Many people will know someone with cervical cancer,&rdquo; says Botha. &ldquo;Women are diagnosed late because there is no screening or very poor screening.&rdquo; Every year in Africa, more than 50,000 women die from the disease, according to 2010 estimates published by the WHO. &ldquo;The vaccine is seen as the best chance we have to make the difference,&rdquo; says Botha. </p>
 
 <p>It helps that over the years the HPV branding strategy has changed from being primarily associated with preventing diseases contracted from unprotected sex&mdash;as the first HPV vaccine, Gardasil, was&mdash;to ending cervical cancer. Tania Cernuschi, GAVI&rsquo;s HPV expert, notes that when the first HPV vaccine, Gardasil, was released in the United States in 2006, &ldquo;it was publicized in a certain way, with a focus on sexually transmitted diseases.&rdquo; Now, says Cernuschi, it is marketed differently. </p>
 
 <p>The success of the vaccine in sub-Saharan Africa is being watched closely by scientists who see it as a model for future vaccines targeted to adolescents. Vivien Tsu, an epidemiologist at the University of Washington, says this includes people working on the HIV vaccine. &ldquo;This was the first time a vaccine in this age group was coming out, and they thought there could be some lessons for them,&rdquo; says Tsu. Those lessons include developing a vaccine plan for an age group outside the usual vaccination range&mdash;newborns and toddlers. &ldquo;Many people are saying we&rsquo;ve neglected adolescents,&rdquo; says Tsu. &ldquo;This is a good time to start building more of a program for them.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>For Snyman, that time can&rsquo;t come soon enough. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s a totally preventable disease,&rdquo; he says, &ldquo;yet cervical cancer is rife. It&rsquo;s a big problem.&rdquo;  </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <body.head>

 
 <slug>South Africa </slug>
 <hedline>Mining for a settlement</hedline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_WORLDNOTES03.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>A sickening job: Thousands of South African miners are suing their former employers</photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Rebecca Cook/Reuters; Michael Regan/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 
 

 <p>More than 30 gold companies in South Africa are facing a class action lawsuit on behalf of 17,000 former miners who say that, as a result of their work, they are sick with silicosis, a debilitating, irreversible lung disease. The mining companies may be liable for as much as US$100 billion, according to Bloomberg News. The lawsuit comes at a difficult time for the mines, which saw massive drops in profit last year due to labour disruptions. </p>
 
 <p>Class action lawsuits are unusual in South Africa, which does not have a long history of this type of litigation. In November 2012, a class action lawsuit was successfully brought against companies found guilty of running a bread cartel&mdash;&ldquo;a seminal judgment,&rdquo; says Wouter De Vos, professor emeritus of law at the University of Capetown. &ldquo;The miners&rsquo; case will likely be the most important case to follow.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Lawyer Richard Spoor, who filed the silicosis suit against some of the country&rsquo;s biggest mining firms&mdash;including AngloGold Ashanti and Harmony Gold&mdash;says the number of plaintiffs is increasing by 500 people a month. &ldquo;People in South Africa can&rsquo;t afford litigation,&rdquo; says De Vos. &ldquo;Class action is the only means to give them access to justice.&rdquo;</p>
 
  <byline>Stephanie Findlay</byline>
  
  
 
  <slug>Britain </slug>
 <hedline>Fat and on welfare? look out</hedline>
 
 <p>If you really want to see benefits from working out, consider a move to the central London area of Westminster. There, overweight Londoners could see their benefit payments rise and fall depending on how often they hit the gym. Under the controversial new proposal, a family doctor could prescribe exercise to obese patients, who would then be rewarded with financial incentives if they followed the doctor&rsquo;s orders&mdash;or be penalized if they didn&rsquo;t. &ldquo;You could use council tax benefits to incentivize people to undertake more healthy activities,&rdquo; says Jonathan Carr-West, of the Local Government Information Unit, the think tank that wrote the report for Westminster city council. Obesity costs Britain about $8 billion a year, he notes. &ldquo;We have to try and be innovative, and we have to try and be radical.&rdquo; The idea made headlines across the country&mdash;and drew scoffs from the medical establishment. The British Medical Association&rsquo;s Lawrence Buckman, a family doctor, said when he heard the idea, &ldquo;I thought it was a joke.&rdquo; But Carr-West isn&rsquo;t bothered by criticisms. &ldquo;Doctors haven&rsquo;t been able to solve this problem,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;We need to try something else.&rdquo; The report comes ahead of a dramatic change in health administration that will see local councils take control of public health care budgets from the National Health Service in April. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s a preventative measure to save money,&rdquo; says Carr-West. And a whole new way to monetize pounds.</p>
 
 
  <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
 




 <slug>Colombia </slug>
 <hedline>Bulletproof kids&rsquo; clothes</hedline>
 
 <p>Colombian fashion designer Miguel Caballero dresses world leaders, the rich and famous and even royalty, with his slim and stylish bulletproof garments. Now the man known as the Armani of bulletproofing wants to outfit a new and unlikely clientele: schoolchildren. Capitalizing on the fears of parents after the slaying of 20 first graders in Newtown, Conn., Caballero recently launched a new line of children&rsquo;s clothing under the MC Kids label. It includes bulletproof T-shirts durable enough resist a Mini-Uzi, reinforced puffer jackets that weigh only five pounds, and a backpack that doubles as a shield. </p>
 
 <p>Caballero says he&rsquo;s no opportunist, just responding to demand&mdash;albeit reluctantly. Over the years, he&rsquo;s received repeated requests for kids&rsquo; clothing from clients in Asia and the Middle East, but always refused, &ldquo;because I believe that minors should not be part of the conflict.&rdquo; But the Bogot&aacute;-based designer does big business in dangerous places, including his native Colombia, where former president &Aacute;lvaro Uribe wore bulletproof <em>guayabera</em> shirts, and Mexico, where he opened an outlet in the capital&rsquo;s posh Polanco neighbourhood. Now he has America&rsquo;s parents lining up.</p>
 
  <byline>David Agren</byline>
 




 


 <slug>China </slug>
 <hedline>Blame it on jaywalkers</hedline>

 <p>In China&rsquo;s densely populated cities, it&rsquo;s not uncommon to see cars driving on the wrong side of the street, barrelling down bike lanes or even parked on the sidewalks. In the last two decades, as the number of motorists has grown astronomically, Chinese roads have become a Wild West of traffic violations. In 2011, nearly 70,000 people were killed in traffic accidents, and tens of thousands more were injured. But last month, traffic wardens began fining some of China&rsquo;s most prevalent lawbreakers: pedestrians. </p>
 
 <p>While some have lauded the government for enforcing any traffic laws at all&mdash;speed limits and red lights are routinely ignored&mdash;critics say targeting pedestrians is ineffective and unfair. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Chinese drivers don&rsquo;t stop at traffic lights, so either you jaywalk or you don&rsquo;t cross the street,&rdquo; says Tyler Ehler, a Canadian student living in Nanjing. The problem, says Ehler, is the driving class has simply grown too large, too fast&mdash;&ldquo;teenagers are learning to drive at the same time as their parents.&rdquo; A country full of new drivers, he says, is bound to have its share of traffic accidents. </p>
 
 <p>While some dismiss traffic accidents as mere growing pains, others question whether China&rsquo;s thousands of road fatalities are an inevitable consequence of its rise.</p>
 
  <byline>Mika Rekai</byline>
 


 <slug>United States </slug>
 <hedline>Hitting them where it hurts </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Republicans take on labour unions&mdash;which helped fund Obama&rsquo;s victory in November</abstract>
 

 <p>As Republicans try to rebuild after November&rsquo;s electoral defeat, one of their priorities for 2013 may be going after the sources of the Democrats&rsquo; power&mdash;and no target is easier, or more inviting, than labour unions. The first post-election salvo against unions came in Michigan, home to thousands of unionized auto workers. By signing a right-to-work law outlawing requirements that workers pay union fees to work, Republican Gov. Rick Snyder may have inspired other Republican-controlled states. Groups like the pro-business American Legislative Exchange Council (ALEC), which provided the template for Michigan&rsquo;s law, are already hoping to take the fight to other blue states in 2013. </p>
 
 <p>Weakening unions has been a traditional Republican priority, from 1947&rsquo;s Taft-Hartley Act that restricted union power, to former president Ronald Reagan&rsquo;s famous fight with the air-traffic controllers&rsquo; union in 1981. But in past decades, there was a countervailing pro-union wing of the party, consisting of moderate northeastern Republicans. Now most are gone, and the party stars tend to align with South Carolina Gov. Nikki Haley, who once declared: &ldquo;I love that we are one of the least unionized states in the country.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Beyond party ideology, taking on unions has a clear political advantage: right-to-work laws cut off an outside source of funding for the Democratic party&mdash;funding that helped drive the get-out-the-vote operations which propelled President Barack Obama to victory in most swing states. But by reducing the amount of money unions can collect by an estimated 20 to 30 per cent, the new Michigan law might make it harder for future Democratic presidential candidates to win the state. </p>
 
 <p>Of course, there are political risks: Mitt Romney&rsquo;s stance against Obama&rsquo;s auto bailout may have cost him labour-friendly states like Ohio and Michigan. And while groups like ALEC are already eyeing Republican-controlled Pennsylvania as a possible new right-to-work state, Gov. Tom Corbett says &ldquo;there is not much of a movement to do it.&rdquo; Then again, movements can start pretty quickly: Snyder once called such laws &ldquo;divisive,&rdquo; and said they were &ldquo;not on my agenda,&rdquo; only to change his mind this year. It remains to be seen whether other governors will, too. </p>
 
 <byline>Jaime J. Weinman</byline>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Business</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>NHL </slug>
 <hedline>A winning record </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Three times now, the commissioner has locked out his players. Three times now, he&rsquo;s delivered a win. Jonathon Gatehouse reports on why Gary Bettman is here to stay.</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_NHL01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Back in business: Bettman&rsquo;s contract&mdash;worth $7.98 million last year&mdash;runs through 2015. From there it&rsquo;s just two years to the league centennial.</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Mary Altaffer/AP</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>For Gary Bettman, one suspects it&rsquo;s the equivalent of winning the Stanley Cup. That instant when the ultra-competitive commissioner of the National Hockey League finally puts his signature to a new collective bargaining agreement. After months&mdash;sometimes years&mdash;of preparation, gamesmanship and horse-trading, there&rsquo;s got to be a fair measure of joy and relief. And more often than his critics and many hockey fans would like, an extra-large helping of triumph. Three times now, since taking over the league in February 1993, Bettman has locked out his players. And three times now, he has delivered his bosses&mdash;the 30 team owners&mdash;a victory. </p>
 
 <p>On the first go-around, the 103-day shut-down that pared the 1994-95 season down to 48 games, it was just a partial win&mdash;limits on rookie salaries and tweaks to free agency. Then at the cost of the entire 2004-05 season, a rout, imposing the toughest salary cap in pro sports and all but destroying the players&rsquo; association. And now on the heels of a 113-day lockout that ended with a tentative deal struck in the wee hours of Jan. 6, another big boost to the bank balances of his proprietors: reducing the players&rsquo; share of league revenues from 57 per cent to 50 per cent. On the basis of the NHL&rsquo;s record-setting $3.3-billion 2011-12 season, that&rsquo;s a transfer of $230 million&mdash;the equivalent of a new network TV deal or expansion fee. And over the course of the 10-year agreement, the shift should be worth closer to $3 billion than $2 billion if the business continues to grow at its current clip. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Clearly, the owners have scored a major victory,&rdquo; says Rod Fort, an economist and professor of sport management at the University of Michigan. The payoff won&rsquo;t be immediate, he notes, thanks to the costs of the shutdown and a negotiated $300-million &ldquo;make whole&rdquo; payment to players to cushion the transition. &ldquo;But losing that seven per cent is a big deal for the players. And the NHL has now set the benchmark for all agreements going forward.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>That the new deal is not more heavily weighted in the proprietors&rsquo; favour is surely a testament to the skill and tenacity of Don Fehr, the executive director of the NHLPA. The longtime baseball union leader is the toughest opponent Bettman has ever faced, and seemed to fluster the commissioner with his deliberate approach and refusal to engage on anything but his own terms. Clearly the lockout dragged on longer than the league had planned, forcing the cancellation of the outdoor Jan. 1 Winter Classic, the NHL&rsquo;s marquee U.S. television event. But whether that miscalculation was the fault of Bettman or of hardline owners like Boston&rsquo;s Jeremy Jacobs and Calgary&rsquo;s Murray Edwards, who aggressively tried to cut Fehr out of the process, is debatable. In the end, the league gave on issues like pensions and the salary-cap ceiling, but also made gains on free-agent contracts, limiting their length to seven years (eight if the player signs again with his current team) and how much compensation can vary over their course. It&rsquo;s all part of Bettman&rsquo;s strategy to rein in team spending and stop monster deals like the 15-year, $100-million agreement that Ilya Kovalchuk signed with the New Jersey Devils in 2010. </p>
 
 <p>Of course, none of this has made the commissioner&mdash;already approaching supervillain status&mdash;any more popular. While there were fewer death threats than in past lockouts, the players&rsquo; respect for the man who leads the league is grudging at best. &ldquo;Most of the owners are decent guys,&rdquo; Red Wing defenceman Ian White told the <em>Detroit News </em>in the wake of the tentative agreement<em>.</em> &ldquo;There were a few of them who wanted to play right from the get-go and not [go] through the shenanigans.&rdquo; Bettman, on the other hand, seemed intent on pushing for maximum advantage, he said. &ldquo;They wanted to sweat us out and it looks like that&rsquo;s what happened.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>And the fans&rsquo; long-standing antipathy for the 60-year-old lawyer has taken on a new, almost obsessive edge&mdash;type &ldquo;Bettman sucks&rdquo; into Google and you get 12,500 hits, including blogs, videos, original songs and Facebook groups all dedicated to the theme. </p>
 
 <p>But the truth is that whatever damage the league has inflicted upon itself by cancelling a total of 625 mostly meaningless early-season games is temporary. It took fewer than 24 hours for aggrieved fans to start breaking out their team jerseys and baseball caps, and even less time for the media to switch back from finger-waving mode to training camp previews and trade gossip. NBC, the NHL&rsquo;s American broadcasting partner, will get to start its Sunday afternoon coverage on Jan. 20, as it always planned. (Although, the network keenly felt the absence of hockey from its NBC Sports Channel throughout the fall. In the week before Christmas its top-rated show was <em>Hunt for Big Fish with Larry Dahlberg</em>, drawing 177,000 viewers.) The CBC is simply happy to have something other than reruns on Saturday night. </p>
 
 <p>And having watched the NBA and NFL lock out their players in pursuit of a 50-50 revenue split last year, corporate sponsors were hardly taken by surprise when pro hockey took the same path. &ldquo;Everybody knew the potential for a work stoppage. It&rsquo;s the nature of the business,&rdquo; says Brian Cooper, president of S&amp;E Sponsorship Group, a Toronto firm that brokers arrangements between sports leagues and businesses. In fact, compensation for such disruptions&mdash;usually a pro-rated discount on a future season, or an extension&mdash;is explicitly spelled out in every deal the NHL signs. </p>
 
 <p>Cooper, who has already been involved in several conference calls between the league and sponsors since the tentative deal was struck, says there&rsquo;s more a sense of relief than anger among his clients. And now faced with the prospect of a compressed season&mdash;five games a week instead of three&mdash;followed by full playoffs, they&rsquo;re starting to get excited at the marketing possibilities. &ldquo;They know the fan anger is only going to last until the puck drops.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>And while delaying the season start by 3&frac12; months won&rsquo;t make things any easier in the crowded and competitive U.S. sporting market, there are early signs that the NHL might have actually been missed. The end of the lockout was front-page news, not just in traditional hockey hotbeds like Buffalo, Chicago and Boston, but also in Sunbelt markets like Los Angeles, Nashville, Tampa and even Phoenix. </p>
 
 <p>In some ways, the business of the NHL might actually be stronger than it was when hockey was last played and the L.A. Kings hoisted the cup on June 11. Greg Jamison&rsquo;s purchase of the Phoenix Coyotes should be completed within days, bringing an end to years of speculation about the franchise&rsquo;s future. Jeff Vanderbeek has taken sole control of the New Jersey Devils and refinanced the team&rsquo;s debt. And the sad-sack New York Islanders are set to move to the shiny new Barclay&rsquo;s Center in Brooklyn, for the beginning of the 2015-16 campaign. Throw in new ownership in Dallas and St. Louis and the league has fewer problem cases than it has in decades. Although history suggests the calm will be fleeting&mdash;even with increased revenue sharing ($50 million more to bring the pot to $200 million) and built-in cost savings under the new agreement. </p>
 
 <p>So despite the howls from fans and media for Bettman&rsquo;s head, he remains as secure as commissioner as he&rsquo;s ever been. His current contract&mdash;worth $7.98 million this past year&mdash;runs through 2015. From there it&rsquo;s just a short two-year skip to the league&rsquo;s centennial. How long will Bettman, already the most powerful figure the game has ever known, stick around? At this point, it&rsquo;s up to him.</p>
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <body.head>
 <slug>analysis </slug>
 <hedline>Hockey is everything </hedline>
 
 <abstract>And yet it could be so much more to its insatiable fans, writes Colby Cosh, who is one of them</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_COSH01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Gluttons for punishment: NHL fans are far too forgiving, and the league knows it </photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <body.content>
 <p>The conventional wisdom on the NHL lockout, usually delivered with a sneer, is that Canadian hockey fans will belly-crawl back to the league uncritically now that all the bickering and all the tantrums have ended. Like all conventional wisdom, it is conventional because it is quite a safe bet. I know I&rsquo;ll crawl with everyone else: I&rsquo;m capable of intellectually segregating my fondness for the game of hockey from my loathing of the existing institutions of hockey. What&rsquo;s different about this lockout is that in the meantime I took the bait of regular-season NBA basketball with enthusiasm for the first time ever. </p>
 
 <p>For me, even during hockey labour struggles of the past, the NBA had never managed to wriggle into the spare time vacated by baseball. Basketball will never make deep sense to me in the way that hockey does. But over many years my prejudices against it were eroded by a new wave of basketball writers and podcasts and analysts&mdash;a cadre of fans who communicate &ldquo;Come join the fun!&rdquo; without saying it, whose collective activity makes of the sport its own fascinating little planet in which the games are almost an afterthought. </p>
 
 <p>The NHL has the same type of total-involvement apparatus and, ironically, it remained on the job throughout the lockout, with reporters physically besieging the owner-player negotiations in quest of the most meagre shreds of intelligence. In the new media landscape, off-ice drama is to some degree interchangeable with on-ice drama; the fan&rsquo;s attachment to the NHL is participation in a world, and that world doesn&rsquo;t stop just because nobody is playing hockey. We all know this already from experiencing the way in which the NHL calendar has stretched to help consume 12 months of our lives every year; between the last game of the finals and the opening of the regular season comes the panic of free-agency day, the theatre of the draft, the global village homecoming that is training camp, and the social media inquisitions into players who&rsquo;ve been photographed after having a bit too much turkey at Christmas. Involvement is total. </p>
 
 <p>Whether the NHL arrives at a proper understanding of this weird new world of total media involvement is actually what will decide whether this lockout was worthwhile. Hockey has nothing to compare yet with mind-altering information firehoses like the NFL RedZone Channel or baseball&rsquo;s MLB.TV. Its handling of the web is a poor cousin to almost anyone else&rsquo;s in sport. Its production of advanced statistics is left mostly to generous amateurs. It has not been as lucky with podcasting as any of the three &ldquo;major&rdquo; rivals. </p>
 
 <p>But it is getting there. My beloved Oilers initially greeted the advent of social media with a hostility that bordered on violence, but the club has relented. It no longer tries to micromanage the players&rsquo; Twitter accounts, or if it does, it hasn&rsquo;t had much luck. Taylor Hall trades sly, abominably spelled barbs with Jordan Eberle; Nail Yakupov gleefully retweets every cute girl who chats him up from anywhere between Burnaby, B.C., and Birobidzhan, Russia; the relatively well-educated Ryan Whitney, nursing his God-botched feet, heaps irony on all. </p>
 
 <p>Most of it is not very interesting, hockey players largely being incurious, horny small-town galoots even when they are not from small towns. But it does tend to bring the players down to the level of global village neighbours, as opposed to faces on Mount Rushmore. Sports are making the transition from being an avenue of cold pagan heroism to being a noisy, lively reality show. </p>
 
 <p>And there will be money in it. The world of the NHL has room for a lot more specialist media barnacles, whether they be podcasters or paparazzi or critics or stat-crunchers. There&rsquo;s a Mel Kiper Jr. niche for an obsessive draft expert still open between the chairs of Bob McKenzie and Pierre McGuire. There&rsquo;s a Will Carroll niche open for an injury specialist. NBC&rsquo;s NFL broadcasts now feature a hired rules expert, a former referee who is on call in the studio to help explain unusual situations: there&rsquo;s an open niche. Has anyone succeeded in doing a hockey blog with the hipster literary heft of <em>Run of Play</em> or <em>Free Darko</em>? Niche. Is there any half-decent cotton-pickin&rsquo; reference source for scouting reports? No, there is not: niche. English-language reporting in any format on the Euro hockey leagues? It&rsquo;s crummy to non-existent: niche. </p>
 
 <p>The job of the NHL is to pave the way for new paths into the game for fans and to let go of its proprietary mentality, its overwhelming sense that it is in the business of selling the specific club good of personal game attendance. In the long run the gate is bound to be an infinitesimal fraction of the revenues from hockey. In baseball the gate revenues are already being displaced, which is one reason baseball now has labour peace; even though the existence of the 4-6-3 double play will never be so much as suspected by a solid three-quarters of humanity, that sport passed through an era of tortured territorialism into a sort of abundant transcontinental technological singularity. </p>
 
 <p>There is no reason hockey should not be able to pull off the same trick. Your favourite NHL team will probably be worth a billion dollars a lot sooner than you think&mdash;hopefully by the end of this hard-won collective bargaining agreement. <byline></byline>
 </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Business</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 
 <slug>Transportation </slug>
 <hedline>Zipcar minus the zip </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Fans say its purchase by Avis will destroy the hip urban start-up. Others say it&rsquo;s already dead.</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_BIZNOTES01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Park it: Analysts say Zipcar has struggled with high capital, labour and energy costs </photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Mark Lennihan/AP</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>The announcement last week that Avis Budget Group is buying Zipcar for $500 million&mdash;close to double its stock market value&mdash;was a watershed moment for the upstart car-sharing industry. Zipcar, founded in 2000 on a model that bills members by the hour to use its cars, had finally been brought into the car-rental big leagues. Avis trumpeted the deal as a perfect match. Its extensive fleet of vehicles could help fix some of the supply problems that made it hard for Zipcar members to get a car on weekends and evenings. &ldquo;We expect to apply Avis Budget&rsquo;s experience and efficiencies of fleet management with Zipcar&rsquo;s proven, customer-friendly technology,&rdquo; said Avis Budget Group CEO Ronald Nelson, in a statement. </p>
 
 <p>But not everyone is convinced Zipcar will remain, well, Zipcar. Zipsters, as the company&rsquo;s fans are known, are worried the hip brand, which offers Minis and sleek hatchbacks in 20 cities in North America and Europe, will put on the ill-fitting suit of an airport car-rental firm, complete with bare-bones American sedans. If its cars lose their cool, so might Zipcar members. And Zipcar can ill afford to alienate its core customers. Despite a membership of 760,000, Zipcar has been stuck mostly in the red; it&rsquo;s expected to record its first profitable year in 2012. (Its stock price has remained well below its 2011 initial public offering price of $18.) And it&rsquo;s been plagued by service glitches. Benjamin Kabak, writer of the popular New York City transportation blog <em>2nd Ave</em>.<em> Sagas</em>, has been a member for 30 months, and says service is merely &ldquo;adequate.&rdquo; The first car he borrowed had an expired registration, and the battery in another car died on him, he says. </p>
 
 <p>Experts say Avis&rsquo;s experience may be just what Zipcar needs. For a start-up, Zipcar&rsquo;s logistics had became too much, says MIT business lecturer Howard Anderson. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s capital-intensive, labour-intensive, energy-intensive. They had very loyal customers, but it&rsquo;s time to step up to more professional management.&rdquo; To gain efficiencies, Zipcar will need to be remade to look a lot more like Avis. The name might survive, and profits might flow, but for fans, it would be the end of Zipcar as they know it.</p>
 
  <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
 
 


<slug>Railways </slug>
 <hedline>Idle on the tracks</hedline>
 
 <p>When the Aamjiwnaang First Nation in Sarnia, Ont., wanted to support hunger-striking Chief Theresa Spence they found a big and easy target in their backyard: the Canadian National Railway. Chief Chris Plain and about a dozen Idle No More supporters blocked the railway&rsquo;s spur line leading in and out of one of Canada&rsquo;s largest industrial complexes, Sarnia&rsquo;s Chemical Valley. &ldquo;It was an effort to target something that would get the federal government&rsquo;s attention,&rdquo; says Plain. </p>
 
 <p>If Ottawa didn&rsquo;t fully get the message, local industry did. CN and its customers took action, getting a court injunction on Dec. 21 to have the blockade removed. A week later, with protesters still there, CN was back in court saying jobs were at stake. The line is &ldquo;a major piece of infrastructure serving major industry,&rdquo; says CN spokesman Jim Feeny. &ldquo;If you interrupt any part of that, you have an effect on our operation but also on the customers.&rdquo; Imperial Oil scaled back gas production by 15 per cent due to the stoppage. The Canadian Propane Association warned that customers east of the city could soon face shortages. One of the biggest industries in the region, Nova Chemicals, also slowed production. With company lawyers calling the lack of rail service &ldquo;disastrous,&rdquo; it shut two chemical units and slowed production in its remaining unit. </p>
 
 <p>Last week, Justice John Desotti ordered the blockade cleared: &ldquo;You are an individual blocking the spur line affecting hundreds of people&rsquo;s employment,&rdquo; Desotti told a spokesman for the blockade. Losses are estimated to be in the millions. The Aamjiwnaang First Nation, however, doesn&rsquo;t regret the action. If anything, they have proven why railways are likely to continue to end up in the crosshairs of demonstrators. Several Via Rail trains were blocked by native protesters in late December, stranding 2,000 passengers. There have also been rail disruptions in eastern Quebec and Sault Ste. Marie, Ont. </p>
 
 <p>In Sarnia, while injunctions were issued, police were reluctant to make arrests for fear that matters would escalate. So while the tents stand on the rail lines and police look for a peaceful ending, industries can only sit by and wait.</p>
 
  <byline>Heather Wright</byline>


  <slug>Fashion </slug>
 <hedline>Filling the Gap</hedline>
 
 <p>Fashion&rsquo;s mania for mixing &ldquo;high&rdquo; and &ldquo;low&rdquo;&mdash;evident in Sharon Stone&rsquo;s pairing of a white Gap button-down shirt with a Vera Wang skirt at the 1998 Oscars&mdash;has become business reality with the Gap Inc.&rsquo;s $130-million purchase of upscale women&rsquo;s retailer Intermix Holdco Inc. The partnership furrowed a few Botoxed brows, but generally was viewed as win-win&mdash;an extension of the Gap&rsquo;s move into the multi-brand, premium arena initiated with its 2010 purchase of <em>Piperlime.com</em>. It gives the Gap a needed toehold in the luxury market for overseas expansion, as well as access to the fashion-forward savvy necessary to compete against Zara and H&amp;M. The plan is to expand Intermix, which will be run by existing management, well beyond its 28 North American stores. We won&rsquo;t ever see an Intermix next to every Gap, but bank on seeing its high-end patina deployed for the masses who shop at the mothership.</p>
 
  <byline>Anne Kingston</byline>
 


<slug>Agriculture </slug>
 <hedline>The potash hangover</hedline>
 
 <p>In 2010, when Ottawa blocked Australia&rsquo;s BHP Billiton&rsquo;s purchase of Potash Corp., the business was booming. Prices for the fertilizer seemed to be ever rising along with global demand. After BHP&rsquo;s bid was rejected (on the grounds it wouldn&rsquo;t be of net benefit to Canada), the company made plans to open its own $14-billion mine in Saskatchewan. Potash mining worldwide ramped up. </p>
 
 <p>But now the industry is experiencing a major hangover, with overcapacity and falling prices. Potash now sells at $425 per tonne, nearly half its peak price of $860 in 2009. Last month, Potash Corp. temporarily closed two Canadian mines for eight weeks, affecting 600 workers. BHP may be forced to halt construction of its new mine; one Bank of Montreal analyst noted that new capacity won&rsquo;t be needed &ldquo;for at least another decade.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Despite falling prices, many farmers view potash as a luxury they can&rsquo;t afford. In India, demand has dried up as farmers turn to cheaper alternatives like nitrogen-based urea. Executives remain hopeful, citing a deal this month between Canpotex Ltd., North America&rsquo;s biggest potash seller, and China&rsquo;s Sinofert Holdings Ltd. Even so, that deal is for $70 less per tonne than the last contract between the two firms, signed in March.</p>
 
  <byline>Ryan Mallough</byline>
 


 <slug>Bright Idea </slug>
 <hedline>eBay goes offline</hedline>
 
 <p>More people than ever are shopping on the Internet: Canadians placed nearly 114 million orders online in 2010, worth $15 billion, says Statistics Canada, in its most recent tally. To target those who might still be wary of online shopping, eBay is turning its attention to face-to-face contact. The online marketplace is trying out new services in the U.S., according to All Things D, including a pickup service that sends eBay employees into people&rsquo;s homes to collect items, which are then sold by &ldquo;expert sellers&rdquo; for a cut. Another encourages people to drop off clothes and electronics at mall kiosks, where they&rsquo;re offered a set price for their goods. eBay is also testing a same-day delivery service so buyers can get the same kind of instant gratification as in-store shopping. Meanwhile, Amazon is expanding its locker service, which allows customers to pick up packages at stores like 7-Eleven. For online giants, future growth seems to be in the offline world.</p>
 
 <byline>Kate Lunau</byline>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Society</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Economy </slug>
 
 <hedline>The new underclass</hedline>
 <abstract>Why an entire generation of ambitious, smart and well-educated young Canadians have no future. Charlie Gillis and Chris Sorensen report</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC01_YOUTHUNDERCLASS09.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Melanie Cullins, 28 Degree: applied linguistics Occupations: waitress, barista, baker</photo.caption>
 
 <photo.byline>Chad Hipolito</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Melanie Cullins is no pipe dreamer. She chose a vocation that, by unanimous opinion, represented a path to steady employment&mdash;teaching English as a second language to the thousands of immigrants pouring into B.C., a good many of whom, the experts predicted, would be making their way to Victoria, where she grew up and wished to make a home. That was back in the early 2000s, when opportunities for the young and industrious appeared unlimited. A rewarding career seemed within reach for all. </p>
 
 <p>Cullins&rsquo;s degree in applied linguistics was the gold standard of ESL qualifications. But she graduated in the thick of the 2008 financial meltdown, and the entry-level position she imagined would launch her career never materialized. Governments cut back on language transition programs. Resum&eacute;s piled up in recruitment offices. Her calls to program directors went unanswered. &ldquo;For me, that was a huge blow,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;I had almost perfect performance reviews from my practicums, but I couldn&rsquo;t even get an interview. You start to wonder: what&rsquo;s wrong with me?&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>She took temporary work to support herself&mdash;waitressing, schlepping latt&eacute;s, baking cupcakes in a family friend&rsquo;s caf&eacute;. She volunteered in an ESL classroom in order to beef up her C.V. Yet the weeks slipped by with nary a callback, and when she got pregnant 2&frac12; years ago, her dreams took a back seat to necessity. She took another stab at finding work in her field when her son Liam was old enough for day care. But by then, incredibly, the job market had worsened. Now, with her husband, Benjamin, doing contract work for the B.C. forest ministry, the 28-year-old wonders whether she&rsquo;ll ever attain a comfortable, middle-class life&mdash;a house, college funds for the kids, money left over for retirement. &ldquo;I have no pension plan. My husband has no pension or benefit plan,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re renters in one of the country&rsquo;s most expensive cities, and we&rsquo;d like to someday own a home. Once you have kids, these things really start to worry you. You&rsquo;re always thinking, &lsquo;Will I ever get ahead?&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
 
 <p> Many in Cullins&rsquo;s age bracket are asking themselves the same question. In Canada, as in the U.S. and Europe, workers in their 20s increasingly find themselves wandering the perimeters of their chosen careers. Youth unemployment in this country reached 15.2 per cent during the recent downturn, the highest level in two decades. Yet the top-line number fails to capture the depth of the problem. It turns out that most young people <em>are</em> working&mdash;typically in jobs well below their levels of qualification, and often outside their fields. Those lucky enough to get a toehold in their chosen professions have a hard time getting enough hours or pay to support themselves, statistics show. Yet they forge on, from unpaid internship to dead-end contract, giving the lie to depictions of a shiftless generation addled by an overdeveloped sense of entitlement. </p>
 
 <p>Labour-market experts refer to this as underemployment&mdash;a gross mismatch between people&rsquo;s skills and the jobs employers wish to fill. Even as young workers scramble for work, they note, companies are complaining about a shortage of engineers, technicians and other skilled tradespeople to fill positions in industries ranging from health care to mining. The problem is poorly understood because it arises from a constellation of forces: the decline of central Canada&rsquo;s manufacturing sector and the union jobs it sustained; relentless cost-cutting by corporations; the demographic bulge of older workers occupying high-skilled, well-paying positions; parents who pressed their kids into university, hoping they&rsquo;d get prestigious, white-collar jobs; and universities and colleges who indulged that urge despite the changing demands of the labour market. &ldquo;We&rsquo;ve injected more human capacity into the system,&rdquo; says Rock Lefebvre, the vice-president of research and standards with the Certified General Accountants Association of Canada, &ldquo;without a growth in opportunity for them to respond to.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The result is a growing pool of well-educated twentysomethings scrapping it out for a limited number of prized positions&mdash;a cohort one might describe as history&rsquo;s most cultivated underclass. Yesterday&rsquo;s stereotypical B.A. bussing tables now has a law degree. Or a B.Comm. in finance. And while he&rsquo;s not exactly roughing it&mdash;fully 42 per cent of Canadians between 20 and 29 are living with their parents&mdash;frustration is clearly setting in. &ldquo;People talk about the entitlement of the millennial generation,&rdquo; says Diana Bailey, a 24-year-old advertising student at Toronto&rsquo;s Humber College, who has found nothing better than an unpaid internship to sustain her after she graduates this spring. &ldquo;But in most cases, the only option that&rsquo;s being offered to us is indentured servitude.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p> </p>
 
 <p>The warning signs were there for anyone who cared to look. At last count, in 2006, nearly one in four young workers with a university education was toiling in a job that didn&rsquo;t require a degree (the proportion is believed to be higher now, following the recession). Some 6.4 per cent of Canada&rsquo;s total workforce&mdash;1.2 million people&mdash;now consists of part-time workers under 30 who wish they could work full time. </p>
 
 <p>Equally troubling, university-educated Canadians experienced a relative increase in unemployment between 1997 and 2005 and a corresponding dip in relative wages, according to a federal government study. By contrast, those with a college, or even a high school education, managed to improve (or at least maintain) their outlook, relative to other workers. In fact, the only group that experienced a similar relative increase in unemployment during the period were those Canadians without even a high school diploma. </p>
 
 <p>It all goes against the narrative that&rsquo;s been drilled into young Canadians over the past few decades: a university education is the ticket to a good job and a comfortable existence. While many have dutifully followed that advice (university enrolment has more than doubled since the early 1980s), even those lucky enough to land a decent job can&rsquo;t afford the rising entry fee to the middle class. Saddled with student debt, they face a world where buying a house seems like an improbable dream&mdash;the average selling price of a detached home in Toronto was $722,393 and $904,200 in Vancouver in December&mdash;and employers increasingly expect workers to pay for their own retirements. That&rsquo;s not easy when you don&rsquo;t have money. A survey by the Bank of Montreal found that only about 10 per cent of Canadians aged 18 to 34 had given any thought to retirement planning. </p>
 
 <p>Bailey says it&rsquo;s as though the promise of a comfortable life was held out before her, then jerked away at the last second. &ldquo;My generation is told not to expect the stuff our parents had, that there&rsquo;ll be no job security or benefits,&rdquo; says the 24-year-old, who left English studies at the University of Toronto because she thought Humber&rsquo;s four-year advertising degree offered a surer route to employment. &ldquo;Intellectually, I can understand that might be true. But I can&rsquo;t imagine what it looks like.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>She contrasts her plight to that of her dad&rsquo;s parents, blue-collar workers who nevertheless lived in an era of optimism. &ldquo;They had families and a nice, comfortable life with nine-to-five jobs and vacations in Bermuda,&rdquo; says Bailey. So did her parents, who had fulfilling careers with the City of Toronto. Bailey herself has found nothing better in her field than an unpaid, 14-week internship, which she can&rsquo;t take because she needs to pay her rent. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t know if I&rsquo;ll ever own a house,&rdquo; she says ruefully. </p>
 
 <p> </p>
 
 <p>It wasn&rsquo;t always so bleak for Canada&rsquo;s youth. Wayne Lewchuk, a professor of labour studies at Hamilton&rsquo;s McMaster University, grew up in Windsor, Ont., and recalls that many of his university buddies took assembly-plant jobs with Chrysler and Ford after graduating in the mid-1970s. The work wasn&rsquo;t great, but it paid well and the benefits were good. &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re measuring life purely by your material standard of living, then they&rsquo;ve had a much better life than I&rsquo;ve had,&rdquo; says Lewchuk, who instead went back to school to pursue two more degrees. &ldquo;They started working 10 years before I even got my first paycheque.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Of course, most of those automotive jobs are long gone. So are many other relatively high-paying factory jobs in Ontario and Quebec. They are casualties of globalization and Canada&rsquo;s subsequent shift toward a &ldquo;knowledge-based economy&rdquo;&mdash;one that&rsquo;s built on providing services instead of forging things out of plastic and steel. At the same time, the global commodity boom that began around 2003 refocused attention on Canada&rsquo;s vast resources, particularly oil and gas. But despite the billions poured into Alberta&rsquo;s oil sands, there&rsquo;s mounting evidence to suggest that Canadian workers, collectively, are no better off. The CGA study, for example, suggested the proportion of workers employed in industries with above-average earnings declined between 1991 and 2011, despite strong overall growth in the economy. </p>
 
 <p>Wages are only part of the picture. Unions, once the guarantor of a comfortable middle-class lifestyle, have shrivelled as employers cut back on pension and health care benefits in a bid to better compete in a globalized market. Indeed, the very concept of a gold-plated, defined-benefit corporate pension plan (which guarantees a certain level of retirement income) has all but disappeared. A recent study by the debt-rating agency, Dominion Bond Rating Service, found that as many as two-thirds of North American defined-benefit plans are underfunded. Many companies are pushing new employees over to less costly and less comprehensive defined-contribution plans. </p>
 
 <p>Job security is also increasingly scarce. Stung by the 2009 recession, employers in industries ranging from retail sales to information technology are preoccupied with building a flexible workforce that can be upsized or downsized to match the peaks and troughs of the economic cycle. A recent survey by consulting firm McKinsey &amp; Co. found that 65 per cent of U.S. corporations cut jobs since the last recession, and that nearly half planned to use more part-time or temporary workers as business returned. Canada has experienced a similar rise in temporary and contract work over the past 15 years, according to Statistics Canada. </p>
 
 <p>Lewchuk describes the cumulative impact of the changes as a &ldquo;hollowing out of the middle&rdquo; of the Canadian job market. &ldquo;There&rsquo;s been growth at the top&mdash;there&rsquo;s more good, white-collar jobs than there used to be&mdash;but we have fewer middle jobs, and more bad jobs,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;So the problem now is if you get one of those bad jobs, even out of university, there&rsquo;s no middle rung for you to go to. The next step up is a good job&mdash;being a lawyer or software engineer.&rdquo; Needless to say, the leap from sales clerk to a triple-digit salary isn&rsquo;t a short one. &ldquo;I think that&rsquo;s what some of these kids are experiencing when they come out of university,&rdquo; says Lewchuk. &ldquo;They&rsquo;re stuck in that bottom tier and they&rsquo;re just not seeing a path to a better job&mdash;ever.&rdquo;</p>
 
 <p> </p>
 
 <p>A cruel irony for frustrated young job seekers is that Canada is actually in the grips of a massive labour shortage. A recent survey of employers by recruiting firm Randstad Canada found that nearly two-thirds were having trouble finding highly qualified people. Why, then, aren&rsquo;t young, educated Canadians being courted by employers at every turn? Mainly because they don&rsquo;t have the skills corporate Canada is looking for. The culprit, according to business leaders, is three decades of parents and teachers extolling the virtues of a university degree, encouraging youth to become doctors, lawyers or teachers. Meanwhile, the economy has been busy stamping out new jobs in all sorts of other industries. &ldquo;There&rsquo;s a big gap between what people like to study in school and what the market demands,&rdquo; says Jan Hein Bax, Randstad Canada&rsquo;s president. He points to the high demand for engineers in the oil sands and other resource sectors: &ldquo;While we&rsquo;re seeing more people with university degrees, they don&rsquo;t necessarily have that sort of background.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The problem is particularly acute in the skilled trades. A recent report by the Canadian Imperial Bank of Commerce suggested that industries like health care, advanced manufacturing, mining and business services are all facing shortages of skilled workers. Taken together, those industries represent a full fifth of all Canadian jobs. The proof is in the numbers. Unemployment in those industries stands at just over one per cent, compared to 7.2 per cent for the workforce as a whole, according the report. Wages paid to workers in those sectors are rising at an annual rate of 3.9 per cent, while employees in other industries are seeing no wage growth at all. </p>
 
 <p>In an effort to close the gap, the federal government is planning to bring in as many as 3,000 foreign skilled workers this year by de-emphasizing the university-educated and focusing instead on welders and electricians. But a longer-term solution would ideally involve Canadians filling some of those vacant jobs. Sarah Anson-Cartwright, the director of skills policy for the Canadian Chamber of Commerce, says a first step is to combat the stigma still attached to skilled trades. She suggests promoting college and apprenticeship programs more actively in high schools. &ldquo;Because of the demand for these jobs, people who discover them go on to earn really decent incomes,&rdquo; she says. </p>
 
 <p>It will be easier said than done. Young people aren&rsquo;t blindly enrolling in university because guidance counsellors told them to. They&rsquo;re taking a calculated risk. With employment becoming more temporary and offering fewer long-term benefits, many are, quite rationally, opting for a similarly flexible approach to the job market. &ldquo;The risk of these trade jobs is that technical change comes along and wipes your trade out,&rdquo; Lewchuk says. &ldquo;That doesn&rsquo;t happen to lawyers, doctors and academics.&rdquo; The risks are further compounded by the fact that few companies are willing to pay for retraining, or, increasingly, any training at all. A study last year by the Conference Board of Canada found that investment in employee training among Canadian companies has fallen nearly 40 per cent since 1993. &ldquo;We&rsquo;ve done things to ourselves that perpetuate this problem,&rdquo; argues Lewchuk, pointing at Ottawa&rsquo;s revamped foreign skilled workers program. &ldquo;This has an impact on employers who are saying, &lsquo;Why should I incur the cost of training someone when I can plead poverty and get someone from Mexico or Brazil to come and do the job at a lower wage?&rsquo;&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Economists say the market will eventually sort itself out. Wages and benefits in the trades should become more attractive as desperate employers try to woo new workers. Universities will be compelled to overhaul programs to ensure more graduates find work&mdash;a key statistic that helps keep enrolment up. In the meantime, young people who are currently unemployed or stuck in go-nowhere jobs may have to rethink their approach. Those who are willing to relocate and build on their degrees&mdash;either by attending college or completing an apprenticeship&mdash;will find plenty of attractive opportunities in a range of growing fields, says Anson-Cartwright. &ldquo;There&rsquo;s a real need for continuous learning. There won&rsquo;t be lifetime jobs for young people. We&rsquo;re all going to have to come to grips with that.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Tom Pinnington counts among those unwilling to sit on his hands. After graduating from the University of Toronto in 2011, the 23-year-old from Ottawa quickly realized the value of his degree in history and political science&mdash;or lack thereof. More useful, he says, were the interpersonal skills he&rsquo;d honed waiting tables at high-end Toronto restaurants while going to school. &ldquo;That&rsquo;s always been my strength,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;Now I&rsquo;ve just got to find a way to use it in a way that&rsquo;s conducive to success.&rdquo; To that end, he&rsquo;s working two jobs&mdash;at an Ottawa bistro and an outdoor-wear store&mdash;until he has enough money to start his own restaurant. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Do I wish that I could be in a job that allowed me to research history and make a good living? Absolutely,&rdquo; says Pinnington. &ldquo;But when have people been able to get into a job that is directly pertinent to what they studied?&rdquo; To him, a middle-class lifestyle is something one goes and gets, and he&rsquo;s not worried by the prospect of never having a pension plan or never owning a house. &ldquo;So far, I&rsquo;ve been able to take care of myself,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;I hope to be able to do so in the future.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Cullins, too, excels at working with people. Yet after four years of underemployment, the Victoria native doesn&rsquo;t share Pinnington&rsquo;s optimism. Openings in her profession come up from time to time, she notes. But internal candidates get first dibs, and she worries about the growing gap on her resum&eacute; between her graduation and the present. She hasn&rsquo;t given up. After having her second child last fall, Cullins is looking into a distance-education program in social work, so she can enhance her degree while chasing a job. &ldquo;But I feel like I went through four years of education to get what I thought were very practical qualifications,&rdquo; she laments. &ldquo;I worked my butt off. Now it looks like it wasn&rsquo;t enough.&rdquo; </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Society</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>Education </slug>
 <hedline>The million-dollar promise </hedline>
 
 <abstract>A university degree was once a guarantee of higher incomes. Those days are gone, argue two profs.</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_MILLIONDOLLAR01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Cost of education: About 60 per cent of graduates carry debt; the average is $24,600</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>ANDREW VAUGHAN/CP</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>The message to young people is simple. If you want an extra million dollars, maybe more, just get a university degree. Your lifetime earnings will be at least that much more than those of someone with only a high school education. Or so says the Association of Universities and Colleges of Canada (AUCC), quoting the 2006 census. </p>
 
 <p>The university establishment does not lack confidence on this matter. In September 2012, Paul Davidson, president of the AUCC, quoted a more impressive statistic: &ldquo;While it is true that tuition has increased in recent years, so too has the value of a degree. The income premium of a university degree is large and growing. University graduates will on average earn $1.3 million more during their careers than a high school graduate and $1 million more than a college grad.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>This number&mdash;the $1-million promise&mdash;has been around for quite some time, pretty much unchallenged. It is time to pose some simple questions about it. Do university graduates actually earn $1.3 million more than high school graduates? If you assume a working career of 40 years&mdash;ages 26 to 65&mdash;the return represents a $32,500 annual &ldquo;bonus&rdquo; over the earnings of a high school graduate, and $25,000 over a college graduate&rsquo;s. Is the university degree the critical factor in determining the extra income earned by degree holders? Does the field of study matter? </p>
 
 <p>For parents planning their children&rsquo;s future and for young adults contemplating their career options, the million-dollar promise is extremely attractive. It is not just the money; it is also the implied guarantee of a place in the Canadian middle class. The implicit message is that university graduates will not have to drive a bus or staff an assembly line. Most Canadian parents want their children to have white-collar office positions, not the kind of resource-based or industrial jobs for which there is still a strong demand. </p>
 
 <p>But is the million-dollar promise something students can bank on, or is it misleading? University graduates as a group will indeed earn more than those without degrees. But if you ask if an individual student will make this much more money, the answer is a resounding &ldquo;maybe.&rdquo; The averages are accurate. But the number applies to all university graduates, everyone from medical doctors, chemical engineers and accountants to&mdash;whom shall we pick?&mdash;graduates in cultural studies, arts, or biology. Some lawyers, for example, make $1.3 million in a couple of years, not 40. As many university graduates have learned to their dismay, the university degree that leads to prosperity can also lead to unemployment, a string of part-time jobs or, more common in current economic times, underemployment&mdash;a low-paid, low-skilled position at $30,000 a year, barely above the average for high school graduates. Averages are just averages. </p>
 
 <p>Here&rsquo;s a personal example of what we mean. Bill Morrison, who co-wrote this story, spent more than 40 years as a university teacher and administrator. After 35 years, his salary was about $120,000, an impressive sum. His son-in-law Jeremy, a high school graduate, is a heavy-duty mechanic with on-the-job apprenticeship training who works for Finning, the big Canadian firm that services heavy machinery. Three or four years ago, Jeremy&rsquo;s salary was $5,000 higher, due to overtime, than Bill&rsquo;s. Bill was then 65, started his university position in his late twenties, and held three degrees. Jeremy&rsquo;s starting salary was around $75,000, not bad for a young man in his twenties holding no degrees. People with Ph.D.s lucky enough to find a permanent university position begin at about the same salary. Both Bill and Jeremy love what they are doing, but using expected income as a reason to take a university degree is misleading. </p>
 
 <p>This reality does not deter universities. The $1-million promise shows up prominently in university promotional materials and recruiters&rsquo; presentations. The University of Victoria&rsquo;s website, for example, cites the AUCC study and provides supporting graphs, summarizing the likely outcomes: $35,000 in average incomes for college graduates, $45,000 for bachelor&rsquo;s graduates, $60,000 for master&rsquo;s graduates, and $65,000 for doctoral graduates. The steady progression is a huge incentive to stay the course and stick with university, continuing to second and third degrees. </p>
 
 <p>University degrees are in many ways a wonderful investment. Four years of advanced study by motivated and intelligent students provides a terrific opportunity for personal growth. Learning for the sake of learning has great merit, both for the individual and for society at large. The problem arises with the reason why students go to university. If it is to broaden their horizons, learn a skill useful to humanity, or steep themselves in knowledge, then the decision is a fine one. If the motive is money, students may be setting themselves up for serious disappointment. </p>
 
 <p>Not only is focusing on money the wrong basis on which to make a decision about attending university, it sheds light on a serious weakness in the rationale: the idea that most worthwhile jobs require a university degree. Canada has massive shortages in the skilled trades. We are trying to import thousands of technical workers, some from places as far afield as Romania. Meanwhile, many people with undergraduate arts and science degrees, who used to find jobs in government offices, banks and corporate middle management, struggle to land decent-paying jobs, let alone ones with a promising career path. </p>
 
 <p>Another issue is student debt. About 60 per cent of all graduating students carry debt, and the average amount owed is $24,600. Imagine a worst-case scenario, in which a student takes more than four years to graduate, and accumulates a debt of $40,000, only to find herself underemployed as a barista, making $25,000 a year. What is the return on her investment in the &#64257;rst 10 years after graduation? </p>
 
 <p>Career prospects and incomes for university graduates vary. While employment prospects in some fields are terrific&mdash;nanotechnologists, economists, nurses and other professionals have impressive career possibilities&mdash;the same is not necessarily true for other academic programs. Competitive-entry, high-quality programs, such as an M.B.A. from an elite school, or a medical degree, offer an impressive return on investment; others do not. It helps to look at the numbers. The latest available are from the 2006 census and were crunched by the Statistics Canada Research Data Centre at McMaster University. They show that the average income for university graduates aged 26 to 35 was $42,176, a decent sum, but not what most university students expect to be earning a decade after they graduate. A closer examination reveals the problem with such generalizations. Using the same data, a female English undergraduate degree holder earned $30,762, well above the $19,000 of a female high school graduate, but below the $32,343 earned by male high school graduates. The numbers for film studies majors were lower, $26,172 for men and $25,447 for women. Lower still were music graduates, at $19,348 and $20,814. Even science graduates don&rsquo;t do as well as most people imagine. Physics graduates earned $40,216 for men and $31,545 for women. Contrast these numbers with the much higher wages for civil engineering ($60,000 for males, $49,924 for females), business administration ($48,405 and $39,295), finance ($55,919 and $42,182), nursing ($53,764 and $47,985), law ($56,975 and $50,000) and pharmacy ($88,425 and $71,493). While gender is obviously important, degree choice can matter as much as the decision to go to university in the first place. </p>
 
 <p>Think about these figures for a moment. Are music graduates going to make $1.3 million more over their careers than unionized construction workers? Obviously not and, of course, no one gets a university degree in music for the money. For a musician, the million-dollar promise is irrelevant as well as false. Musicians do what they love to do, and we are the better for it. </p>
 
 <p>In the current economic situation, prospective teachers need a similar passion for teaching, because many may not be able to make much money at it. Consider the situation facing newly minted teachers. Entry to a teachers&rsquo; college is highly competitive, for teaching holds the prospect of a solid, well-paid, middle-class life. But demographic shifts have resulted in the closure of schools and a great reduction in the number of teachers. According to the Ontario College of Teachers, just under a third of the 2010 graduating class was unemployed the following year. And almost half of the graduates described themselves as underemployed, with only supply teaching or a non-teaching job. The Ontario government responded by reducing the number of spots in education programs, and even contemplated the odd step of doubling the length of the teacher-education programs. The graduates who do get full-time teaching positions will have stable incomes; many others face uncertainty, short-term positions and a much lower-than-expected income. </p>
 
 <p>The prospect for academic success&mdash;defined as completing a degree&mdash;is another factor to consider when assessing the net value of attending university. Close to one-quarter of first-year students fail. As many as a third do not finish their degrees. This is partly because, as universities scramble to pay their bills and meet government and public demands for wider accessibility, admission standards have dropped, a fact masked by the inflation in high school grades. The $1-million promise applies only to people who graduate. If the incomes of everyone who ever enrolled in university were included in the calculation, the $1-million gap would undoubtedly shrivel dramatically. </p>
 
 <p>Traditionally, bachelor of arts and bachelor of science graduates started their careers at a lower salary than applied science and professional university graduates, but caught up by mid-career. They did so because of the uniformly high general skill level of B.A. and B.Sc. graduates and the small number of such graduates relative to the size of the then-expanding Canadian middle class. According to research on the experience of B.A. graduates conducted by John Goyder, past president of the Canadian Sociological Association, this advantage has eroded. For instance, with business schools producing thousands of graduates each year for middle-management positions, and with the relative number of those positions falling, the growing legion of B.A. and B.Sc. graduates find fewer opportunities. The $1-million promise worked for university graduates in the 1960s and 1970s&mdash;people now at the peak of their earning potential. But, as Goyder&rsquo;s work shows, it does not appear to be working in the 21st century. Indeed, underemployment is becoming more common among university graduates, particularly for those without a specialized or professional degree. </p>
 
 <p>More distressing, and here we rely on American studies, there is evidence that the intellectual benefits of a degree have been overhyped. When universities complain about worsening student-to-faculty ratios, huge first-year classes and limited student-faculty interaction, it follows that many students are not getting the personalized attention needed to remedy their shortcomings and to capitalize on the intellectual and skills benefits of an undergraduate education. In their provocative 2011 book, <em>Academically Adrift</em>, Richard Arum and Josipa Roksa demonstrate that university students in the U.S. show very little progress in critical thinking and core intellectual development. This indictment, they say, strikes at the very heart of the university enterprise. Rather than guaranteeing that a university graduate has sophisticated critical thinking, writing and analytical abilities, institutions can say only that undergraduates and graduates in the non-professional fields had the opportunity to gain these crucial career-ready skills. </p>
 
 <p>In reality, a major factor in predicting future earnings and career success is family background. Many of the students going to Canadian universities come from wealthier, better-educated families. Parental income is a key indicator of the academic progress and career earnings of offspring. Research in the U.S. shows that a substantial portion of the income boost connected to a university degree is due in fact to a combination of personal qualities and family background, assisted by the university education. Smart, hard-working, well-connected young people from well-off families will do well, despite their educational background. </p>
 
 <p>Parental income aside, talent and character are probably as good predictors of future success as is a university degree. University graduates should be compared, not to high school graduates, but to young people who could have gone to university but did not. Comparing these cohorts would produce a more useful indication of the actual career value of a university degree. A U.S. study that compared high school graduates who attended Ivy League schools with those accepted to these institutions, but who did not go, showed that these expensive institutions added little to the career or earning experience of their students. Talent, not a diploma, wins out in the end. Furthermore, a substantial number of students with a high school diploma are not capable of attending university successfully.&nbsp; So, why do universities compare their graduates to them? </p>
 
 <p>It is quite possible that the long period in which universities enjoyed unquestioning public support and generous public subsidies may be coming to an end. Canadian universities have done well since the 1950s, a period when governments provided billions for research and new facilities. Enrolment soared and tuition rates climbed faster than inflation. </p>
 
 <p>While universities wanted to believe that the spike in enrolment sprang from government and public commitment to the value of learning and the preparation of an educated citizenry, most everyone knew this was not the real motivation. The core rationale was much more basic: university graduates supposedly got better jobs and higher incomes. Even better, the high-income university graduates paid more taxes, thus repaying the state&rsquo;s investment. </p>
 
 <p>If universities were honest about the question of career opportunities and income, they would say this: &ldquo;The top performing students, particularly those in high-demand technical and professional fields, have very good employment prospects and will likely make impressive incomes. Students in more general areas of study and, particularly, those who fall short in skill level, motivation and work ethic, will likely struggle after graduation. Many students will, if academically capable, have to continue to an advanced degree; a growing number will have to continue their studies at a community college in order to prepare for the workforce. Plan accordingly.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>One of the sadder aspects of the overselling of a university education is the deprecation of a community college and technical education. In the public&rsquo;s mind, going to university holds great promise; college is second-best. The implication is that talented young people go to university and the less able attend college. This was never entirely true, but is much less so now. Canada has an impressive network of community colleges, one of the best in the world. </p>
 
 <p>For those ready for the challenge and the opportunity, university remains a special and wonderful option. If they are young adults of broad curiosity, comfortable in the world of ideas and discovery, and want to explore the depth and breadth of the academy, then they are truly welcome on any campus. They will leave richer for the university experience, whatever their later income may be. But getting a degree without paying close attention to career aspirations&mdash;through co-op programs, proper summer jobs and volunteer activity&mdash;is a recipe for post-graduation disappointment. Students need to start their academic careers by: doing careful research about the Canadian workforce; carefully choosing their institutions and programs of study; and reflecting carefully on their reasons for attending university. They must also be willing to commit to the demanding and intense university work required of devoted students. The intellectual and personal benefits of a university degree are there for all students who truly want them. Just don&rsquo;t count on that million-dollar bonus. <byline>Ken Coates and Bill Morrison </byline>
 </p>
 
 <p>Ken Coates and Bill Morrison are authors of <em>Campus Confidential: 100 Startling Things You Don&rsquo;t Know About Canadian Universities</em>. Ken Coates is Canada Research Chair in regional innovation at the University of Saskatchewan; Bill Morrison is a professor emeritus of history at the University of Northern British Columbia.</p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Society</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 
 <slug>Photo Essay </slug>
 <hedline>The Ultimate Slide</hedline>
 
 <byline>Ryan Mallough</byline>
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_PHOTOESSAY_ICE04.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_PHOTOESSAY_ICE02.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_PHOTOESSAY_ICE03.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_PHOTOESSAY_ICE01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Cavernous: Ice in caves is not uncommon, but Booming&rsquo;s size makes it unique. &lsquo;The proportions of this room are immense. It makes you feel very small and insignificant,&rsquo; says De Ruydts.</photo.caption>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Long way down: The 1.6-million-year- old cavern extends 140 m into the earth</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <body.content>
 
 <p>The Booming Ice Chasm, named for its ringing echoes, was first explored back in 2008, by a team from the Alberta Speleological Society led by Chas Yonge. Yonge stumbled on the chasm&rsquo;s entrance, near Crow&rsquo;s Nest Pass on the southern end of the Alberta-British Columbia border, by accident while en route to an established cave. In July, Vancouver-based photographer Francois-Xavier De Ruydts joined the only expedition to explore, survey and photograph a new passage there. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;I have never seen anything like it before,&rdquo; says De Ruydts. &ldquo;The ground is made up of hard, blue and very thick ice that forms a slide straight to the bottom of the cave.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Being in such a place is indescribable,&rdquo; adds the 31-year-old. &ldquo;The ice on the ground is so transparent. You feel like you&rsquo;re flying.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>De Ruydts&rsquo; pictures will help explorers further understand the caves. &ldquo;The headlamps used by cavers aren&rsquo;t powerful enough to get a good view of the cave,&rdquo; says De Ruydts, who brought portable lights for the shoot. &ldquo;The photos allowed us to get a real sense of the size of the room for the first time.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The chasm is known as a &ldquo;cold-trap&rdquo; cave because the cold winter air sinks to the bottom and is unable to circulate. This phenomenon insulates the cave from any warmer air, keeping temperatures below freezing and making ice present year-round. Slight temperature variations can alter the ice thickness from one to two metres between summer and winter. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not a place frozen in time,&rdquo; says De Ruydts, &ldquo;but definitely a dynamic environment.&rdquo; 
 </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Film</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Twin nightmares </hedline>
 
 <abstract>American Mary has made Jen and Sylvia Soska global sensations on the cult horror circuit</abstract>
 
 <byline>Brian D. Johnson</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_TERRORTWINS01.jpg"></photo>
 
  <photo.caption>Directing and acting duo: Casting themselves as femme-fatale auteurs, the Soska twins have carved out a unique brand</photo.caption>
 
  
 <photo.byline>PHOTOGRAPH BY BRIAN HOWELL; Courtesy of IndustryWorks Pictures</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Most people had never heard of them, but by the time they left, everyone was talking about them. The Soska twins were by no means the biggest stars to visit last month&rsquo;s Whistler Film Festival, where the guest list was led by Daniel Radcliffe, a.k.a. Harry Potter. But Radcliffe showed up in a beige sweater and rumpled jeans. The Soska twins hit the red carpet in matching skin-tight fetish gear&mdash;low-cut nurse uniforms, with hot pants and black vinyl aprons. The occasion was the late-night premiere of <em>American Mary</em>, a sinister little movie about surgical body modification that has made the twins a global sensation on the cult horror circuit. </p>
 
 <p>From David Cronenberg to Atom Egoyan, Canadian &#64257;lmmakers have a reputation for romancing the weird, but none personifies kink with as much brazen relish as Vancouver&rsquo;s Jen and Sylvia Soska, 29-year-old identical twins. Sibling director duos are strangely common. But they all seem to be guys&mdash;the brothers Coen, Farrelly, Dardenne, Duplass, Hughes, Schlossberg, Weitz and Wachowski (although Larry Wachowski has switched sexes to become Lana). Casting themselves as femme-fatale auteurs, the Soska twins have carved out a unique brand. </p>
 
 <p><em>American Mary</em>, their second feature, is the tale of a medical student, played by Vancouver&rsquo;s Katharine Isabelle (<em>Ginger Snaps</em>), who takes surgical revenge on date-raping doctors. It scored an international release from Universal Pictures, along with separate deals with U.S., Canadian and Australian distributors. And its success is almost entirely fan-driven. The twins have been touring the world with the movie, charming fanboys and fangirls, in Cannes, San Diego&rsquo;s Comic-Con, London&rsquo;s Fright Fest, L.A.&rsquo;s Monsterpalooza&mdash;and Toronto&rsquo;s After Dark Film Festival, where it took four prizes. &ldquo;The film is playing well all over,&rdquo; says Chris Alexander, editor of <em>Fangoria</em>, a Canadian horror magazine. &ldquo;What you see on screen is an extension of the twins&rsquo; personas. They&rsquo;re shameless, but they understand that you have to be. And they have the courage of their convictions.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Touring with<em> American Mary</em>, the twins have been working their fan base like campaigning politicians; this week, they begin a seven-city British tour. &ldquo;We really put ourselves into it,&rdquo; says Sylvia. &ldquo;Every time someone messaged us online, we&rsquo;d get back to them.&rdquo; In promoting the feminist revenge fantasy of <em>American Mary</em>, the twins would play their roles to the hilt, modelling their look on Vargas girls. &ldquo;We dyed our hair black, and had the black eyeliner and red lips,&rdquo; says Sylvie, &ldquo;and we&rsquo;d show up identically dressed, which we don&rsquo;t normally do.&rdquo; It&rsquo;s early morning in Whistler, and the twins have both donned full makeup for our interview, although they&rsquo;ve barely slept after blazing the festival party trail until 5 a.m. Yet they are shockingly articulate as they tell their story in polished anecdotes, finishing each other other&rsquo;s sentences with the tandem energy of a rock duo trading refrains. </p>
 
 <p>The Soska twins have been hooked on horror since they were kids, devouring their parents&rsquo; Stephen King novels. &ldquo;I remember being called into school because the teacher thought it was inappropriate,&rdquo; says their mother, Agnes, a retired BC Liquor Stores employee. Both she and her husband, Marion, a graphic designer, are eastern European immigrants and horror fans. The girls &ldquo;would always be peeking around the corner&rdquo; if their parents were watching a scary movie, Agnes recalls. &ldquo;We tried to explain that what they were seeing was just a lot of special effects.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The sisters have been acting from the age of 7. &ldquo;When you&rsquo;re an identical twin,&rdquo; explains Sylvie, &ldquo;it&rsquo;s not so much that you have talent, but they want two of the exact same thing for child labour laws. But as soon as we hit puberty, roles for identical twins changed to over-the-top sexualized. We were bikini girls, sexy co-eds, sexy aliens, sexy everything.&rdquo; The twins were both straight-A students, and &ldquo;when you have a brain,&rdquo; says Jen, &ldquo;you can do those roles only so many times before you hurt yourself intellectually.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Trained in mixed martial arts, the sisters took a stab at becoming stunt actors. &ldquo;We thought, &lsquo;We&rsquo;ll still be in bikinis, but we&rsquo;ll be on fire and thrown through things,&rsquo; &rdquo; says Sylvia. In 2007, hopes of a stunt career drew them to a pricey film school that didn&rsquo;t deliver. &ldquo;It was a good way to waste $20,000 each,&rdquo; says Sylvia. &ldquo;We had just $200 to make a movie and they cut our funding.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>But the twins got even. Their eureka moment came when they went to see Quentin Tarantino&rsquo;s <em>Grindhouse</em> anthology. It was preceded by a fake trailer for <em>Hobo with a Shotgun</em>, a horror film that Canadian director Jason Eisener had not yet made. &ldquo;We walk out of the theatre,&rdquo; says Sylvia, &ldquo;and Jen turns to me and goes, &lsquo;Dead Hooker in a Trunk!&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>That became the title for their own fake trailer, which they sprang on their show-and-tell graduation ceremony as a prank. The school had a list of banned subjects for student films, and the twins crammed every one of them into their short&mdash;plus necrophilia and bestiality (&ldquo;which the school forgot to put on the list&rdquo;). The film screened last, sight-unseen, to a chaotic mix of revulsion and laughter. And the grindhouse girls were born. </p>
 
 <p>Inspired by Roberto Rodriguez&rsquo;s DIY feature debut, <em>Desperado</em>, the Soskas went on to make <em>Dead Hooker in a Trunk</em> as a micro-budget feature, maxing out their credit cards and calling in favours. Both practising Roman Catholics, they shot much of the movie in their church. The location was donated, along with the houses of some fellow churchgoers. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re probably<em> the</em> most accepting Catholics,&rdquo; says Jen, pointing out that <em>Dead Hooker</em> is riddled with Biblical references, and that she and her sister were Western Canada&rsquo;s first female altar servers. </p>
 
 <p>The twins sent their first feature to the six directors of <em>Grindhouse</em>, and drew an enthusiastic response from Eli Roth. They also submitted it to film festivals. &ldquo;But on title alone, they would not show it,&rdquo; says Sylvia. &ldquo;We were like, &lsquo;Did you watch it? It&rsquo;s a dark satire.&rsquo; And they&rsquo;re like, &lsquo;We don&rsquo;t show those kinds of movies.&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>But <em>Dead Hooker </em>found a fan in Hannah Neurotica, who runs the feminist horror zine <em>Ax Wound</em> and created Women in Horror Month in February 2010. Soon the movie was the talk of the international cult horror circuit. But they met resistance in their own country. At Saskatoon&rsquo;s Dark Bridges Film Festival, their Canadian premiere was cancelled after the theatre owner balked at the title. &ldquo;It is very tongue-in-cheek,&rdquo; says Sylvia. &ldquo;People have arms ripped off and are set on fire and have teeth pulled out. But I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;d want to get out of bed if I wasn&rsquo;t doing something like that.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>With <em>American Mary</em>, the twins tackled a much slicker production, and their parents mortgaged their house to help finance it. <em>Fangoria</em>&rsquo;s Alexander calls it &ldquo;a quantum leap&rdquo; after <em>Dead Hooker</em>. &ldquo;It has style to burn,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s got the classic mad-scientist sensibility with this tie-you-up, cut-you-up thing that kids want today. But it&rsquo;s very elegant and not sexually explicit.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p><em>American Mary</em> is riddled with astute references, from its nod to Mary Harron&rsquo;s <em>American Psycho</em> to a shot of Isabelle in red surgical scrubs that echoes Cronenberg&rsquo;s <em>Dead Ringers</em>. But the Soskas are facelifting horror archetypes with their own brand of genre modification. &ldquo;You see Freddie, you see Pinhead, you see Jason, but you rarely see a female character like that,&rdquo; says Sylvia, who describes Mary as a mix of heroine and psychopath. &ldquo;You hear, &lsquo;Oh, women don&rsquo;t have that capacity for evil.&rsquo; But I&rsquo;m a woman. I know the crazy thoughts that go through my head sometimes.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>In conversation, the twins come across as sweet, charming and smart. But they&rsquo;ve cultivated such a dark image&mdash;augmented by cameos in their films&mdash;that they tend to scare off potential boyfriends. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re married to our careers,&rdquo; says Jen, &ldquo;although we&rsquo;re willing to have affairs with actual human beings. It rarely works that way. Our first goal is our work, second comes each other, and most guys aren&rsquo;t okay with being third. Festivals are not the place to look for a relationship. I compare it to being a guide dog: when I&rsquo;m working, you can&rsquo;t pet me.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Sylvie is more categorical: &ldquo;We&rsquo;re undatable, and after this movie, we&rsquo;re even more undatable.&rdquo; When <em>American Mary</em> showed at the market in Cannes, she recalls, &ldquo;a gentleman started hitting on me. He said, &lsquo;What are you doing here?&rsquo; I said, &lsquo;I&rsquo;m here for the movie, which I made with my sister.&rsquo; He said, &lsquo;I hope it&rsquo;s good.&rsquo; The movie plays, he looks at me, grabs his coat and speed-walks out. There you go.&rdquo;  </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Books</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Creating the poetry bug </hedline>
 
 <abstract>After 11 years and $120,000 in research, Christian B&ouml;k has put words to DNA</abstract>
 
  <byline>Anthony A. Davis</byline>

 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_DNA01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Living verse: A harmless bacterium, Deinococcus radiodurans, can store and reproduce Christian B&ouml;k&rsquo;s poem&mdash;and then write its own </photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>photograph by Chris Bolin</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m the poet who does the impossible thing. I am the poet who aspires to have the biggest imagination in the room,&rdquo; Christian B&ouml;k says bluntly. Yet his grandiose inventiveness has been focused on the most minuscule attempt at verse. After 11 years of working on what he&rsquo;s dubbed &ldquo;The Xenotext,&rdquo; B&ouml;k is close to creating the world&rsquo;s first living poem. A short stanza enciphered into a string of DNA and injected into an &ldquo;unkillable&rdquo; bacterium, B&ouml;k&rsquo;s poem is designed to trigger the micro-organism to create a corresponding protein that, when decoded, is a verse created by the organism. In other words, the harmless bacterium, <em>Deinococcus radiodurans</em> (known as an extremophile because of its ability to survive freezing, scorching, or the vacuum of outer space), will be a poetic bug. </p>
 
 <p>B&ouml;k first conceived of &ldquo;The Xenotext&rdquo; after reading a scientific article by Pak Chung Wong at Pacific Northwest National Laboratory in Washington and another by Arizona-based astrobiologist Paul Davies. Wong encoded the lyrics to Disney&rsquo;s<em> It&rsquo;s a Small World After All </em>into bacteria. Davies speculated that if extraterrestrial civilizations wanted to make contact with other worlds, they would send highly adaptable self-replicating bio-probes&mdash;something akin to a bacterium or virus&mdash;that could carry messages and survive the destructive environment of outer space. </p>
 
 <p>In October, B&ouml;k, 46, professor of creative writing at the University of Calgary, got word from a California lab that his DNA concoction had caused a test organism to fluoresce, signifying that it was responding to his gene sequence. It had done so on a few prior attempts, but when the scientists examined the results, they discovered the organism was cutting off part of the protein string. &ldquo;That was bad news for me,&rdquo; says B&ouml;k, because it meant his creation was being destroyed. &ldquo;Instead of having created the first microbial writer, I had effectively created the first microbial critic.&rdquo; Now, at last, the organism created a properly folded protein that survived in its cell and could be interpreted as the first bacterial attempt at composing verse. </p>
 
 <p>To find a poem that would live happily inside a bacterium&mdash;and would enable the professor to teach his microbial student to try its hand at a stanza that could be decoded&mdash;B&ouml;k combed through eight trillion ciphers and decided on this: </p>
 
 <p>
 <em>Any style of life / is prim</em> </p>
 
 <p>And the organism, which emits a red luminescence, always writes back: </p>
 
 <p>
 <em>The faery is rosy / of glow</em> </p>
 
 <p>To create both poems, B&ouml;k immersed himself for years in grad-level biochemistry, genetic engineering and proteomics, the branch of biology focused on the interactions of proteins within cells. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m an autodidact,&rdquo; he shrugs. &ldquo;Part of the artistic exercise in doing the project would be to teach myself the necessary skills.&rdquo; It also took six years to raise the $120,000 for the research and lab work. When &ldquo;The Xenotext&rdquo; is published, in 2014 at the earliest, the book of the same name will include a slide containing the bacterium, and essays and poems about the project. </p>
 
 <p>B&ouml;k, the antithesis of the beatnik poet (he prefers expensive Canali suits to corduroy, and drinks Lagavulin scotch, distillers edition) is no stranger to poetic experiments. He has created artificial languages for series such as Gene Roddenberry&rsquo;s <em>Earth: Final Conflict</em>. In 2002, he won the prestigious Griffin Poetry Prize (and $40,000) for his bestselling book <em>Eunoia</em>. Each of the &#64257;ve chapters consists of a poem written with words containing just one of the vowels. To write it, B&ouml;k read the three-volume <em>Webster&rsquo;s </em>dictionary five times. </p>
 
 <p>For B&ouml;k, &ldquo;The Xeno- text&rdquo; is about nudging poetry into a new form. &ldquo;I am amazed that poets will continue to write about their divorces, even though there is currently a robot taking pictures of orange ethane lakes on Titan.&rdquo; He notes there are no poems about that, or the moon landing, &ldquo;probably the greatest achievement of any life form on this planet. Had the ancient Greeks rowed a trireme (boat) to the moon, you can bet there would be a 12-volume epic about that adventure.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Architecture</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Frank Lloyd Wright&mdash;for rent </hedline>
 
 <abstract>Starchitect-designed structures are now for rent around the world</abstract>
 
  <byline>Julia De Laurentiis Johnson</byline>

 </body.head>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Room with a view: Dune House in Suffolk, on Britain&rsquo;s east coast, has an open-concept main floor allowing views of the surrounding sand dunes</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Living Architecture</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Frank Lloyd Wright called it Still Bend, because the nearly 3,000-sq.-foot house overlooks a marsh on the East Twin River in Wisconsin. Completed in 1940 and funded by local businessman Bernard Schwartz, the house has a main floor unfettered by walls, which measures 63 feet from front door to back wall. It also boasts an interior balcony and a soaring, two-storey ceiling typical of Wright&rsquo;s designs. </p>
 
 <p>You can tour many of the famous American architect&rsquo;s buildings, from Fallingwater in Pennsylvania to his desert masterpiece, Taliesin West in Arizona, but what would it be like to live in one? </p>
 
 <p>Michael Ditmer, co-owner of what is now called Bernard Schwartz House, wants to share that experience. For US$295 to $425 a night, depending on the season, you can rent the four-bedroom house and warm yourself in front of one of the three fireplaces centred around a massive brick chimney, including one in the outdoor sunken court. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Wright had a lifelong interest in building homes for the middle class,&rdquo; says Ditmer, who bought the house with his brother for $375,000 in 2003. Since most people can&rsquo;t afford a Wright-designed house, he keeps the architect&rsquo;s dream alive (and funds maintenance and renovations) with short-term rentals. Nearly 600 people a year take him up on the offer. </p>
 
 <p>Ditmer, whose business keeps him in Minnesota most of the year, rents the house through his website and through <em>airbnb.com</em>, a travel site with a section for aesthetes who want to stay in starchitect-designed structures by the likes of Wright or Frank Gehry all over the world. He&rsquo;s had such an increase in bookings recently that when he wants to stay there himself, he has to turn people away. </p>
 
 <p>In England, a project called Living Architecture has the same idea. A not-for-profit originally funded by a panel of wealthy patrons, its goal is to promote modern architecture&mdash;and its enjoyment. In five years, it has commissioned notable architects to design five rental properties around England. </p>
 
 <p>Dune House, a structural marvel with a &#64257;shbowl-like main &#64258;oor that provides a 360-degree view of the seaside landscape in Suffolk, sleeps nine and costs about $30 per person a night. It recently received a nod from the Royal Institute of British Architects and has since been booked right through 2013. With two more residences planned for next year, Living Architecture aims to act as a modern antidote to the long-standing British tradition of charming (read ancient), drafty holiday cottages. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Most rental houses in the U.K. are of dire standards,&rdquo; says the group&rsquo;s creative director, the philosopher Alain de Botton, who wrote the 2006 book, <em>The Architecture of Happiness</em>. &ldquo;The bathrooms don&rsquo;t work, there&rsquo;s mould on the ceiling, the fridge was last cleaned a year ago.&rdquo; He believes that living in a well-designed structure can satisfy the brain&rsquo;s pleasure centres, much like being in the presence of a beautiful work of art, though on a much grander scale. &ldquo;Architecture is a total immersive experience. It touches you from the start to the end of the day.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Structural engineer Jane Wernick, the London-based editor of a book of essays called <em>Building Happiness: Architecture to Make You Smile</em>, agrees that well-being and a well-designed space are inextricably linked. &ldquo;The human scale of a beautifully designed house is largely what&rsquo;s so attractive,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;It seems that if a space is designed to encourage chance encounters where people can stop and have conversations, that leads to a happier environment.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Back in Wisconsin, Ditmer is leafing through the comments in his guest book. His favourite is from an 11-year-old girl, who, he says, &ldquo;loved the way the sunlight came through the cutout windows in the morning and put on a sort of light show on the walls. She really got it.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 
  
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>TV</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Title fight: short vs. long</hedline>
 
 <abstract>Many TV shows now have minimal or no title sequences </abstract>
 
 <byline>Jaime J. Weinman</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_TITLEMERGE.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Don&rsquo;t blink: Boardwalk Empire lures you in with a lush theme, while New Girl and Girls are content to get in and get out as quickly as possible</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <body.content>
 
 <p>The A&amp;E drama<em> Bates Motel</em>, a TV prequel to <em>Psycho</em>, is giving fans a chance to create the opening title sequence&mdash;but with a catch: it has to be really short. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re looking for an awesome 15-second title sequence that captures the feel of <em>Bates Motel</em>,&rdquo; series creator Carlton Cuse (<em>Lost</em>) said when announcing the contest, whose winner will be announced before the series premiere in March. Fifteen seconds is actually a pretty generous amount of time for a title sequence today. Many shows don&rsquo;t have them at all: HBO&rsquo;s most hyped recent show, Lena Dunham&rsquo;s <em>Girls</em>, has nothing but a simple title card, like a low-budget movie. &ldquo;In my view, short sequences are a missed opportunity,&rdquo; says Danny Yount, who created the nearly two-minute opening for HBO&rsquo;s<em> Six Feet Under</em>. But if <em>Bates Motel</em> is any indication, a title sequence may not be important enough to take a lot of time for, or even to hire professional designers for. </p>
 
 <p>A full-length title sequence is certainly expensive to do, especially for shows that don&rsquo;t take the easy route and string together a bunch of old clips. Yount says his sequence for<em> Six Feet Under</em>, a mini-movie that summed up the themes of the show, required &ldquo;a full crew, three locations and two days of shooting,&rdquo; but adds that &ldquo;the producers wanted something unique to television, so I think it was a worthwhile investment for them.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>The bigger issue with long titles is that they eat up screen time, and most shows don&rsquo;t have much of that. A show like <em>Cheers</em> could afford a minute for its famous titles (with old pictures of bar patrons) because it had five minutes of ads, as opposed to nine minutes for a half-hour show today. And it&rsquo;s not just time that networks are worried about: now that TV viewers have hundreds of choices, a long title sequence can give them an excuse to change the channel. </p>
 
 <p>Most shows can&rsquo;t just get rid of the main title, though, because that&rsquo;s often what people remember about a TV program. On YouTube, most older shows are represented only by their introductory sequences, and fans use them as a basis for a lot of their own videos, such as a live-action recreation of the opening of <em>The Simpsons</em> that went viral. That&rsquo;s why shows are increasingly trying the<em> Bates Motel</em> solution: have a very short opening that sums up the theme and style of the program with blinding speed. </p>
 
 <p>Yount thinks this emphasis on brevity in title sequences is a let-down after the tiny epics HBO made to introduce its classic dramas. &ldquo;I feel the length to build a story, or a film within a film, is better,&rdquo; he says. And it&rsquo;s not only the storytelling that&rsquo;s impaired by short titles, but the ability of the composer to come up with really memorable theme music. &ldquo;One of the best things about<em> Six Feet Under</em> is the wonderful music Thomas Newman created,&rdquo; Yount recalls. &ldquo;It would not be the same thing as a short jingle. It really transports you into this dream-like place and sets the moods perfectly.&rdquo; From this point of view, if shows took a little more time for their opening credits, they might stand a better chance of coming up with theme songs that could become hits the way the <em>Friends</em> theme did in the &rsquo;90s. </p>
 
 <p>Other title designers, though, point out that a short sequence isn&rsquo;t always an artistic compromise. &ldquo;You can do more in 90 seconds than you can with 23, but it also depends on what might serve the show best,&rdquo; says Ian Albinson, editor of the website <em>Art of the Title.</em> He points to the Emmy-nominated sequence for the comedy <em>New Girl</em>, where what seems to be a full-length theme abruptly cuts off as the male characters lose interest and walk away. &ldquo;Its impact comes from the fact that it is short and sweet,&rdquo; says <em>Art of the Title</em> managing editor Lola Landekic. &ldquo;Any longer and it&rsquo;d be saccharine.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>
 <em>Bates Motel</em> may point the way to another advantage of the short main title: an interactive title is a cheap way to generate fan participation before a show even begins. Still, some recent dramas, like <em>Boardwalk Empire</em>, have stuck with the long and expensive format, and Yount, for one, hopes it never goes away completely: &ldquo;The viewer should be made to believe that something very special is about to happen. You can&rsquo;t do that by just rushing right into the show.&rdquo;  </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Books</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Venice, from empire to tourist town</hedline>
 
 <abstract>Plus, a new take on Flavius Josephus, Jefferson&rsquo;s slave brings haute cuisine to America, Diana Vreeland, Elizabethan spies, and a political lyricist</abstract>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_BOOKS01.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>&lsquo;Venice: A New History&rsquo;: As Thomas F. Madden&rsquo;s lively new history makes clear, Venice was always a little ancient and a lot proto-modern</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Eric Herchaft/Reporters/Redux</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 
 <em>VENICE: A NEW HISTORY </em>
 <p>Thomas F. Madden </p>
 
 <p>Western tradition is studded with iconic cities representing moments in time, from Periclean Athens to Victorian London, but none is as protean as Venice. The Italian city is at once: a mudbank shantytown founded by survivors fleeing the fifth-century ruin of the Roman world; the powerful seagoing republic known as <em>La Serenissima</em> (&ldquo;most serene&rdquo;), which sent Marco Polo all the way to Cathay, and whose doge annually married the sea by tossing a ring into the Adriatic; Casanova&rsquo;s art-stuffed city of masques (and masks), so redolent of Poe&rsquo;s &ldquo;The Cask of Amontillado&rdquo;; and the modern Disneyland writ large, sinking under the weight of its millions of tourists. </p>
 
 <p>But none of those images captures Western history as a whole because, as Madden&rsquo;s lively new history&mdash;the first in English in a generation&mdash;makes clear, Venice was always integral to Europe and slightly out of sync with it, always a little ancient and a lot proto-modern, even while the rest of the Continent was thoroughly medieval. While mainstream Europe was a collection of agriculture-based feudal states, Venice was an urban capitalist republic, a pioneer in deposit banking and double-entry bookkeeping. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;The first Venetians were Romans,&rdquo; Madden notes, and they held fast to their roots for over a millennium. The openness of their democracy varied considerably over time, but Venetians never abandoned their republican government or had a less than broad-based ruling elite. Although La Serenissima and the U.S. co-existed for only two decades before Napoleon swept away the former, John Adams, one of the founding fathers of the world&rsquo;s newest republic, carefully studied the institutions of the world&rsquo;s oldest. Perhaps he was struck by its system of checks and balances, which makes American political gridlock look streamlined: at one point,Venice required nine groups, consisting of 282 electors chosen largely by lot, just to nominate a doge, a process, writes Madden, &ldquo;meant to be so cumbersome that only God could influence it.&rdquo; Rather like the U.S. House of Representatives. </p>
 
 <byline>Brian Bethune</byline>
 
 
 <em>A JEW AMONG ROMANS: THE LIFE AND LEGACY OF FLAVIUS JOSEPHUS </em>
 <p>Frederic Raphael </p>
 
 <p>The author of <em>The Jewish War</em>&mdash;our sole account of the 70 CE destruction of Jerusalem and its temple by the Romans&mdash;has always been one of the Ancient World&rsquo;s most controversial figures. Born Joseph ben Mattathias to a Judean priestly family, Josephus was a leading Jewish general during the first years of the doomed rebellion, but, unlike so many of his contemporaries, he did not die either in battle or&mdash;like the martyrs of Masada&mdash;by his own hand. Instead, Josephus survived a brutal siege and passed into the hands of the Roman general Vespasian and his son Titus, both later emperors, and so became Titus Flavius Josephus, Roman citizen and adviser to the imperial family. Small wonder two millennia of commentators, Jewish and otherwise, have mostly seen him as an apostate and traitor. </p>
 
 <p>But in the multitalented and prickly Raphael&mdash;novelist, classicist and Oscar-winning screenwriter for <em>Darling</em> (1965)&mdash;the ancient survivor has found his ideal judge, a man as certain of being a Jew as he is uncertain of the meaning of that fact, much as Josephus himself was. (&ldquo;There is comedy of a kind,&rdquo; the 81-year-old Raphael writes, &ldquo;that the only people who might now insist that I am not really a Jew&mdash;since I neither pray nor abstain from forbidden foods&mdash;are other Jews.&rdquo;) </p>
 
 <p>The result is a mesmerizing study that evaluates Josephus&rsquo;s choices within the context of internecine Jewish strife (both real and polemical) and overwhelming Gentile power. Josephus was the first, Raphael argues, of a long line of Diaspora Jews, from Maimonides to Spinoza, balanced on a similar knife-edge between internal suspicion and outside hatred. Who has the right to judge Josephus, whose works are one long defence of his people and his God (and filled with necessarily subtle denunciations of their persecutors)? asks Raphael. Exile, witness, reluctant loyalist who argued against a suicidal war, less than dependable propagandist for the victorious enemy: Josephus deserves respect. </p>
 
 <byline>Brian Bethune</byline>
  
 
 <em>THOMAS JEFFERSON&rsquo;S CR&Egrave;ME BR&Ucirc;L&Eacute;E: HOW A FOUNDING FATHER AND HIS SLAVE JAMES HEMINGS INTRODUCED FRENCH CUISINE TO AMERICA </em>
 <p>Thomas J. Craughwell </p>
 
 <p>In the summer of 1790, Thomas Jefferson invited James Madison and secretary of the treasury Alexander Hamilton to dinner at Monticello to discuss the federal government assuming individual states&rsquo; crippling American Revolution debts. Hamilton was all for it. Madison opposed it. And Jefferson sympathized with both. But he hoped the trio would &ldquo;find some temperament for the present fever.&rdquo; And they did, over a lavish meal paired with fine French wines. &ldquo;So ended one of the most momentous private dinners in American history, and it had been prepared by James Hemings,&rdquo; writes Craughwell of the founder&rsquo;s slave. </p>
 
 <p>Never mind Julia Child: Craughwell, working extensively from letters, documents and recipes, chronicles how Jefferson and Hemings introduced French cuisine to America, a new country that knew nothing of truffles, olive oil and champagne, not to mention macaroni. Heartbroken after the death of his wife, Jefferson took the post of minister to France and crossed the Atlantic in 1784 with Hemings, who was brought for the sole purpose of learning to cook&mdash;think hollandaise and b&eacute;chamel&mdash;from French chefs. In return for his efforts, Jefferson promised to free Hemings once he&rsquo;d passed on what he&rsquo;d learned to an apprentice back at Monticello. In 1796, Jefferson kept his promise. </p>
 
 <p>The book is packed full with gastronomic details, from the colonial diet to what Jefferson planted in the garden behind his home on the Champs-&Eacute;lys&eacute;es. And no tale of Jefferson would be complete without acknowledging his moral inconsistencies when it came to slavery. He condemned it as an &ldquo;abominable crime,&rdquo; but unlike George Washington, he never freed his slaves in his will. Craughwell skims the surface. But he does provide a glimpse of Jefferson and Hemings&rsquo;s complicated relationship: in 1801, when Jefferson sent his former slave, now a tavern cook in Baltimore, a letter to see if he&rsquo;d be his chef at the &ldquo;President&rsquo;s House,&rdquo; Hemings wrote back asking for more details. Jefferson never responded.</p>
 
  <byline>Jessica Allen</byline>
 
 
 <em>EMPRESS OF FASHION: A LIFE OF DIANA VREELAND </em>
 <p>Amanda Mackenzie Stuart </p>
 
 <p>The fact that style arbiter Diana Vreeland had a famously uneven relationship with what less imaginative people call the truth makes her a challenging, if delicious, subject for biography. But British writer Stuart is clearly equal to the task in this entertaining, authoritative study that reads like a novel begging to be made into a movie. </p>
 
 <p>Vreeland is best known for her 18-year tenure as <em>Vogue</em>&rsquo;s influential, imperious editor-in-chief in the &rsquo;60s and &rsquo;70s. But her quest for the escape fashion offers dates to her privileged upbringing in New York. The ugly-duckling daughter of a glamorous, distant mother, young Diana laboured to cultivate a distinctive style that won her friends, celebrity and a too-handsome husband. The couple made a splash in Europe among the likes of Coco Chanel and Cecil Beaton before returning to America, where Diana became notorious for her <em>Harper&rsquo;s Bazaar</em> &ldquo;Why Don&rsquo;t You?&rdquo; column. (Typical advice: &ldquo;Why don&rsquo;t you rinse your blond child&rsquo;s hair in dead champagne to keep its gold, the way they do in France?&rdquo;) </p>
 
 <p>Hired at <em>Vogue</em> in 1963, at age 61, Vreeland shocked with her bold choices. Her own eccentricities&mdash;fondness for lacquered red walls, a Kabuki-like appearance, and sphinx-like pronouncements (&ldquo;Pink is the navy blue of India&rdquo;)&mdash;sealed her legend. But fashion is fickle; she was turfed in 1981 but would resurface for one last act: staging blockbuster exhibits for the Costume Institute at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York. </p>
 
 <p>Stuart&rsquo;s deft portrayal is full of context and detail, such as Vreeland&rsquo;s reaction at hearing president Kennedy had been shot: &ldquo;My God, Lady Bird [Johnson] in the White House. We can&rsquo;t use her in the magazine!&rdquo; Such utterances make her easy to mock, though Stuart never does. Rather, she presents Vreeland as a complex trailblazer&mdash;a self-invented woman who put her stamp on modern fashion and thrived professionally into her 70s. And she never stopped, even when she could no longer see the lovely surfaces that had given her life its meaning.</p>
 
 <byline>Anne Kingston</byline>
 
 
 <em>THE WATCHERS: A SECRET HISTORY OF THE REIGN OF ELIZABETH I </em>
 <p>Stephen Alford </p>
 
 <p>Elizabeth I was the Gloriana, the virgin queen who reigned over England&rsquo;s Golden Age, the Renaissance of Shakespeare, Sir Francis Drake and Sir Philip Sidney. Yet behind that beautiful facade, her 45 years in power were dogged by threats of invasion, treason and treachery. Her Catholic enemies, both domestic and foreign, were determined to rid Europe of the woman deemed a bastard heretic unworthy of the throne. Her closest advisers, especially spymaster Francis Walsingham, spent considerable time, and a large chunk of the treasury&rsquo;s gold, stamping out any threat to their sovereign. He planted loyal Protestants within Catholic exile groups as couriers so he could intercept their communications, and even knew about one invasion force&rsquo;s plans before its top commanders did. </p>
 
 <p>Using letters and documents that have somehow survived from the era, including amazingly frank communications from Walsingham or his minions, Alford weaves an exciting tale of intrigue, mystery and danger from the spies&rsquo; and traitors&rsquo; points of view. There&rsquo;s Charles Sledd, an agent who infiltrated priests&rsquo; colleges, writing detailed descriptions of Jesuits about to be smuggled into England, allowing them to be hunted down. Thomas Phelippes, one of Walsingham&rsquo;s best code breakers, carefully lays out evidence for the treasonous guilt of Elizabeth&rsquo;s cousin, Mary, Queen of Scots. There&rsquo;s even a letter to Elizabeth in which William Parry, a rather hapless spy turned politician and would-be assassin, tries to explain his actions: &ldquo;Your Majesty may see by my voluntary confession the dangerous fruits of a discontented mind.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Against all odds, the spymaster, his agents and successors proved successful. In 1603, Elizabeth died of natural causes in her own bed. Her successor was the son of her cousin, Mary. And, to the dismay of Elizabeth&rsquo;s enemies, a Protestant.</p>
 
  <byline>Patricia Treble </byline>
 
 
 <em>YIP HARBURG: LEGENDARY LYRICIST AND HUMAN RIGHTS ACTIVIST </em>
 <p>Harriet Hyman Alonso </p>
 
 <p>Before the &rsquo;60s, E.Y. &ldquo;Yip&rdquo; Harburg was one of the few American popular songwriters with an openly political bent. The lyricist of such classics as Paper Moon, April in Paris and all the songs from <em>The Wizard of Oz,</em> Harburg was famous for his passionate love lyrics and whimsical language games (such as rhyming &ldquo;Lydia&rdquo; with &ldquo;encyclopedia&rdquo;). But he was also, as Alonso notes, one of the few major songwriters to &ldquo;place human rights at the centre of his work.&rdquo; His first big hit, Brother, Can You Spare a Dime? had a theme that Harburg summed up as &ldquo;I produce&mdash;why don&rsquo;t I share?&rdquo; The left-wing New Deal spirit of his work eventually got him blacklisted in Hollywood and attacked by Ayn Rand, for a Second World War song in praise of Russia. </p>
 
 <p>Alonso, who teaches at Harburg&rsquo;s alma mater, City College in New York, has built much of this biography out of the lyricist&rsquo;s own words, with long excerpts from previously unpublished interviews. The debacle of <em>Jamaica</em>, a show that became successful only after it was taken away from him, is summed up in seven pages of angry interview quotes (&ldquo;I felt so brokenhearted about it, I never went back to see it&rdquo;), and the fear and paranoia of the blacklist era is memorably conveyed in a 1950 letter from Burton Lane, the composer of Harburg&rsquo;s Broadway hit <em>Finian&rsquo;s Rainbow</em>, who informs him that producers are calling him a Communist. </p>
 
 <p>Because Alonso mostly limits her own writing to connective tissue, &ldquo;weaving together&rdquo; the interviews and providing context and background, the story can sometimes seem a little thin. Though Harburg was a famously difficult man to work with, that only comes out occasionally, as in his bitter opposition to a dark Civil War ballet. But Harburg&rsquo;s interviews and reprinted lyrics do provide a good introduction to a lyricist who spent his life trying to balance his strong political messages with his belief in &ldquo;sweet songs with hope and romance.&rdquo;</p>
 
 <byline>Jaime J. Weinman</byline>
 
 
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Taste</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Men who love to loaf around </hedline>
 
 <abstract>&lsquo;What&rsquo;s not to like about a man who bakes his own bread?&rsquo;</abstract>
 
 <byline>Jessica Allen</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC53_TASTE01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Gender divide: While women buy lots of cookbooks, nearly 90 per cent of bread-making volumes at one specialist store are bought by men</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Jetta Productions/Dana Neely/Getty Images; photograph by jessica allen</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Near the back of the Cookbook Store in Toronto on a November evening, two men lingered in the bread-making section. Shane Carruthers, a cook who&rsquo;s started to experiment with baking bread, carried <em>How to Make Bread</em> by Emmanuel Hadjiandreou in an Indigo bag. And Matt Harris, who doesn&rsquo;t bake, left with a copy of Nick Malgieri&rsquo;s <em>Bread</em>&mdash;for his wife. </p>
 
 <p>That gave store manager Alison Fryer pause, considering that in the past 30 years, she and her staff have observed that roughly 90 per cent of their bread-making books have been bought by men. &ldquo;When you point it out to people, they&rsquo;re not really aware of it,&rdquo; she explains. &ldquo;But then the penny drops and they go, &lsquo;Oh, that&rsquo;s right. It <em>is</em> all males.&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>What exactly fascinates men about mixing flour, water and yeast is debatable. It could have something to do with the fact that most European bakers of the past 200 years have been male, explains food historian Heather Evans of Queen&rsquo;s University in Kingston, Ont. And although she notes that &ldquo;cookery-book purchasing patterns don&rsquo;t necessarily bespeak patterns of cooking,&rdquo; the only bread-making cookbook Evans and her partner own in their vast collection was bought by him. &ldquo;Perhaps,&rdquo; she suggests, &ldquo;all these bread-making books are being purchased with a view to integrating bread-making into the courtship process. What&rsquo;s not to like about a man who bakes his own bread?&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>
 <em>Globe and Mail</em> food critic Chris Nuttall-Smith believes the fixation has to do with the fact that there&rsquo;s really nothing modern about it. &ldquo;Bread is totally analogue,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s kind of like other things that a lot of men like, [including] golf and cars. Ultimately, they&rsquo;re unknowable.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Nuttall-Smith, who is currently obsessed with recreating a loaf of dark rye he had at a restaurant in Copenhagen, points to Jim Lahey as the person who&rsquo;s &ldquo;done more for bread and getting people to eat good bread.&rdquo; After Mark Bittman wrote about Lahey&rsquo;s revolutionary no-knead loaf in a 2006 <em>New York Times</em> column, it became the most popular recipe ever to run in the paper. </p>
 
 <p>Lahey isn&rsquo;t certain why more men than women bake bread, he says on the phone from New York, home to his 18-year-old Sullivan Street Bakery, but he advances his own theory. &ldquo;I would say that more often with men than women there is a desire or impulse to play with wet, gooey, sticky things.&rdquo; Over the past 20 years, he has noticed that successful bakers have come to terms with the fact that playing with wet, gooey sticky things is a means to an end. The end, of course, being a plump, piping-hot loaf of crusty bread, preferably slathered with butter. </p>
 
 <p>Sullivan learned how to make bread from male master bakers in Italy, where it&rsquo;s rare to see females in the profession. It&rsquo;s not so common in Canada, either. There&rsquo;s Andrea Damon Gibson, the professional baker behind Toronto&rsquo;s famed Fred&rsquo;s Bread, who, when asked to name other female pros in Canada, mentions Saskatoon&rsquo;s Tracey Muzzolini. Gibson suggests men&rsquo;s obsession with dough might have to do with the thrill of creating something from very little, nurturing it and watching it grow. </p>
 
 <p>Giuliano Pediconi, a master baker from the Marches region of Italy, teaches bread making back home and women are the majority in his classes. The 46-year-old, who&rsquo;s in Toronto to consult on Terroni restaurant&rsquo;s soon-to-open bakery, is initially surprised to hear of the Cookbook store&rsquo;s observation. But as he studs bread batter with bits of torn-up anchovy and candied orange peel, he reconsiders. Historically, bakers in Italy are men and, particularly in rural areas, even cutting the bread is left to the patriarch of the family. &ldquo;Maybe there is a bit of narcissism at work, because the recipe is nothing&mdash;just flour, water and yeast&mdash;but to create bread out of nothing gives you a sense of accomplishment, a sense of . . . ,&rdquo; he says, raising his wet, sticky, gooey hands to his chest, &ldquo; . . . &lsquo;I made this.&rsquo; &rdquo;  </p>
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Help</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>Viewing the city in a different light </hedline>
 
 <abstract>A writer sees beauty in a discarded sofa on walks designed to elevate the mundane</abstract>
 
  <byline>Julia McKinnell</byline>

 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_ONLOOKING01.jpg"></photo>
 
 
 <photo.caption>Bonanzas: Alexandra Horowitz&rsquo;s dog inspired her to take a closer look at ordinary details and avoid being a sleepwalker on the sidewalk</photo.caption>
 
 
 
 <photo.byline>Sam Javanrouh</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Cognitive psychologist Alexandra Horowitz credits her dog for making her aware of all the sights and smells she was missing outdoors. Horowitz teaches canine behaviour at Columbia University in New York. On walks with her dog, she often found herself being led astray. The dog would stop to sniff lampposts or zigzag through the park. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;I began trying to see what my dog was seeing and smelling that was taking us far afield,&rdquo; she explains in her new book, <em>On Looking: Eleven Walks With Expert Eyes</em>. &ldquo;I was paying so little attention to most of what was right before us that I had become a sleepwalker on the sidewalk.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Horowitz teamed up with a geologist, an artist and a physician, among others, to learn extraordinary things about seemingly ordinary cities and their inhabitants. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;In this book, I aim to knock myself awake,&rdquo; she writes. &ldquo;I took the &lsquo;walk around the block&rsquo;&mdash;an ordinary activity engaged in by everyone nearly every day&mdash;dozens of times with people who have distinctive, individual, expert ways of seeing all the unattended perceived ordinary elements I was missing.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>To start, Horowitz met with geologist Sidney Horenstein, a 40-year veteran of coordinating field trips for the American Museum of Natural History. When Horenstein walks the streets of Manhattan, he doesn&rsquo;t just see glass and concrete. When he looks at a building, he sees giant outcroppings of rock and scattered trees on grassy plains. &ldquo;Each building is, of course, forged of stone or hewed from a once-living tree,&rdquo; says Horowitz. Seen this way, the city feels less artificial to her. </p>
 
 <p>Further along, Horenstein stops in front of an &ldquo;unlovely&rdquo; retaining wall. Horowitz sees a few bright yellow leaves stuck to the stone, but to Horenstein, the wall tells an ancient story. &ldquo;This rock (limestone from Indiana) was once loose stuff on the sea floor, and you have sea worms going through it and leaving trails.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>On her next walk, Horowitz is accompanied by artist Maira Kalman. &ldquo;While I was bee-lining down the block, Kalman was loitering,&rdquo; Horowitz observed. When Kalman spied an old couch on the street, she could not believe it. &ldquo;Oh my god. That&rsquo;s like the bonanza of bonanzas&mdash;there it is&mdash;a sofa on the street.&rdquo; Kalman rushed over, pulled out a camera and snapped a photo. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;She loved it for the boldness of its naked arrival on the curb,&rdquo; writes Horowitz. The couch had clean lines, a surfeit of frilliness and a proud back. &ldquo;Under our gaze it seemed to turn elegant again, lightening my heart burdened with the thought that it was now simply trash.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>On another expedition, Horowitz meets Dr. Bennett Lorber, a physician and professor at Temple University School of Medicine in Philadelphia. As soon as the walk starts, Lorber&rsquo;s eye is caught by a man who he says needs his hip replaced. </p>
 
 <p>The experience reminded Horowitz of the deductive brilliance of Sherlock Holmes, making her more conscious of her own health. &ldquo;Glancing at my own thumbnail, I noticed it was ridged somewhat. My brow furrowed: what could this mean? Low iron? Liver disease?&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Walking with the doctor helped her realize how much of our health is revealed on our face and in our posture or gait. &ldquo;Just as a ballerina might have particularly fine posture, or a fencer an enlarged thigh muscle, we all wear our physical condition, and someone attuned to this can tell a lot from very few clues.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>On the phone from Manhattan, Horowitz says the walks enriched her life. Those who want to try this in their own neighbourhood might start by looking for one new thing, she suggests. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;Just have something in mind that you&rsquo;re looking for: how do other people look on the street? Or look where the dogs are facing as they walk down the street as opposed to taking it in unthinkingly. That&rsquo;s very simple and will help people notice the dimensions of a scene. It allowed me to &#64257;nd great entertainment in the mundanity of walking down a familiar, boring block.&rdquo; </p>
 
 
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>Feschuk</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <hedline>I go back and forth on Idle No More</hedline>
 
 <abstract>How to stay unmoved by someone so devoted to a cause, she&rsquo;s living on fish broth?</abstract>
 
  <byline>Scott Feschuk</byline>

</body.head>
 
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_FESCHUKMERGE.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.caption>Oh right, the fast: I had Harper pegged as the kind of guy who&rsquo;d ignore a hunger striker&mdash;or maybe deliver to her a plate of nice, crisp bacon</photo.caption>
 
 
 <photo.byline>photo illustration by taylor shute</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>According to its founders, Idle No More &ldquo;calls on all people to join in a revolution which honours and fulfills Indigenous sovereignty.&rdquo; That doesn&rsquo;t sound like a very fun revolution. The best revolutions are, like, &ldquo;Hey, let&rsquo;s kill the king!&rdquo; or &ldquo;Hang on, we preferred the original Coke!&rdquo; Honouring and fulfilling stuff doesn&rsquo;t usually cut it. </p>
 
 <p>But the movement has taken off. We&rsquo;re at the point now where it&rsquo;s like Occupy, but with fewer hacky sacks and douchebags. And it&rsquo;s splitting opinion pretty sharply. For many, your perspective on Idle No More may come down to how you feel about the hunger strike of Chief Theresa Spence. Many find inspiration in her commitment. Others feel Spence is cheating because she&rsquo;s consuming tea, lemon water and fish broth.<em> Fish broth is food! </em>they say. <em>Kind of but not really!</em> comes the reply. Although, if we&rsquo;re debating the calorie count of fish water, we have perhaps strayed some distance from the larger point. </p>
 
 <p>There is one thing for certain: I would be the world&rsquo;s worst hunger striker. I&rsquo;d have the fish broth. I&rsquo;d have the lemon water. I&rsquo;d have the lemon and the lemon peel. I&rsquo;d have the pizza&mdash;but just one or two slices because, you know, hunger strike. Worse still, if my hunger strike actually got me a meeting with the Prime Minister, as Spence&rsquo;s did, I wouldn&rsquo;t be able to say anything because for three hours my mouth would be full of muffin. </p>
 
 <p>These days, what with the Internet and the tweeting and whatnot, everyone feels strongly about things. Confidence is the currency of the times. And so we get: Idle No More is dumb and the people who think it&rsquo;s awesome are stupid. Or we get: Idle No More is awesome and the people who think it&rsquo;s stupid are dumb. Can&rsquo;t we just all agree that Idle No More has given us the opportunity to focus on an important national issue, assess the pertinent facts of the matter and reflexively accuse each other of being racists? </p>
 
 <p>Personally, I go back and forth on the merits of Idle No More. Please join me for a walk along my path of indecision. </p>
 
 <p><em>Pro:</em> Having witnessed first-hand the living conditions in Aboriginal communities, and having had my capacity for empathy somehow survive following Donald Trump on Twitter, I recognize the need for genuine change and meaningful action. </p>
 
 <p><em>Con:</em> A hunger strike is the most childish of all negotiating ploys. <em>If you don&rsquo;t give me what I want, I am GOING TO DIE!!!</em> It&rsquo;s basically the grown-up equivalent of dropping to the floor in Toys R Us and wailing until Mommy says, &ldquo;Fine, <em>one</em> Power Ranger.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p><em>Pro:</em> It&rsquo;s hard not to be moved by someone so devoted to a cause she is willing to subsist for a month on fish juice. I&rsquo;m not sure there&rsquo;s an injustice in this world that would motivate me even to order the salad instead of fries. </p>
 
 <p><em>Con:</em> I can&rsquo;t support any movement that forces me to spend even 10 extra minutes on a train. Aboriginals of Canada: I sympathize with your plight, but please do not form any more barricades on train tracks. Many of us can barely tolerate long red lights. DON&rsquo;T PUSH US. </p>
 
 <p><em>Pro:</em> Ezra Levant has been pretty outspoken in attacking Chief Spence and no one wants to be on the same side of an issue as that guy. </p>
 
 <p><em>Con:</em> When the &ldquo;scathing&rdquo; audit of her band&rsquo;s finances was released this week, Spence called it a ploy to &ldquo;discredit&rdquo; her. It sure was, and it worked. In reading the audit, the only surprise is that the reserve didn&rsquo;t wind up with a monorail. It put North Haverbrook on the map! </p>
 
 <p>It&rsquo;s a divisive issue, but let&rsquo;s at least agree on this: the biggest surprise so far is that Stephen Harper caved and agreed to meet with a delegation that includes Chief Spence. I had Harper pegged as the kind of guy who&rsquo;d ignore a hunger striker. Or perhaps have delivered to her a plate of nice, crisp bacon. </p>
 
 <p>But it turns out the PM is a softie! And now we know his weakness. Let&rsquo;s all get in line to starve our way to a meeting on the issues that matter most to us. It&rsquo;ll be worth a few weeks of suffering to make my case for why we need a fifth season of <em>Starsky &amp; Hutch</em>. </p>
 
<em>Follow Scott Feschuk on Twitter @scottfeschuk</em>

 </body.content>
 
 
</body>
<body>
 <body.head>
 
 <hedline>Now Available: The Best of The End</hedline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>A collection of the best, most moving obituaries 	from <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> in 2012 as 	they appeared on our hugely popular final page, The End</p>
 <p>Always surprising and poignant, these obituaries feature an eclectic mix of 	ordinary Canadians whose deaths were often emblematic of the way they lived </p>
 <p>Get it wherever ebooks 	are sold </p>
 </body.content>
 
</body>
<body>
 <sections>The end</sections>
 
 <body.head>
 <slug>1981-2012 </slug>
 
 <hedline>Nicholas Vachon </hedline>
 
 <abstract>He loved volunteer firefighting so much that he&rsquo;d recently decided against a career move to Calgary so he could keep fighting fires</abstract>
 
 <byline>Jane Armstrong</byline>
 
 </body.head>
 
 <photo href="file://images/MAC02_THE_ENDMERGE1.jpg"></photo>
 
 <photo.byline>illustration by marc ngui</photo.byline>
 
 <body.content>
 <p>Nicholas Vachon was born Sept. 12, 1981, at Montfort Hospital in Ottawa to Isabelle and Claude Vachon, two quiet schoolteachers who lived in Curran, a small village about 80 km east of Ottawa. Nicholas was their first son, the third of five Vachon children. </p>
 
 <p>As a boy, Nicholas was serious beyond his years, Claude says. He brooded about global issues like pollution and foreign conflicts, and pestered his father with questions about the 1991 Iraq war. Art was an outlet, and he&rsquo;d spend hours drawing elaborate pictures of war scenes and sinking ships. </p>
 
 <p>At the village school, the other kids bullied Nicholas. But his younger sister, Marie-Claude, worshipped him. In winter, they&rsquo;d take their sleds to the highest hill in town, packing a picnic so they could spend the entire day on the slope. &ldquo;We did everything together,&rdquo; Marie-Claude says. &ldquo;I wanted to be with him everywhere he went.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Nicholas had a thirst for adventure and physical challenges. Together, he and his dad, a phys. ed. teacher and Scout leader, hiked peaks in Quebec and New York state and canoed the lakes near their home. When Nicholas was 12, Claude took him on a week-long trip that ended at Lac Vert in the Gatineau region. Nicholas instantly fell in love with the secluded spot with the sparkling green water. </p>
 
 <p>In high school, Nicholas&rsquo;s life took a dark turn. He started drinking and using drugs. Claude says his teenage son didn&rsquo;t feel like he belonged anywhere. &ldquo;He was a misfit. It was a hard time for him.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>His grades plummeted and eventually he was expelled. He fought with his family, including Marie-Claude. &ldquo;It was really hard to get close to Nick,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;His dark years were really dark.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>At age 20, he sought help. He entered a detox centre in Ottawa and when he emerged, got his high school diploma and earned a mechanic&rsquo;s licence from Algonquin College. He found work at a garage in Rockland, an Ottawa suburb where his parents had moved. </p>
 
 <p>In 2005, he met M&eacute;lanie Abdelnour at a Christmas party. She was instantly attracted to the shy, serious man. He was &ldquo;insecure, I think, frightened of basically having to start his life over.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>For years, the pair was inseparable. Nicholas taught her to snowboard and brought her to Lac Vert on camping trips. At home, he worked hard to repair his strained relationships. Marie-Claude and younger brother Jean Philippe were at first leery. &ldquo;You wonder, &lsquo;Are you really okay? Is this really the time to open my heart? Because I don&rsquo;t want to have it broken again,&rsquo; &rdquo; says Marie-Claude. </p>
 
 <p>In 2009, Nick answered a recruitment ad for volunteer firefighters at the Clarence-Rockland Fire Department. Claude had urged him to apply. &ldquo;You love action,&rdquo; Claude told his son. &ldquo;This would be a good challenge for you.&rdquo; </p>
 
 <p>Nicholas loved firefighting, especially the physical rigours. Sometimes, Claude came to watch his son&rsquo;s rescue training sessions on the Ottawa River. Nicholas juggled his day job as a mechanic with firefighting. He carried his pager with him everywhere and responded to every call he could, even if it was the middle of the night. </p>
 
 <p>In early 2012, he and M&eacute;lanie split up. They&rsquo;d been growing apart for years, but remained friends. Nicholas thought about moving out West for a fresh start. His older sister Jade lived in Calgary, and on visits there, he remarked on the beauty of the Rocky Mountains and the economic opportunities. </p>
 
 <p>&ldquo;I could double my salary,&rdquo; he told his father. For months, Nicholas talked of moving West, but had recently dropped the subject altogether. He told Marie-Claude he decided to stay in Rockland because he wanted to pursue firefighting full-time. And he couldn&rsquo;t leave his friends and family behind. </p>
 
 <p>On Dec. 14, 2012, Marie-Claude threw a Christmas party and invited both brothers. Five years ago, the two were barely speaking. That Friday night, Nicholas, Jean-Philippe and Marie-Claude stood for hours in her kitchen, laughing and swapping stories from their childhood. </p>
 
 <p>The next night, Nicholas donned a new designer suit and headed to a Christmas party for firefighters and Clarence-Rockland municipal employees at the Clarence Creek arena. Buses were ordered to ensure revellers got home safely. But Nicholas left the party right after dinner and struck out for home on foot on a side road. Half an hour into the walk, a car hit him. Nicholas was killed instantly. </p>
 
 </body.content>
 
</body>
</catalog>