<catalog><body>
 
  <sections>From the editors</sections>
  
 <body.head>
 
  <hedline>There&rsquo;s a silver lining  in the cloudy F-35 fiasco</hedline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_EDIT99.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>$24 billion over budget: Conservatives grossly underestimated the total cost of F-35s</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Samuel King Jr./U.S. Air Force/AP</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The Canadian Forces webpage extolling the virtues of the F-35 Joint Strike Fighter is amply supplied with photos of the sleek jet silhouetted against crimson sunsets and streaking across scenic vistas. What else will one find there? An unusual caveat admitting the F-35 may never actually fly the colours of the Royal Canadian Air Force. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;This website may contain some information associated with the acquisition of Canada&rsquo;s next fighter aircraft which may no longer be current,&rdquo; the page says, a polite way of acknowledging the jet has become a black mark on defence procurement generally and an enormous political headache for the Conservative government. </p>
  
    <p>Recent figures from a comprehensive KPMG audit put total procurement and maintenance costs for 65 F-35s at more than $40 billion. This has finally prompted the Conservative government to reconsider its fighter jet purchase. It&rsquo;s a far cry from last year&rsquo;s election campaign, when the Conservatives firmly declared the F-35 to be the only plane that could fulfill Canada&rsquo;s needs, and at a total cost of $16 billion. </p>
  
    <p>While the F-35 saga has properly been declared a fiasco, and further evidence of how Stephen Harper&rsquo;s government has tried to run roughshod over Canada&rsquo;s parliamentary structures, what&rsquo;s been lost in this tale is the fact that Canada&rsquo;s democratic institutions performed well, and are vigorously defending taxpayer interests. </p>
  
    <p>The first legitimate concerns raised about the cost and procurement of the F-35, which was awarded without an open tender, came in October 2010, when Alan Williams, former assistant deputy minister of national defence, told a parliamentary committee the F-35 sole-source contract raised troubling issues of transparency, bias and the possibility that costs could rise uncontrollably. </p>
  
    <p>From there the issue became political, taken up with much gusto by opposition party leaders Michael Ignatieff and Jack Layton. The Parliamentary Budget Officer later released a report putting the total cost at $29 billion over 30 years. And recall that the Harper government&rsquo;s reluctance to release all cost data on the F-35 was one of the reasons behind the non-confidence motion that triggered the 2011 federal election. </p>
  
    <p>Earlier this year, federal auditor general Michael Ferguson released another devastating report on the F-35 contract. Critical flaws cited by Ferguson included &ldquo;significant weaknesses in the decision-making process used by national defence&rdquo; and a lack of &ldquo;due diligence&rdquo; from bureaucratic oversight. It appears defence officials decided early on which plane they wanted and then carefully massaged the data to ensure their political bosses only saw information that bolstered their case. Necessary government oversight was nowhere to be seen. </p>
  
    <p>Now, with the added opinion of the KPMG report, we find the all-in cost has blown past $40 billion. And the federal government has been forced to restart its search for jets to replace our aging CF-18s. </p>
  
    <p>All this certainly looks like a fiasco. And the Harper government seems to have deliberately stonewalled and obfuscated throughout the process. Nonetheless the checks and balances of the parliamentary system did their job. Expert opinion at parliamentary committee hearings raised important issues. The media and opposition parties offered a full public airing to these concerns. Independent officers of Parliament, including the Parliamentary Budget Officer and auditor general, dug deeper into the issue and presented information that contradicted the government&rsquo;s claims. Finally, mounting public pressure forced further investigations, such as the KPMG report. The final result: a hitherto resolute government was forced to cave, and in dramatic fashion. </p>
  
    <p>And keep in mind that, according to the auditor general, only $335 million has been spent so far on the F-35 program. While still a lot of money, this is a small fraction of the expected total bill, whichever jet is ultimately selected. A bigger fiasco would have involved buying the F-35s for $16 billion, only to find out later the real bill was $40 billion or more. </p>
  
    <p>There&rsquo;s clearly much that needs fixing at Defence, to make no mention of the Harper government&rsquo;s bizarre fixation with secrecy and message control. But the scrutiny and oversight of Parliament is still in good working order. In particular, the endless conflict between the Parliamentary Budget Officer and federal cabinet has once again proven to be a good thing for taxpayers. Plus, this episode ought to put paid to widespread complaints that the unilingual Ferguson was the wrong man for the job when he was hired as auditor general in 2011. The vigilance and independence of both offices are crucial to Canadian democracy, and both must remain free from political inference. </p>
  
    <p>Now all we need to do is find the right fighter jet for Canada&rsquo;s air force. </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Letters</sections>
  
  <body.head>Letters</body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_LETTERS23.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.byline>Nathan Denette/CP</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Family ties </p>
  
    <p>Thanks for your editorial on the &ldquo;post-familial&rdquo; world we&rsquo;re living in (&ldquo;Are we facing a future without families?&rdquo; From the editors, Dec. 17). This past summer, a friend of mine had her 10th child, a boy, healthy and surrounded by caring siblings in a house they all help to run. Another friend just had her eighth. Another is due with her fifth and two are expecting their third. It&rsquo;s a beautiful growing world, at least in some pockets of the country. Of course, there&rsquo;s a cost. Everything costs. It&rsquo;s about values. These days, family values do seem counter-cultural. I&rsquo;d love to see that change. </p>
  
    <p><em>Dayna Mazzuca, Victoria  </em></p>
  
 
  
    <p>Your editorial overlooks the increasing number of men who refuse to risk their lives, love, money and future in a no-win marriage. The courts, society and government tilt the playing field against men, with unfair and punishing levels of alimony and child support. As a 61-year-old lifelong bachelor, I can understand why so many young men now refuse to sacrifice everything for little in return. That doesn&rsquo;t make them self-indulgent, as you claim; it makes them smart enough to understand that the cards are stacked against them. </p>
  
    <p><em>Gerold Becker, Thunder Bay, Ont. </em></p>
  
 
  
    <p>The editorial praising Canada&rsquo;s immigration policies states that these have insulated us from the &ldquo;worst of global depopulation trends.&rdquo; Temporary access to non-renewable fossil fuels has allowed human numbers to overshoot basic ecological carrying capacity. We had better get used to the fact that we have a choice between adopting policies that gradually decrease the global population to levels that can be supported by renewable energy sources&mdash;or having population decreases thrust upon us by natural-resource scarcity in the long term. Modern, complex societies depend on abundant energy. We know that fossil fuel will ultimately be exhausted. </p>
  
    <p><em>Peter Salonius, Durham Bridge, N.B. </em></p>
  
   
  
    <p>It&rsquo;s irresponsible of you to state that creating more suburban sprawl will result in more family units in Canada. While your cited research shows that more families live in the suburbs, it doesn&rsquo;t show the suburbs create families. What evidence do you have that people would not have families if suburbs did not exist? By your logic, if you transplanted people from downtown condos into the suburbs, automatically, they would have babies. </p>
  
    <p><em>Shannon Whittle, Ottawa  </em></p>
  
    <p>Real heroism </p>
  
    <p>What a joy to read the discussion with Pte. Taumy St-Hilaire (Interview, Dec. 24), who is, in my estimation, the type of military person who deserves the Star of Military Valour he received, but not just for his heroic act. I have two sons who were both Army reservists and served overseas&mdash;one in Bosnia and one in Afghanistan&mdash;so I have a deep respect for those who decide to be part of our armed forces. In this case, it is not the heroism of this soldier that makes me write, it is St-Hilaire&rsquo;s incredible modesty. The father and child he saved may never know his name, but St-Hilaire&rsquo;s insistence that his fellow soldiers were equally part of this act of bravery is commendable. The precise teamwork of this troop is brought to the fore by this soldier&rsquo;s comments. </p>
  
    <p><em>Sue Boxall, Fort Qu&rsquo;Appelle, Sask. </em></p>
  
    <p>Throw the bums out </p>
  
    <p>It&rsquo;s hard to argue with your choice of Elizabeth May as Parliamentarian of the Year (The Power List, Dec. 3). But the contest is unfair to dedicated Conservative MPs who tirelessly vote &ldquo;yea&rdquo; on omnibus bills that no one has time to read, let alone debate, and who stand together to keep budget details away from the prying eyes of parliamentarians. To give them a chance at recognition, <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em> must also introduce an Anti-Parliamentarian of the Year award. As for Stephen Harper being the Most Knowledgeable Parliamentarian&mdash;well, he&rsquo;s the only one eligible. </p>
  
    <p><em>Bart Hawkins Kreps, Port Hope, Ont. </em></p>
  
  
  
    <p>Surely the appellation under Stephen Harper&rsquo;s name in the Dec. 3 issue is incorrect (&ldquo;The 25 most important people in Ottawa,&rdquo; The Power List). Shouldn&rsquo;t this read &ldquo;the dictator,&rdquo; not &ldquo;the decider&rdquo;?  </p>
  
    <p><em>Phyllis Thom, Surrey, B.C.  </em></p>
  
 
  
    <p>Writing about Immigration Minister Jason Kenney, Paul Wells claims there is &ldquo;no anti-immigration constituency in Canada.&rdquo; What planet are you from? From the Fraser Institute to the man on the street, the hard-working, taxpaying Canadian citizen is tired of being treated like a second-class citizen, while many of these new arrivals benefit from housing assistance, language lessons, free eyeglasses and health care, not to mention that Canada doesn&rsquo;t even have the infrastructure to keep supporting all these immigrants. We need a moratorium of immigration and a complete overhaul of a system that is abused, bruised, battered and far too benevolent.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Valerie Price, Westmount, Que.  </em></p>
  
    <p>Deporting criminals </p>
  
    <p>Bravo to Immigration Minister Jason Kenney for his persistent, rational and fair approach to the expeditious deportation of foreign criminals (&ldquo;Foreign convictions,&rdquo; National, Nov. 26). My vote stands for actions that protect Canadians and preserve our laws&mdash;laws that have been formulated by our elected politicians, not by a special-interest group of immigration lawyers. I would suggest that when a judge arbitrarily reduces a federal conviction to a provincial one of two years less a day, that the judge be called before an inquiry to justify the decision.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Brien Dolan, Campbell River, B.C. </em></p>
  
    <p>The death of history </p>
  
    <p>The remarkable Viking research of archaeologist Patricia Sutherland (&ldquo;A twist in time,&rdquo; National, Nov. 26) and her incongruent dismissal from the Canadian Museum of Civilization is symptomatic of the ruin that has been visited upon our National Library and Archives, Parks Canada and the Canadian Museum of Civilization&mdash;all institutions vital to Canadian archaeology, history and genealogy research. More than just a matter of budget cuts, it seems our politicians want to keep us in the dark about our collective past. Politicians and their parties come and go, but Canadian heritage is the legacy of all Canadians, present and future. </p>
  
    <p><em>Joyce M. Wright, Ottawa </em></p>
  
    <p>Apr&egrave;s tu </p>
  
    <p>Regarding your article about the politics of French pronouns (&ldquo;Time for &lsquo;<em>tu</em>&rsquo; to go?&rdquo; International, Dec. 17), the use of &ldquo;<em>tu</em>&rdquo; is not semantics; rather, it&rsquo;s a linguistic tool. &ldquo;<em>Tu</em>&rdquo; and &ldquo;<em>vous</em>&rdquo; give one the opportunity to distinguish between levels of formality in address, which correspond to levels of formality in relationships. I have more than passing familiarity with a half-dozen languages. Among these, only English does not have, or no longer has, a similar tool. Rather than drop &ldquo;<em>tu</em>&rdquo; from French, let&rsquo;s give serious consideration to reintroducing &ldquo;thou&rdquo; to English.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Emanuel Laufer, Halifax  </em></p>
  
    <p>Fencing in the rogues </p>
  
    <p>I must state that I take exception to your inclusion of Sea Shepherd&rsquo;s Paul Watson in your &ldquo;Rogues&rsquo; gallery&rdquo; in the Dec. 17 Newsmakers issue. While the bristly Watson may not be quite as user-friendly as icon-ized David Suzuki, there is no way he should be sharing space in a collection of &ldquo;dubious achievers.&rdquo; His steadfast quest to save the world&rsquo;s whales from those who would decimate them should be applauded, not reviled. He should be included in a section that applauds Canadian heroes. </p>
  
    <p><em>Ian Lidster, Comox, B.C. </em></p>
  
 
  
    <p>In the Olympics section of your Newsmakers issue (&ldquo;London calling,&rdquo; Newsmakers, Dec. 17), you had a brief report on the Korean fencer Shin A Lam, whom you accused of having a &ldquo;temper tantrum&rdquo; after losing a match by one contested point. In fencing, you may appeal any decision the referee makes, and if you do, you must remain on the piste until a decision is made. As a result, Shin had to remain on the piste for an hour, unsure of who had won the bout. Had she left, the appeal made by her country would not have even been considered. She did not impede the tournament in any way that was against the rules of fencing. If she had, she would have been black-carded, meaning she would have been kicked out of the tournament.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Katy Holland, Victoria  </em></p>
  
    <p>Prince George, home of the safe </p>
  
    <p><em>Maclean&rsquo;s referred to Prince George as the &ldquo;most crime-ridden&rdquo; city in Canada (&ldquo;Canada&rsquo;s most dangerous cities,&rdquo; National, Dec. 17). In 2011, Prince George did not have a single homicide, though it was statistically credited with one homicide from a 2010 incident. StatsCan&rsquo;s recent homicide report listed a high number of murders in Toronto and Montreal and a record number in Edmonton, yet none of these large cities made Maclean&rsquo;s top 10 list. While homicides should likely not be used as the only indicator in the crime ranking, I would think having zero homicides in a community would weigh heavily when concluding which city in Canada is the most dangerous. Prince George is a challenging policing environment. It is a hub for northern British Columbia, and with that comes a segment of the population who participate in a high-risk lifestyle that includes gangs, drugs and violence. To respond, the Prince George RCMP has launched a number of crime-reduction initiatives that focus on the prolific offenders in our community. We have seen a number of successes, with no fewer then 40 chronic offenders successfully targeted and arrested since April 1. The high percentage of people in Prince George who contribute positively to the community feel safe. Those who participate in a high-risk lifestyle are the ones at risk.  </em></p>
  
    <p><em>Supt. Eric Stubbs, Officer in Charge, Prince George detachment of the RCMP, Prince George, B.C. </em></p>
  
   
  
    <p>I grew up in Prince George, married my high-school sweetheart and raised five children here. Four of my grandchildren were also raised here, and now my five great-grandchildren are enjoying their childhoods in Prince George. I have never felt unsafe in this city. We have all the amenities of a much larger city but, alas, we also have to deal with crime and social issues. What city doesn&rsquo;t? Why don&rsquo;t you send a crew out and see for yourself? Only this time, please look at the whole city and you will be pleasantly surprised!  </p>
  
    <p><em>Evelyn Rebman, Prince George, B.C. </em></p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>This week</sections>
  
 <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Good News</hedline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_WEEK_GOODNEWS01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>A child in Romania signs the world&rsquo;s longest letter to Santa Claus</photo.caption>
   
  <photo.byline>Bogdan Cristel/Reuters</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
    <p>Clement Claus </p>
  
    <p>The Harper government has slashed nearly 11,000 public sector jobs this year, and thousands more are on the chopping block. So what&rsquo;s the good news for federal civil servants? The ones still standing are free to decorate their cubicles with tinsel, wreaths and menorahs. Repeating a directive issued last holiday season&mdash;after a senior bureaucrat in Quebec banished all Christmas trees from front-line Service Canada offices across the province&mdash;Treasury Board president Tony Clement said employees are free to break out the ornaments. The government &ldquo;will not allow the Christmas spirit to be grinched,&rdquo; he said.  </p>
  
    <p>Myth buster </p>
  
    <p>The chairman of the U.S. Federal Communications Commission has urged the Federal Aviation Administration to finally let passengers use electronic devices during takeoff and landing. There is no evidence that tablets or laptops cause aircraft interference (some airlines have even replaced flight manuals in the cockpit with iPad versions) and thankfully, the FAA is now reviewing its policies. Because the last thing we need is 15 minutes of off-line existence. </p>
  
    <p>Parental plus </p>
  
    <p>Despite an abundance of anecdotal evidence to the contrary, it turns out parenting is actually good for your health. A new Danish study examined more than 21,000 couples who had sought in vitro fertility treatment and found that women who remained childless were four times more likely to die prematurely compared to those who had a child. The researchers also found a smaller but still significant trend with men: fathers are half as likely to have early deaths as childless men. Something to think about the next time junior has you pulling out your hair. </p>
  
    <p>No monkey business  </p>
  
    <p>A well-dressed monkey goes shopping in a Toronto Ikea store, and the Twitterverse goes bananas (pun intended). But this week&rsquo;s best newsmaker from the animal kingdom comes courtesy of Vancouver Island, where a German shepherd police dog named Rook not only protected his RCMP handler from a family of hungry black bears&mdash;but managed to chase down and capture his suspect, too. &ldquo;It happened so quick,&rdquo; said the handler, Const. Jarrod Trickett. &ldquo;It was not your typical morning, put it that way.&rdquo;</p>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC52_WEEK_BADNEWS01.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption>Fishermen walk through an impoverished harbour near Karachi, Pakistan</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>khtar Soomro/Reuters</photo.byline>
  
  <hedline>Bad News</hedline>

    <p>Hot off the presses </p>
  
    <p>Memo to climate change cynics: you&rsquo;re wrong. A new report published in the journal <em>Nature </em>says global warming predictions made two decades ago have proved largely accurate. In 1990, a group of the world&rsquo;s top climate scientists predicted a temperature hike of 1.1&deg; C between 1990 and 2030 (or 0.55&deg; by the halfway point of 2010). The actual figure? Just slightly below the estimate, at 0.39&deg;. According to the report, the really bad news is yet to come, as environmental policies enacted between now and 2030 &ldquo;will only very gradually manifest themselves in the climate signal.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>&lsquo;A&rsquo; for effort, &lsquo;F&rsquo; for timing </p>
  
    <p>Just months after a teacher was turfed for giving zeros to students who didn&rsquo;t complete their work, the Edmonton Public School Board has reversed its stance and is now proposing a policy that allows for zeros. It is the right decision&mdash;but it comes a few months too late. Instead of firing Lynden Dorval for having the audacity to fail a student who missed a test or skipped an assignment, school officials should have held him up as a model for fellow teachers. They failed to do the right thing, and their sudden change of heart can never fix that.  </p>
  
    <p>Hard at work </p>
  
    <p>Speaking of model employees, it was a not-so-stellar week in workplace conduct. In Vancouver, a health official was canned after peeking at the medical records of five local media personalities. (Out of &ldquo;curiosity,&rdquo; she said.) In Toronto, a Pearson airport worker was caught inside a terminal watching porn on his laptop. And a shocking new study says Canadian psychiatrists are twice as likely as other doctors to face professional discipline&mdash;and nearly four times as likely to be sanctioned for sexual misconduct. </p>
  
    <p>(Down)loaded weapons </p>
  
    <p>Having a hard time keeping up with technology? Try wrapping your mind around this: as 3D printers become cheaper and easier to procure (one desktop model costs $2,200), a group called Defense Distributed is developing a &ldquo;fully printable firearm.&rdquo; So far, they&rsquo;ve managed to print off a workable trigger and grip that can attach to a rifle. It&rsquo;s still a work in progress: in testing, it broke after firing just six rounds. </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>This week</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>Newsmakers</hedline>
  
    <abstract>Berlusconi returns to the political ring, Ch&aacute;vez takes leave, and Christine Sinclair gets her due</abstract>
  
  <byline>Charlie Gillis, Rosemary Westwood and  Tamsin McMahon</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_NEWSMAKERS05.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Christine Sinclair</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Julian Finney/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Making their mark </p>
  
    <p>A week after soccer&rsquo;s brain trust, FIFA, snubbed Canada&rsquo;s Christine Sinclair, fans of the game had plenty to celebrate. First, the Argentine superstar Lionel Messi scored his 86th goal of 2012, surpassing a 40-year-old record and affirming the Barcelona striker as the greatest scorer the game has seen. Then, Sinclair was announced as winner of the Lou Marsh Award, given to Canada&rsquo;s top athlete of the year. The honour comes after FIFA left Sinclair off its shortlist for female player of 2012&mdash;a cold shoulder some chalked up to Sinclair&rsquo;s intemperate remarks about the officiating after Canada&rsquo;s hard-fought semi-final loss to the U.S. at the London Olympics. To John Herdman, Sinclair&rsquo;s national team coach, her body of work speaks for itself: &ldquo;I&rsquo;d put her up there with the biggest and best athletes in the world.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>Back to bunga?  </p>
  
    <p><em>Silvio Berlusconi</em> could provide survival tips to vampires. No sooner had his foes left him for dead, politically speaking, than the scandal-ridden former Italian prime minister rose anew, forcing current PM Mario Monti out of power this week, and declaring his candidacy for the national leadership. Berlusconi&rsquo;s resurrection marks a new low for Italian politics, critics say: at 76, he is still appealing convictions for tax fraud, while fighting charges of having sex with an underage prostitute&mdash;this, at time when Italy is drifting toward a full-blown debt crisis. Yet the media tycoon hasn&rsquo;t lost an ounce of audacity. On his Facebook page, he claimed that he tried to find a worthy successor, but added: &ldquo;There isn&rsquo;t one.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Good, but not golden </p>
  
    <p>Despite their &ldquo;exquisitely executed&rdquo; (not to mention &ldquo;exceptionally difficult&rdquo;) interpretation of <em>Carmen</em>, Canadian ice dancers Tessa Virtue and Scott Moir placed second at the Grand Prix final in Sochi, Russia. Their American rivals Meryl Davis and Charlie White clinched the gold.  </p>
  
    <p>Vengeance, served cold </p>
  
    <p>The customer might not always be right, but she surely doesn&rsquo;t deserve to be labelled a &ldquo;fat girl&rdquo; on her bill, as three women were last week at Chilly D&rsquo;s bar in Stockton, Calif. <em>Christine Duran</em>, <em>Isabel Robles</em> and <em>Christina Huerta</em> were outraged when their electronically printed receipt arrived carrying the &ldquo;fat girls&rdquo; notation in the upper left-hand corner. A duty manager tried to mollify them, but seemed to snicker even as he offered them 50 per cent off their bill, they said, prompting them to take their story to the media. That did the trick: their server&mdash;identified only as &ldquo;Jeff&rdquo;&mdash;was fired, while the bar manager offered a grovelling apology. </p>
  
    <p>The revolution pauses now  </p>
  
    <p>Venezuelan President <em>Hugo Ch&aacute;vez</em> departed for Cuba this week to undergo another operation for cancer. While the 58-year-old has successfully fought the illness before, Ch&aacute;vez caused greater concern this time by publicly anointing a successor, his vice-president. Were he unable to continue as president, Ch&aacute;vez said, &ldquo;my strong opinion, as clear as the full moon, irrevocable, absolute, total&rdquo; is that &ldquo;you should elect Nicol&aacute;s Maduro,&rdquo; he told Venezuelans. &ldquo;Long live our homeland!&rdquo; he shouted as he boarded a jet bound for Havana.  </p>
  
    <p>Christmas came early  </p>
  
    <p>Back when Albertan <em>Jack Speers</em> was shipped off to Ontario for training during the Second World War, his mother wrote him a Christmas Eve letter. It arrived at his doorstep just in time for the holidays, albeit 69 years too late. Speers, now 87 and living in Namao, Alta., received the letter late last month from an RCMP officer who had retrieved it from the home of a local youth. Authorities couldn&rsquo;t explain where exactly it had been for the better part of a century. In the letter dated Dec. 24, 1943, Speers&rsquo;s mother, Bertha May, wishes him a quick recovery from the flu and discusses the $12 fountain pen she bought for his father&mdash;a princely sum in those days. The letter ends: &ldquo;Merry Christmas and Happy New Year. Signed Mom.&rdquo; A bittersweet Christmas present for Speers, whose mother died 20 years ago. </p>
  
 
      <p>An &lsquo;it&rsquo; girl for the intelligentsia </p>
  
  <p>Lena Dunham&rsquo;s book proposal was leaked online this week, giving fans a peak at the 66-page proposal that landed her a $3.7-million book deal with Random House. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve been in therapy since I was seven,&rdquo; the 26-year-old creator of Emmy Award-winning show <em>Girls</em> writes, and &ldquo;at 24, I felt like an old maid.&rdquo; Dunham also posed as Twiggy, the doe-eyed &rsquo;60s supermodel this week, complete with heavy lashes, and a slight bouffant, an apparent comment on image and fame.</p>
  
  <p>Reality bites </p>
  
    <p><em>John McAfee</em>&rsquo;s turn as an unpaid reality star goes on. On Sunday, the anti-virus software millionaire conducted a live-streaming webcast from the Guatemalan detention centre where he&rsquo;s fighting a deportation order to neighbouring Belize. Looking tired but generally unfazed, he mused in the grainy video that he&rsquo;d like to return to the United States or, failing that, the United Kingdom, where he was born and holds citizenship. The quixotic 67-year-old is wanted in Belize in the shooting death of his neighbour, Gregory Faull&mdash;a crime he swears he didn&rsquo;t commit and that police there are setting him up for. In the broadcast, he repeated his oft-stated warning: &ldquo;If I am returned [to Belize], bad things will clearly happen to me.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>Inciting immolation? </p>
  
    <p>Two Chinese men became the &#64257;rst to face homicide charges under China&rsquo;s newly enacted law targeting people who &ldquo;facilitate self-immolation.&rdquo; Lorang Konchok, a 40-year-old monk, and his 31-year-old nephew, Lorang Tsering, were arrested for &ldquo;inciting&rdquo; eight people to set themselves on fire, in protest of Chinese rule, state news agency Xinhua reported. The arrests appear to be part of China&rsquo;s efforts to rein in the self-immolations. There have been 80 such demonstrations this year alone. </p>
  
 
    <p>A teetotaller&rsquo;s lament  </p>
  
    <p><em>Jason Carter</em> doesn&rsquo;t drink. Alas for the 37-year-old mayor of Charlo, N.B., tippling is apparently part of municipal life in the seaside village. Carter resigned last week, seven months after taking office, saying his fellow council members wouldn&rsquo;t stop partying in his office, and insisted on stocking the mayoral fridge full of booze. Concerned the alcohol might cloud council&rsquo;s judgment and expose the village to lawsuits, he tossed out the booze and put up a sign declaring his fridge alcohol-free. His colleagues grew angry at being &ldquo;dictated to,&rdquo; and Carter finally gave up. &ldquo;I strongly believe that alcohol has no place in the governance of a municipality,&rdquo; he wrote in his resignation letter, &ldquo;especially when members of council and staff are being paid and are on duty.&rdquo; </p>
  
  
    <p>An icon takes ill  </p>
  
    <p>Uncertainty swirled around the health of Nelson Mandela this week, as the 94-year-old former president of South Africa sought treatment for a recurring lung infection. South Africa&rsquo;s defence minister told reporters the revered anti-apartheid leader and Nobel Peace Prize laureate was &ldquo;doing very well&rdquo; after a recent visit. His wife, Gra&ccedil;a Machel, said it was painful to see his trademark &ldquo;spirit and sparkle&rdquo; fading. </p>
  
    <p>Morsi concedes </p>
  
    <p>Egypt&rsquo;s President Mohamed Morsi rescinded the most controversial elements of a decree that had led to violent street protests in Cairo. But the move wasn&rsquo;t enough to satisfy opponents, who argue that Morsi&rsquo;s Muslim Brotherhood will force through its draft constitution, placing the country under Islamist control. Determined to push forward with a planned referendum on the constitution, Morsi granted the Egyptian army the power to arrest citizens to maintain order. The concession, apparently intended to highlight Morsi&rsquo;s flexibility, seemed only to deepen divisions. Opposition leaders responded by announcing they would boycott the referendum, while protesters flooded the streets around Cairo&rsquo;s presidential palace. </p>
  
 
    <p>The monkey and the meme</p>
    
    <p>To the query: what else can you find at Ikea? Answer: a monkey. A sweet simian was spotted wandering around a Toronto Ikea parking lot on Dec. 9 after it escaped from a crate in its owner&rsquo;s car. Twitter images of the #IkeaMonkey sped around the world, while animal control &#64257;ned the monkey&rsquo;s owners, and moved the animal to Sunderland, Ont.&rsquo;s Story Book Farm Primate Sanctuary. The baby rhesus macaque, named <em>Darwin</em>, wore a miniature shearling coat and a diaper, earning him kudos from around the world for fashion sense perhaps not typically seen in the suburbs north of Toronto. To no one&rsquo;s surprise, it turned out he&rsquo;d spent time in Montreal.</p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Opinion</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Ottawa</slug>
  
   <hedline>We mean it. Except when  we don&rsquo;t.</hedline>
  
    <byline>Paul Wells</byline>

</body.head>
  
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_WELLS01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>China is coming: State-owned enterprises like China&rsquo;s CNOOC will be permitted to buy Canadian firms just this once, then not again, said Harper</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>ChinaFotoPress/Keystone Press</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The other day Stephen Harper&rsquo;s government announced it will support an NDP bill that will require officers of Parliament to be fluent in French and English. &ldquo;Our support for this bill,&rdquo; said Industry Minister Christian Paradis, &ldquo;sends a clear message that the promotion of the two official languages, now more than ever, guides the actions of the federal government.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Paradis&rsquo;s comment was accurate. But it would have been more precise if, instead of &ldquo;now more than ever,&rdquo; he had said, &ldquo;now more than in October 2011, when we appointed an auditor general who couldn&rsquo;t speak French and spent months insisting that was no big deal.&rdquo; In short, the government is now preparing to require, by law, that it not do what it just did. </p>
  
    <p>It has been that kind of month. More or less explicit repudiation of previous acts and stances has been the theme of the year-end for Stephen Harper and his colleagues. One of the questions we are left with is how Harper, notoriously a risk-averse, control-freak incrementalist, managed to leave hundreds of feet of skid marks around a bunch of big files. </p>
  
    <p>Take the new jet fighters. We used to call them F-35s, but now we are less sure. In the office of Rona Ambrose, the public works minister, there is a jar. I am told in all seriousness that if anyone involved in &#64257;nding a replacement for Canada&rsquo;s aging F-18 fighter fleet calls that replacement &ldquo;the F-35,&rdquo; the minister has them put a dollar in the jar. That&rsquo;s how adamant Ambrose is that the choice of the F-35 not be locked in. </p>
  
    <p>Of course for two years the government was adamant that the choice of the F-35 was locked in. It&rsquo;s a little cruel to dig up old quotes on this. But just one. On March 10, 2011, the Prime Minister said: &ldquo;This is the option that was selected some time ago, because it is the only option available,&rdquo; he said. &ldquo;This is the only fighter available that serves the purposes that our air force needs.&rdquo; Hope you have a dollar for the jar, big guy. </p>
  
    <p>Of course what happened is that times changed. The government&rsquo;s costing of the F-35 was optimistic and short-term to begin with. Optimism worked out the way it usually does when you&rsquo;re buying something big and untested. The old talking points grew stale, then ludicrous, and the government stuck with them until the government looked stale and ludicrous, and now it denies saying what it once said. None of this is a tragedy: the jets haven&rsquo;t been bought, no purchase order has been cancelled, there is still time to choose a more realistic course. But it&rsquo;s all been a bit awkward. </p>
  
    <p>Take energy. A year ago Harper pronounced the nation&rsquo;s energy sector open for business, shed a tear for the newly reluctant Yankee customer who had blown whatever right he might once have had to our bounty, and looked eastward, which means westward across the Pacific, to new markets. These markets included China, which was new only in the sense that Harper had spent five years hoping he could find some other market as ravenous as China but less, well, Communist. The Chinese welcomed our new-found willingness to sell them things, and responded with new-found eagerness to buy Canadian things. Things like Alberta. Harper faced another conundrum. </p>
  
    <p>At the beginning of the month he announced his solution: state-owned enterprises would be permitted to buy Canadian firms just this once, and then not again. His stated reason was that if too many state-owned enterprises from one country bought up parts of the oil patch, it would constitute foreign government ownership of an entire industry. So he would permit two proposed takeovers, including the purchase of Nexen by China&rsquo;s CNOOC, then no more. </p>
  
    <p>Got it. State-owned industry bad, oil sands sensitive. None of this explains why the government rejected the purchase of Potash Corp., which is not in the oil sands, by Australia&rsquo;s BHP Billiton, which is not state-owned. Nor does it explain why the government first blocked the takeover of Progress Energy by Malaysia&rsquo;s Petronas, before accepting it later. </p>
  
    <p>(Full disclosure: my spouse, Lisa Samson, is a registered lobbyist for Progress and Petronas.) </p>
  
    <p>The likeliest answer is that Harper was surprised by the antipathy the CNOOC-Nexen bid stirred up. His candidate and visiting party dignitaries heard an earful about it from voters on the doorstep during the recent Calgary Centre by-election campaign. So he improvised an adjustment to earlier plans, and left himself tons of wiggle room for next time. Further energy-sector takeovers by state-owned companies will be accepted &ldquo;in exceptional circumstances,&rdquo; which means: &ldquo;We&rsquo;ll tell you when it happens.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>None of this is a pretty sight, but neither does it spell trouble for Harper in the short term. As long as he usually moves from more trouble to less, he is moving the way Conservative voters want him to. The PM has had a messy year, but on jets, language politics and energy, he has stopped digging himself deeper. Jan. 23 will mark the seventh anniversary of his election. </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Opinion</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Christmas</slug>
  
   <hedline>Santa has a dark side&mdash; as kids well know</hedline>
  
    <byline>Emma Teitel</byline>

  </body.head>
  
  
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_TEITEL01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.byline>China Photos/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Every year, millions of children are told not to talk to strangers, and every year they do. In fact, not only do they talk to strangers; at the behest of their parents, they sit in a stranger&rsquo;s lap. This stranger goes by the name of Santa Claus, Saint Nick, Father Christmas, or Sinterklaas. He could be the Antichrist, but between November and January, from 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. at your local shopping mall, he is God&rsquo;s gift to children everywhere. He is also, as the story we tell them goes, the purveyor of coal, or last year&rsquo;s iPhone, so you better watch out&mdash;that is, sit in his lap and appear at ease while he mumbles platitudes into his glued-on beard. There are those, however, who aren&rsquo;t comfortable with this arrangement. We see them each year: the kids who are dragged kicking and screaming onto the knees of St. Nick. It&rsquo;s a condition our society has dubbed &ldquo;Santaphobia&rdquo; and, judging by recent events, it&rsquo;s probably getting worse. </p>
  
    <p>At the Lowe&rsquo;s Christmas Market in Toronto this month, one Santa Claus decided to critique a three-year-old boy&rsquo;s choice of clothing. According to the boy&rsquo;s mother, Santa looked at her son and said, &ldquo;Oh you&rsquo;re wearing a Toronto Maple Leafs toque. You shouldn&rsquo;t be wearing that; they suck.&rdquo; (The boy went home crying.) At a shopping mall in Portland, Maine, recently, a Santa Claus who was described as &ldquo;weird&rdquo; and &ldquo;grumpy&rdquo; refused to promise a little girl the doll she wanted. (He promised her a football instead.) </p>
  
    <p>Indignant parents took to Facebook and got the bad Santas fired. One thing they probably didn&rsquo;t do, though, was tell the truth. The mother of the crestfallen Maple Leafs fan told her son that Santa was having a bad day. &ldquo;I can&rsquo;t really tell him Santa&rsquo;s a jerk,&rdquo; she said. Which means she can&rsquo;t really tell him that Santa&rsquo;s not Santa. Apparently, a real Santa Claus who hurts your feelings, or smells like rubbing alcohol, is better than no Santa at all.&nbsp; </p>
  
    <p>This means that, unlike other mythological creatures who stalk children (the bogeyman, the monster under the bed), Santa gets a free pass. Parents like to dispel negative myths and affirm seemingly happy ones, but everyone has a dark side. Even Santa.&nbsp;&nbsp; </p>
  
    <p>If you cross him, if you&rsquo;re &ldquo;naughty&rdquo; (and he knows it), there is no room for repentance: you are condemned to a lifetime of inferior presents. He is a true disciplinarian; a throwback to the days when you got real marks on your report card and it was possible to fail&mdash;when the world had clearly defined winners and losers in it. He is the last bastion of tough love in a culture of parenting that has all but rejected it, yet he remains more popular, and as mandatory a part of childhood, than ever. He is omnipotent (&ldquo;he knows if you&rsquo;ve been good or bad&rdquo;) which is, frankly, creepy. But most of all, to a lot of kids, he is&nbsp;real, very real, which means that going to the mall to see Santa isn&rsquo;t a photo opportunity. It&rsquo;s judgment day. </p>
  
    <p>Natale Dankotuwage, a lifelong friend of mine, says Santa put the fear of God in her when she was a child. &ldquo;The whole &lsquo;he sees you while you&rsquo;re sleeping&rsquo; thing? It&rsquo;s scary,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;I thought it was creepy that he could come into your home. It&rsquo;s funny, &rsquo;cause my parents didn&rsquo;t really understand how scared I was. I thought he was like God.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>So did I.&nbsp;I&rsquo;m a Jew, and before I knew about Jesus Christ, I assumed the Christian deity was Santa Claus and that our God (Jehovah) was bogus, or incapacitated, because he couldn&rsquo;t show his face at a&nbsp;single&nbsp;shopping mall. &ldquo;His God is God,&rdquo; Yul Brynner said as Rameses in&nbsp;The Ten Commandments, but he was talking about a deity we hadn&rsquo;t heard from in years, and that appeared as a burning bush. Meanwhile, down the street at Hillcrest Mall in Richmond Hill, Ont., the Christian God was hosting the whole neighbourhood on his lap and promising everyone Tamagotchis. How could my people be so delusional?&nbsp; </p>
  
    <p>I wasn&rsquo;t afraid of Santa, so much as wistful about him (he passed over my house, as he did over the houses of all Jews), but that doesn&rsquo;t mean other kids aren&rsquo;t perfectly justified in being scared of him today.&nbsp;Or that their fear is some manufactured, new-agey invention of paranoid hipster parents who equate Santa with the latest obscure food allergy.&nbsp;We&rsquo;re speaking here of a deep and primal discomfort, even more primal than the Tooth Fairy: there would be something wrong with kids today if they weren&rsquo;t a little creeped out by the fat guy in the red pyjamas.&nbsp;For all the hype, Santa is not all sweetness and light; he&rsquo;s also Big Brother, he&rsquo;s watching you, and he has a sack of toys.&nbsp;Or coal. </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Interview</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Politics</slug>
  
   <hedline>On founding a political party for $26 million&mdash;and tackling corruption in Austria </hedline>
  
    <abstract>Frank Stronach in conversation with Jonathon Gatehouse</abstract>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_INTERVIEW99.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.byline>Cole Garside</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>He is Canada&rsquo;s foremost rags-to-riches story: a poor Austrian immigrant who built a global auto parts empire through his sweat and determination. But even though Frank Stronach recently stepped down from the board of Magna International, the firm he founded in 1957, he is far from retired. There&rsquo;s a just-released autobiography, <em>The Magna Man</em>. And most intriguingly, Team Stronach&mdash; a new, self-funded political party that seeks to shake up the status quo in his homeland.  </p>
  
  
  
    <p>Q: <em>You&rsquo;ve been politically active before&mdash;running for the Liberals in 1988, and supporting your daughter Belinda&rsquo;s campaigns. But why did you want to re-enter the fray at age 80?</em> </p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> I think we all have a conscience. And if things don&rsquo;t work too well we always say, &lsquo;I wish somebody would do something.&rsquo; And now, if my grandchildren ask me if I ever tried to improve society, I can say yes. But it&rsquo;s not a game for me. Before, I made a lot of money&mdash;$40 million or $50 million a year. And now this is going to cost me maybe 20 million euros [$26 million]. And you know that when you enter the political arena there&rsquo;ll be a lot of poisoned arrows flying toward you.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Why Austria? It&rsquo;s a country you left almost 60 years ago. Why not Canada? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Yeah, but for the last 20 years I&rsquo;ve spent a lot of time there. I built a global company. So I got a little closer to the political scene there. It&rsquo;s a much smaller country and I think Europe has got a major, major problem. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: So is it that you think their problems are graver, or just more fixable? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> I think the need is greater in Austria. When they watch television they see what is going on in Greece and Spain and they feel that something is not right. The living standards are still pretty high there, but the debt is enormous. And that will lead to problems. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: You&rsquo;re obviously at the centre of this new party. But there seems to be some confusion about what your role will be. Are you going to stand for election? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> I&rsquo;ve made it quite clear: I will be elected, I will be a member of Parliament. But I won&rsquo;t be the prime minister, or the <em>Bundeskanzler,</em> as they call it. A PM has to be there for his people 24 hours a day, and I am a certain age, I&rsquo;ve worked very hard, and I still want to live. I just want to put a program together, a charter with some basic principles to help develop a more prosperous country. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Since you formed Team Stronach in September, you&rsquo;ve had five sitting MPs join, received official party status, and now you&rsquo;re polling at around 10 per cent. But that&rsquo;s still a long way from power. Some analysts are describing this as a protest party. Is it? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> You know, the media over there is controlled by a very small group of people who want to maintain power. Most of the newspapers are aligned with the ruling party.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: But what are you hoping to achieve? Do you want to be part of someone else&rsquo;s government? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> No, I think the first time we&rsquo;ll get more media attention, then we&rsquo;ll have better access to the public. And the next time around, I think we will get a majority. Austria has had a coalition government for the last 50 years, and every year they have had huge deficits, and now a huge debt. They&rsquo;re going to crash. And hopefully, I can help them avoid that.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: In Canada, you ran as a Liberal. And your daughter was a Conservative MP and then a Liberal one. So where does Team Stronach fit on the political spectrum? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Look, I&rsquo;m no extremist&mdash;neither left, nor right. The party label never meant anything to me. I think it&rsquo;s a matter of what you stand for. And I have very specific programs and proposals, which I think are needed in order to run a country.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: The one that&rsquo;s gained the most attention&mdash;at least on this side of the pond&mdash;is your criticism of the euro. Are you calling for Austria to return to the schilling? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> No, no. I&rsquo;ve said that it&rsquo;s a very complicated subject. But the one thing we know is that this system doesn&rsquo;t work. The difference between a businessman and a politician is that when a businessman sees a giant hole he doesn&rsquo;t throw in more money. But politicians keep doing that because if they admit they made a mistake they won&rsquo;t get re-elected. To have one common European currency is a great, great mistake. There is a great hatred building up from the south against the north. And it&rsquo;s kind of stupid for the German government to be telling the Greeks how to live. I&rsquo;m for the European Union, but only when it comes to avoiding war, and free movement of people and goods. Not the currency. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: But how do you disengage from the EU without causing an even worse crisis? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> How can it get worse? Politicians just say that to scare everybody. It ain&rsquo;t so. You don&rsquo;t need any more consulates or trade missions or anything&mdash;you&rsquo;ve got the Internet. What&rsquo;s important here is the overhead. Austria has got gigantic overhead, and then in addition you have the European overhead. And if you could chop all that, you could have a very high living standard. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Some would argue that Austria already has a very high living standard. </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> No, that&rsquo;s all via debt. It&rsquo;s gigantic. It&rsquo;s not feasible. Maybe the fourth generation could pay it back if you changed things now.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: You&rsquo;re also proposing a switch to a flat tax. </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Yes, yes. Because there are so many grey areas. No one really understands how the system functions in Canada, or the States or Austria, or wherever. That shouldn&rsquo;t be because a society can&rsquo;t function if people don&rsquo;t know the rules.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: You&rsquo;ve always contended that business is simple. So you think politics should be the same? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A: </em>It should be. We don&rsquo;t understand as a people that government can&rsquo;t give you anything unless they take it away first. And they waste maybe 80 per cent. I don&rsquo;t mean to be cynical. There are a lot of idealistic politicians. But their mandate is to be re-elected, and thereby the whole country is managed for political reasons instead of socio-economic ones. And what really worries me is that in the Western world, we have more and more people who take out of the system, and fewer people who pay in. The taxpayers get less and the people on welfare get more.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Analysts say that Team Stronach is taking most of its support from existing parties on the right, like the Freedom Party. </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> No, no. We&rsquo;re taking it from the left and the right. From everywhere. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Okay. But where does your party stand on social issues? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Those issues are very important. And I have a great track record&mdash;you can&rsquo;t run a company unless you take care of people. A country can only be measured by the way it looks after the people who for one reason or another can&rsquo;t take care of themselves.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: But are there social issues you&rsquo;re taking a stand on? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> No. Look, Austria is way over-governed. But I&rsquo;ve said you have to reduce it in a civilized way, not with a chainsaw. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: You&rsquo;ve pledged to cut the size of government by 10 per cent over five years. Don&rsquo;t you have specific sectors you have in mind? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Oh, there are many sectors where it&rsquo;s so flagrant, where&rsquo;s there&rsquo;s so much overhead. We&rsquo;ve got 22 health programs. All with their own bureaucracies. There&rsquo;s a problem there. There&rsquo;s a lot of corruption. It&rsquo;s run by a clique. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Do you feel like corruption in Austria is worse than it is in Canada? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> You read about some new corruption over there every other day.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: You&rsquo;ve done business all over the world. So where does Austria rank in terms of corruption? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Anytime when you have a system where there&rsquo;s no clear-cut tax laws, where there&rsquo;s a lot of grey areas, where politicians aren&rsquo;t directly elected, you&rsquo;ve got a problem. And everything that&rsquo;s not open and democratic leads to corruption.  </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Lots of books have been written about you over the years. </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Not lots of books, vicious books. It&rsquo;s easy to write about me. I&rsquo;m a big guy. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: So that was the motivation for writing your own book? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> No, no. I know who I am. My friends know who I am. The book was written as a guide for young people who want to start in business. To show that there are ways we can improve society. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: In recent years your image has taken a bit of a beating in the press. </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Let&rsquo;s face it. When you run a large company like Magna, you live in a glass house. Printing bad news is better for the papers. Everything was taken out of context. I stayed within the rules. I stayed within the law. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: The criticism that was levelled against you&mdash;about your compensation, and the structure of the company&mdash;do you understand why some investors were upset? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> Look, we got criticized by the pension funds. They have absolutely the worst governance. Their investors get no say. Why don&rsquo;t people write about that? </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: What about your relationship with Canada?&#65279; Are you going to be spending much time here? </em></p>
  
    <p><em>A:</em> I&rsquo;m a big fish. Everybody wants to have a slice of my income. So I follow the rules. I have a whole bunch of lawyers and tax advisers and they work it out with the various governments. That&rsquo;s the way it is.</p>
    
   </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>National</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Quebec</slug>
  
   <hedline>The foundation  of corruption</hedline>
   
   <abstract>Allegations of kickbacks in the construction industry and illegal political financing have shocked Quebec. The inside story of the man at the centre of the storm.</abstract>
  
  <byline>Martin Patriquin</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_QUEBEC01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Coming clean: Zambito is facing 12 fraud charges and admits to bilking taxpayers</photo.caption>
 
  <photo.byline>Vincenzo D&rsquo;Alto</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Lino Zambito is many things, not all of them good. The former contractor, would-be construction magnate and budding restaurateur is currently facing, he estimates, &ldquo;about 12&rdquo; fraud, collusion and breach of trust charges for, among other things, his role in an alleged bid-rigging scheme in the Montreal suburb of Boisbriand. In April, he pleaded guilty to a charge of attempting to subvert the outcome of a municipal election in that same community. Two days after Maclean&rsquo;s met with him at the strip-mall pizzeria he now runs, Revenu Qu&eacute;bec officials raided it in search of some $38,000 in unpaid taxes. And as the owner of the construction company Infrabec, he has, by his own admission, spent much of the last decade participating in a system that bilked taxpayers out of millions of dollars. </p>
  
    <p>Yet it is precisely because of his misdeeds, or at least his willingness to talk about them under oath, that Zambito is something of a folk hero in Quebec these days. Subpoenaed on Sept. 5&mdash;one day after the Quebec election&mdash;by the commission investigating the province&rsquo;s notorious construction industry, Zambito testified for eight days, and what came out of the tall, beefy 43-year-old&rsquo;s mouth shocked a province and arguably brought a premature end to the careers of two big city mayors. </p>
  
    <p>As a contractor in Montreal, Zambito says he participated in bid-rigging schemes involving the Rizzuto Mafia clan that usually culminated with mobsters stuffing wads of cash into their knee-high socks in the ill-lit backroom of a north end coffee shop. He not only kicked up a cut of his profits to those mobsters but also to various municipal and provincial political parties as well.  </p>
  
    <p>And when not currying favour with various provincial Liberal ministers, he was hosting their fundraising parties. He also testified he paid bribes to Gilles Vaillancourt, the long-serving mayor of the Montreal suburb of Laval. And he did it, he said, because fixing prices, paying off mobsters and making friends with politicians at various levels of government was the cost of being in the construction business in the province. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Listen, at the beginning it&rsquo;s a bit frustrating, but those are the rules,&rdquo; Zambito says today. &ldquo;You&rsquo;re not happy? Pack your bags and go work elsewhere. You have to say, &lsquo;Either I change business or I agree to do whatever I have to do.&rsquo; You don&rsquo;t have many choices.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>He then shrugs his massive shoulders and sips Pizzeria Etcetera&rsquo;s cappuccino. &ldquo;The industry is sick. You oblige people to do criminal acts to work. It&rsquo;s not like one guy in the industry does it. Everybody does it.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Everybody does it.&rdquo; Since the beginning of the hearings into the industry, it might be a sticker slogan plastered on Quebec&rsquo;s collective rear end&mdash;much to the horror of Quebecers themselves. Colloquially known as the Charbonneau commission, after France Charbonneau, the judge chairing it, these hearings have exposed deep, long-standing corruption within the construction industry. </p>
  
    <p>And as titillating as they may be, tales of cash-stuffed envelopes are hardly the biggest problem facing Quebec, as far as corruption is concerned. It goes deeper than that, permeating the levers of political and industrial power in the province. Quebec&rsquo;s protectionist labour laws, and insistence that all contracts be done in French, has effectively guaranteed an artificially small labour pool, along with limiting the number of construction companies able to bid on contracts.  </p>
  
    <p>Critics also say Quebec, through its laws and lack of oversight, has allowed large engineering consulting firms to wield incredible influence over both construction sites and political parties. All of this has contributed to the epic show of corruption and illicit party financing we are witnessing today. </p>
  
    <p>Of the province&rsquo;s 10 biggest engineering consulting firms, eight have been named during testimony. Four of them have had their offices raided by police in the last six weeks. The former president of SNC-Lavalin, by far the largest engineering firm in the province, was recently indicted on fraud and conspiracy charges. The development followed reports that the company paid $22.5 million to secure a contract to build McGill University&rsquo;s new hospital, though the claims have not been proven. </p>
  
    <p>Zambito lived through it all, from the grim-faced mobsters lording over Montreal to the virtual one-man government of Gilles Vaillancourt to the parallel, cash-only world of illicit political financing at the behest of these engineering consulting companies.  </p>
  
    <p>Today, lounging at one of his pizzeria&rsquo;s tables, Zambito seems as worried about his safety as he is about those pending charges. That is to say, not very. &ldquo;Yes, people thought I was going to get shot in the first couple of weeks, I admit,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;But I&rsquo;m not worried for myself. I did things correctly. I did what I had to do, I got caught, I gave my version of what happened with the goal that things will change in Quebec.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>He has told his story on the record, implicating everyone from mobsters to construction magnates to some of the most powerful political figures in the province. Far from cowering in fear of reprisals, Zambito has embraced his odd celebrity status, if not with gusto then at least with an obvious belief that he has done the right thing by admitting to his many wrongs as publicly as possible. </p>
  
    <p>Zambito&rsquo;s first construction contract was a long time coming. His father, Giuseppe, owned a construction company in Laval, and Zambito remembers being obsessed as a child with bulldozers, earth movers and other heavy machinery his father kept at his yards in Laval. In 1997, he cut short his law studies at the Universit&eacute; de Sherbrooke to join his father in running Infrabec, which specialized in civil engineering jobs. He began to look for contracts. </p>
  
    <p>It wasn&rsquo;t easy. &ldquo;We came to realize that Montreal was a closed market,&rdquo; Zambito testified in October. &ldquo;I submitted bids in Laval, and it was closed as well. I submitted bids on the north shore [the suburbs north of Laval] and it was a closed market. We quickly realized that not any company could go work wherever it felt like.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>He ended up bidding on a small contract in Montreal&mdash;a &ldquo;hermetically sealed&rdquo; market, as he called it. To gain a foothold, he bid purposefully low, and in April 2000 found himself at Montreal&rsquo;s historic Lantic Sugar refinery, replacing water pipes. </p>
  
    <p>Montreal&rsquo;s construction industry was insular long before Zambito, or even the Mafia, got involved. Through its labour and language laws, Quebec had both limited the number of companies able to bid on contracts and restricted the workforce putting shovels in the ground. </p>
  
    <p>Quebec&rsquo;s construction unions have the sole power to place workers on a given work site&mdash;a situation unique to the province. The construction union federations, of which FTQ-Construction is the largest, dictate which workers go to what sites. This, critics argue, gives the unions far too much power and allows for favouritism within the industry. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;It means that if you get a contract, you can&rsquo;t necessarily get the manpower to get the job done,&rdquo; says former Montreal police chief and anti-corruption squad head Jacques Duchesneau. &ldquo;I got a lot of emails from anglophones who went through this. Union representatives can make life miserable.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Language has been a barrier in other ways. In a 2010 report, Duchesneau singles out the fact that all contracts must be in French, for &ldquo;limiting competition and ensuring higher prices throughout the manufacturing, distribution and contracting chain.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Finally, there is the issue of the labour movement within Quebec. Simply put, it is difficult for anyone outside of Quebec to work in the province&mdash;this despite a housing boom in Montreal and its suburbs and massive development in the province&rsquo;s north. A 2009 labour mobility agreement between Ontario and Quebec was meant to assuage what both governments saw as a labour shortage in their respective provinces; the easy cross-border flow of labour envisioned has yet to materialize.  </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;There is a huge labour shortage in Quebec,&rdquo; says Luc Martin, vice-president of Corporation des entrepreneurs g&eacute;n&eacute;raux du Qu&eacute;bec, which represents the province&rsquo;s building contractors. &ldquo;But the unions say we have enough. They say we just have to pay overtime.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>It was into this uniquely fraught climate at the start of the last decade that Zambito began his education in the way business was done. </p>
  
    <p>Former city inspector Luc Leclerc, who admitted in testimony to pocketing kickbacks, remembers paying Zambito a visit not long after he&rsquo;d broken ground on his first Montreal contract in 2000.  </p>
  
    <p>During the meeting, over wine and cigars, Zambito became keenly aware he wasn&rsquo;t welcome on the island of Montreal when he was informed his &ldquo;friends&rdquo; in the industry weren&rsquo;t happy that he dared bid on contracts they felt were rightfully theirs. Bravado seems to drip from his every pore, though, so if Leclerc&rsquo;s friendly warning put him off, he didn&rsquo;t show it. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ll face the music when it&rsquo;s time to face the music,&rdquo; Zambito said to Leclerc. </p>
  
    <p>Having lowballed his way into an otherwise impenetrable market, Zambito says he suddenly found himself both beholden to and beneficiary of three well-established forces in the Montreal construction industry: corrupt city officials, the Italian Mafia and Union Montr&eacute;al, the party of G&eacute;rald Tremblay, who recently stepped down as mayor of Montreal. The first came in the form of Leclerc, as well as city engineer Gilles Surprenant. </p>
  
    <p>A friendly-looking fellow who sports a goatee and a perpetually bemused look, Surprenant testified that by 2000 he had practically made an art out of inflating the cost of city contracts; he became so good at it that by 2011 an outside auditor found that Montreal typically paid upwards of 30 per cent more for work on its sidewalks, water piping and sewage systems. The auditor dubbed it &ldquo;L&rsquo;effet Surprenant&rdquo;&mdash;literally, the surprising effect. </p>
  
    <p>Leclerc, meanwhile, took care of the &ldquo;fake extras.&rdquo; As the supervising engineer on many city projects, Leclerc was in charge of overseeing each contract&rsquo;s &ldquo;contingency fees,&rdquo; or payments for unforeseen work&mdash;and he worked diligently (and for a fee) to liberate them without any work being done. Zambito, Surprenant and Leclerc all testified that 2.5 per cent of each contract&rsquo;s value went to organized crime, another of Zambito&rsquo;s new realities once he entered Montreal&rsquo;s construction industry. </p>
  
    <p>The distribution centre for this cash-only business was Caf&eacute; Consenza, in a white-bricked strip mall. More church basement and less velvet-draped clubhouse of Mafia lore, Consenza was where Nicolo and Vito Rizzuto and company met to divvy up the cash kicked up to them by the various construction firms. In 2004 the RCMP installed cameras to tape the proceedings in Caf&eacute; Consenza&rsquo;s two back rooms. The results are a banal but sometimes enthralling narrative of how the Mafia&rsquo;s cash-harvesting operation works. </p>
  
    <p>For two years, the RCMP cameras recorded images of these 10-minute rituals, in which Nicolo Rizzuto Sr., Rizzuto associate Rocco Sollecito and Nicolo Milioto sort money pulled from a satchel into five piles&mdash;a reference, according to Montreal police organized-crime investigator Eric Vecchio, of the five heads of the contract-rigging network. The three in the room would laugh and gesticulate. And then they would take the stacks and tuck them into their socks. </p>
  
    <p>The contractors themselves would often stop by the caf&eacute; to drop off wads of cash&mdash;including Zambito, who in one video hovers in a black leather jacket, looking like he could be Jay Leno&rsquo;s brutish cousin. By that point, around 2004 and 2005, Zambito and nine other companies controlled who did what and at what price to the water, drainage and sewer pipes servicing the 1.8 million people living on the island of Montreal. </p>
  
    <p>Zambito also testified he met Quebec construction magnate Tony Accurso at a Laval restaurant in the early 2000s. The subject of the meeting was a $25-million contract Zambito was looking at, and which Accurso wanted. Vito Rizzuto mediated the disagreement. Zambito backed off the contract following the meeting. (Accurso denied the meeting happened.) </p>
  
    <p>The 61-year-old Accurso looms large over the industry; he and his children, Jimmy and Lisa, control 63 construction and real estate companies in the province, according to an anti-corruption squad analysis. Accurso, who didn&rsquo;t respond to an interview request, is currently facing multiple fraud, conspiracy, breach of trust and influence peddling charges. By the size of his operations alone, he is indispensable to the industry; according to a 2012 La Presse report, Accurso&rsquo;s companies receive upwards of 80 per cent of the public sector contracts in the province.  </p>
  
    <p>That domination is in large part due to FTQ-Construction, the province&rsquo;s biggest construction federation. </p>
  
    <p>Accurso was close with Louis Laberge, one of the FTQ&rsquo;s storied leaders, and the friendship proved fruitful: through Fonds FTQ, its financing and investment arm established in 1983, the FTQ invested heavily in Accurso&rsquo;s businesses in the early 1980s. It was a mutually beneficial relationship: Accurso&rsquo;s businesses grew exponentially, while the Fonds FTQ enjoyed a booming return on its investment. </p>
  
    <p>Yet there was an apparent conflict of interest in the relationship between the province&rsquo;s largest union organization and its largest construction magnate. Because it controls labour placement, the FTQ can favour the companies in which it has invested, if only to see its own rate of return rise. It&rsquo;s exactly what happened in Accurso&rsquo;s case, says Duchesneau. &ldquo;With the FTQ and Accurso, it wasn&rsquo;t just money, but manpower. The FTQ invested in him, and in order to get their return on investment, they made sure that Accurso got the manpower he needed.&rdquo; (FTQ spokesperson Patrick McQuilken didn&rsquo;t return an interview request.) </p>
  
    <p>By 2007, Zambito was cementing other relationships of his own. He regularly met with Nicolo Milioto, an intimidating bald man with big ears and dark eyes, to hand over his 2.5 per cent to the Mafia. Beginning in 2005, Milioto began extracting another three per cent for &ldquo;the political party of G&eacute;rald Tremblay,&rdquo; Zambito testified that Milioto told him. </p>
  
    <p>Tremblay vociferously denied Zambito&rsquo;s allegations&mdash;&ldquo;My conscience is at peace,&rdquo; he said during an ensuing press conference. Yet in the days following Zambito&rsquo;s testimony the commission heard from former Union Montr&eacute;al fundraiser Martin Dumont, who testified that he had to help the party&rsquo;s chief fundraiser Bernard Tr&eacute;panier, known as &ldquo;Mr. Three per cent,&rdquo; close a safe overflowing with cash. There is no evidence the cash was collected illegally, but Tremblay resigned a week later. </p>
  
    <p>Ditto Gilles Vaillancourt, who resigned in early November not long after Zambito said the Laval mayor pressed him into making a $25,000 contribution so Infrabec&rsquo;s contigency fees would be approved. Vaillancourt was quick to deny this&mdash;only to have police raid his safety deposit boxes nine days later. </p>
  
    <p>If Zambito found municipal contracts to be lucrative, they were nothing compared to the potential windfall that could be earned from the provincial government. Starting at around the same time of his first municipal job in 2000, he bid on his first contract with Transports Qu&eacute;bec, and was working regularly with the transport ministry by 2007, when Jean Charest&rsquo;s government launched a five-year, $16-billion plan to revamp the province&rsquo;s roadwork. </p>
  
    <p>By then Zambito was also working with some of Canada&rsquo;s most powerful engineering consulting firms and raising money for the Parti Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois and the now-defunct ADQ. The lion&rsquo;s share of his fundraising efforts, though, were for the Quebec Liberal party. It was in this line of work, Zambito figured out, where the real hustle was. </p>
  
    <p>Zambito&rsquo;s entrance into provincial government contracts meant spending a significant amount of time raising money for political parties at the behest of various large engineering consulting firms. &ldquo;It became redundant. One week we were seen at Liberal functions; the week after it was the ADQ; two weeks later it was the Parti Qu&eacute;b&eacute;cois. It was always the same business people who would attend,&rdquo; Zambito testified in October. </p>
  
    <p>These firms constantly asked Zambito for $3,000 cheques&mdash;the maximum political donation per person, according to Quebec electoral law. The firms, he said, would pay him back by granting &ldquo;false extras&rdquo; on the contracts he received from them. Zambito wrote cheques in the name of his employees and his parents. Even his wife&mdash;who was &ldquo;beyond apolitical,&rdquo; Zambito says&mdash;became a loyal donor to the Quebec Liberal party. </p>
  
    <p>As with corporate donations, the practice of &ldquo;pr&ecirc;te-noms,&rdquo; or writing a cheque to a political party in someone else&rsquo;s name, is forbidden under Quebec electoral law. Yet witnesses appearing at the commission, Zambito included, have named eight of the 10 largest <em>g&eacute;nie-conseil</em> firms in connection with allegedly nefarious campaign financing charges. </p>
  
    <p>These engineering firms have essentially taken over the planning and management of the province&rsquo;s road construction work. And yet, in most cases, they don&rsquo;t compete with each other for government contracts&mdash;not in the usual sense, anyway. That&rsquo;s because the laws in Quebec were such that a company&rsquo;s reputation and experience were weighed when awarding contracts; price was a lesser concern. By 2008, price considerations were stripped out altogether, to remove the urge to cut corners. But over time critics say this transformed the bidding process into a pure lobbying exercise. &ldquo;What&rsquo;s the message that you give to those firms who are all good at their jobs?&rdquo; asks Luc Martin of the Corporation des entrepreneurs g&eacute;n&eacute;raux du Qu&eacute;bec. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s no surprise they are close to government, because they have to lobby it.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Which is why Zambito&rsquo;s testimony about his party financing activities alarmed observers. Over several days he named a number of high-level Liberal ministers and party members as being recipients of his largesse. He testified that he helped organize fundraisers for Nathalie Normandeau, then Quebec&rsquo;s deputy premier, at the behest of Genivar, an engineering consulting firm, and for former labour minister David Whissell, on behalf of BPR, another firm. Meanwhile, he testified he gave $30,000 to a fundraising event in the spring of 2009 for senior minister Line Beauchamp, well in excess of the legal donation limit. </p>
  
    <p>As for Normandeau, Zambito testified he sent her 40 roses for her 40th birthday. &ldquo;Dear Lino, it is with pleasure that I received your magnificent flowers for my birthday,&rdquo; she wrote in a note. &ldquo;You have helped make this day ever more beautiful.&rdquo; Zambito would soon follow up with nine tickets to a C&eacute;line Dion concert. Normandeau, Whissell and Beauchamp have all denied any wrongdoing, while the two firms, Genivar and BPR, refused to comment to <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em>. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;I fixed contracts, I financed political parties, I corrupted bureaucrats,&rdquo; Zambito told the commission. &ldquo;But the system is such that if I wanted to work in Laval, Montreal, on the north shore or for the ministry, I didn&rsquo;t have a choice in the matter.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>In October 2009, the Radio-Canada investigative program <em>Enqu&ecirc;te</em> broadcast a piece on Zambito&rsquo;s attempts to influence the municipal election in Boisbriand, where he&rsquo;d landed several contracts. Zambito&rsquo;s career as a fraudster, fundraiser and political hanger-on had come to an end. </p>
  
    <p>Undoubtedly, the noise emerging from the commission has hurt Quebec&rsquo;s already-damaged reputation. &ldquo;There is something rotten in the Kingdom of Quebec,&rdquo; wrote a <em>Le Devoir</em> columnist. Some turned to satire. Comedian Guy Nantel&rsquo;s next show, entitled <em>Corrompu</em> (Corrupted), will make light of its misery next summer. Judge Charbonneau will have tabled her recommendations by the end of <em>Corrompu</em>&rsquo;s run, in fall 2013. </p>
  
    <p>There are other rays of sunshine. For all this misery, Montreal (and Quebec in general) has weathered the economic crisis better than most of North America. The city&rsquo;s real estate market is doing quite well, thanks in part to a condo boom in the last five years. Last year, the Liberal government tabled legislation ending the practice of union labour placement. The PQ, despite its ties to the labour movement, has warily accepted the law. </p>
  
    <p>And there&rsquo;s precedent. &ldquo;New York and Chicago had problems with corruption, too. Not to say they don&rsquo;t anymore, but it was dramatically reduced by commissions like the one we are having,&rdquo; says Michel Leblanc, president of Montreal&rsquo;s chamber of commerce. &ldquo;If the government implements Charbonneau&rsquo;s recommendations, then new systems will be in place to get rid of corruption.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>And Zambito? When he isn&rsquo;t posing with fans or getting propositioned by married women&mdash;he&rsquo;s become quite popular since testifying&mdash;the man who exposed the rot in Quebec&rsquo;s construction industry spends his time running the restaurant. He wasn&rsquo;t entirely saddened when Infrabec went bankrupt in 2011. &ldquo;The restaurant&rsquo;s a different ball game,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;People are out to enjoy, to pass an evening with their family. Every client is your boss.&rdquo; An added bonus: these bosses don&rsquo;t expect bribes. </p>
  
  
  
  
  
 
    <p><em>Called out </em></p>
    <p>Of the 10 largest engineering firms in  Quebec, eight have been named in  testimony at the Charbonneau commission related to political financing irregularities</p>
    
    
    <em>Company	Employees in Quebec </em>
    <p>SNC-Lavalin	5,200  </p>
  
    <p>Dessau	3,729  </p>
  
    <p>BPR	2,200  </p>
  
    <p>Cima+	2,100  </p>
  
    <p>Genivar	2,000  </p>
  
    <p>Aecom	1,500 </p>
  
    <p>Groupe S.M. International	1,500 </p>
  
    <p>Roche	1,435 </p>
  

 <p>Facing accusations</p>
 
 <p>Testimony from Zambito and others has ended two political careers and shone a light on those caught up in the scandal</p>
  

<p>Ex-Mayors</p>
  
  <p><em>G&eacute;rald Tremblay</em> Former mayor of Montreal dodged allegations for years</p>
  
  <p><em>Gilles Vaillancourt</em> Former mayor of Laval reigned for 23 years</p>
  
 
  <p>Money Dispensers</p>
  
  <p><em>Nick Rizzuto Sr., Rocco Sollecito, Nicolo Milioto</em> These three men&mdash;alleged associates of the Rizzuto crime family&mdash;were caught on tape together stuffing cash in their socks</p>
  
  <p>Implicated City Engineers</p>
  
  <p><em>Luc Leclerc</em> Admitted taking more than $500,000 in kickbacks</p>
  
  <p><em>Gilles Surprenant</em> Estimated to have taken more than $700,000</p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>National</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>New Brunswick</slug>
  
   <hedline>Talking turkey</hedline>
  
    <abstract>Hunters want to import hundreds of wild turkeys  to shoot. Farmers aren&rsquo;t nearly as keen.</abstract>
  
  <byline>Karen Pinchin</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_TURKEYS01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Big bird: In the U.S., turkey hunting is a lucrative business </photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Jeff McIntosh/CP</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>With extraordinary eyesight, strength beyond their size and uncanny survival skills, wild turkeys are a favourite target for sportsmen. In New Brunswick, where the birds are increasingly showing up in fields and at backyard bird feeders, hunters have been lobbying the provincial government for decades to institute a legal wild-turkey hunt, and allow more birds to be brought in to boost the population. Now, despite trepidation from some farmers and naturalists who fear what could happen if the birds&rsquo; numbers explode, it appears the government is ready to act. </p>
  
    <p>Rob Wilson, president of the local chapter of the Canadian Wild Turkey Federation, says his group hopes for an announcement within weeks. As a hunter who usually heads to the U.S. to bag his yearly bird, he&rsquo;s excited at the prospect of finally being able to hunt at home. &ldquo;They&rsquo;re very challenging: not as easy as a white-tailed deer or moose,&rdquo; says Wilson, who helped lead a volunteer-funded environmental assessment that was delivered to the government earlier this year.  </p>
  
    <p>Hunting the bird is currently legal in six provinces and 49 states. Bruce Northrup, New Brunswick&rsquo;s natural resources minister, tagged along on a spring hunt in Maine to see what it entailed. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m not a hunter,&rdquo; he says, describing a chilly morning wake-up for a dawn hunt. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re really trying to do our homework on this.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>If given the go-ahead, Wilson and others will travel to Ontario this winter, where they plan to use air-powered net cannons to trap 200 of the province&rsquo;s estimated 70,000 wild turkeys. The birds will be tested for diseases, put in crates and shipped east to be released. They plan to repeat the process every winter for four years, aiming to more than double the existing population from 600 to 1,400, not including any natural increase. A biologist with the turkey federation estimates New Brunswick could support 10,000 birds. </p>
  
    <p>One reason the province is considering a hunt is the money. Maine started its own program with 40 stocked birds in 1977 and now has roughly 60,000, says Northrup. Each year the hunt generates millions of dollars in spinoff revenue for the state. For every New Brunswick hunter who heads south to bag a bird, that&rsquo;s money the province loses. </p>
  
    <p>Yet many farmers are horrified at the idea of importing more of the birds, because wild turkeys are known for their voracious appetites. In Ontario, for instance, the birds are regularly blamed for devastating crops. With more than 300 wild blueberry farms in New Brunswick, there&rsquo;s a lot at stake. </p>
  
    <p>Another concern is how the birds might hurt other animal populations, such as grouse. </p>
  
    <p>Wilson acknowledges the concerns, but says turkeys are often blamed for damage caused by other animals. As for fears the population will get out of hand, Rod Currie of the New Brunswick Wildlife Federation, a fish- and game-hunting group, isn&rsquo;t worried. &ldquo;If you have 20-lb. turkeys wandering around, and a number of sportsmen looking for something for the Thanksgiving table, those problems sort themselves out.&rdquo;  </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>National</sections>
  
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>British Columbia</slug>
  
   <hedline>Nursing a grudge against flu shots</hedline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_NATNOTE01.jpg"></photo>
  
  
  
  <body.content>
  
  <p>British Columbia&rsquo;s front-line health professionals must either get the flu shot this year or wear a surgical mask in patient areas. Except it&rsquo;s okay if they don&rsquo;t. Such is the confusion in B.C. hospitals and clinics after the ministry of health watered down its controversial policy of mandatory flu shots for health workers who deal with patients.  </p>
  
    <p>The province originally announced the policy in August to combat low vaccine coverage among health workers. At the time, B.C.&rsquo;s chief medical officer, Dr. Perry Kendall, said it would protect patients from contracting influenza, which causes more deaths than any other vaccine-preventable disease. An editorial in the <em>Canadian Medical Association Journal</em> praised the move, but B.C.&rsquo;s major health unions fought it, arguing it infringed on worker&rsquo;s rights and liberties. </p>
  
    <p>On Dec. 4, the health ministry suspended the enforcement of the new policy for one year. That&rsquo;s left &ldquo;considerable confusion,&rdquo; says Bonnie Pearson of the Hospital Employees Union, which helped negotiate the temporary compromise. Some employers are still telling workers to wear a special badge if they don&rsquo;t get the shot, even though that part of the policy has been suspended, she says. Pearson argues a mandatory policy can have the opposite effect: &ldquo;It&rsquo;s that kind of a perverse &lsquo;I&rsquo;m not going to do it because you tell me I have to&rsquo; argument,&rdquo; she says. </p>
  
    <p>There&rsquo;s been an upside to the controversy: more workers now get immunized than before. In the Fraser Health region, 70 per cent of full-time health professionals got a flu shot this season, compared to the typical 35 to 45 per cent. Province-wide, the figure is 60 per cent, suggesting a flu shot boom among health workers. Other provinces considering similar rules for their doctors and nurses are no doubt taking note.</p>
    
     <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
  
  
  
  
    <hedline>Capital Diary</hedline>
    
    <abstract>Mitchel Raphael on Lisa Raitt&rsquo;s &lsquo;Miserables&rsquo; Christmas</abstract>
    
    <p>What Raitt expects under the tree </p>
  
    <p>On Dec. 25 expect to find Labour Minister Lisa Raitt in the movie theatre watching Les Mis&eacute;rables. She is a huge fan, having seen the musical twice in London and twice in Toronto. The song I Dreamed a Dream, she confessed, makes her cry every time&mdash;but only in the context of the play. That means no tears were shed for Susan Boyle, the underdog who sang it famously on Britain&rsquo;s Got Talent. Raitt has told her partner Bruce Wood that advance Les Mis&eacute;rables movie tickets &ldquo;better be under the Christmas tree.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>Someone is posing </p>
  
    <p>It was a rare moment of cross-partisanship on the Hill, with politicians from opposite sides coming together for a photo op. But there&rsquo;s no shared version of events as to how that photo came about. Liberal leadership candidate<em> Justin Trudeau</em> told Capital Diary that Tory MP <em>Eve Adams</em> was hosting a group of visitors, including one from her home city of Mississauga, Ont., and asked him if he would pose for a picture with them. They went to the House foyer for better lighting. Adams, however, says it was Trudeau who asked her group if they wanted a picture, though she did join in for the snap. Trudeau says opposition MPs asking him to pose with people, even constituents, &ldquo;happens all the time.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>Senate reform, at last </p>
  
    <p>The internal Senate TV channel&mdash;which only provides live audio, not visuals from the Red Chamber&mdash;used to just have a red screen that had the date with a note that the Senate was sitting. Now it actually says who is talking, with a caption on what they are talking about, and has rotating still images of Senate scenes. Liberal Senate staffer Christian Dicks says it&rsquo;s made it much easier to follow. Before, if you didn&rsquo;t catch the name of who was talking, you had to listen carefully and guess at who was speaking and the context. </p>
  
    <p>Liberal party crasher </p>
  
    <p>The Liberal Christmas party had some disgruntled staffers upset over the price of bottles of wine for a table. So upset, in fact, that some of them looked up the options online and snuck in the same bottles into the packed event. The least expensive wine was $51; they snuck in an LCBO version for $8.98. A surprise guest at the Liberal holiday bash was Bruce Hyer, who left the NDP in April 2012, and currently sits as an Independent. Liberal leadership candidate Joyce Murray said Hyer was her date for the night. Other Liberal leadership candidates included Martha Hall Findlay, whose table was furthest from the stage, but on the upside was close to one of the bars. At the beginning of the night Howard Liebman, aide to Liberal MP Irwin Cotler, came to the event carrying around a large box filled with holiday cards his boss still had to sign.  </p>
  
    <p>Liberal horsing around </p>
  
    <p>During the recent voting marathon, Liberal MP Mark Eyking got an emergency video sent to his BlackBerry. His wife Pam Eyking wanted to show him that their 10-year-old mare named Wonder had gotten past a fence on their farm and was now eating the grass on their front lawn. Milder weather meant the grass had grown longer. Eyking told his wife to just let the horse be. &ldquo;Now I don&rsquo;t have to go home and mow the lawn,&rdquo; he quipped to Capital Diary. </p>
  
    <p>MP has her sister&rsquo;s back </p>
  
    <p>This Christmas holiday, Ontario Conservative MP Kellie Leitch is off to Edmonton. Her sister is pregnant and she wants to be by her side. If the birth goes smoothly, she will be in the waiting room. If her sister needs a C-section, Leitch plans on being in the operating room, since she is also a surgeon. She says being in the room is okay as long as she is not the primary doctor doing the procedure.</p>
 
 
      <em>On the Web: Visit Mitchel Raphael&rsquo;s blog at macleans.ca/mitchelraphael</em>



  
   <slug>Manitoba</slug>
   
   <hedline>The signs  all say  cash cow</hedline>


    <p>In the past, when residents complained billboards were a blight on the urban landscape, politicians might have responded by banning them. Now cash-strapped cities view them as an untapped source of tax revenue. </p>
  
    <p>Winnipeg city council recently debated a plan to hike taxes on billboards by as much as 380 per cent. Taxes on animated digital boards would have increased from $1,000 a year to $23,000. Last week, the city postponed the decision until next year following an outcry from the industry, which argues billboards aren&rsquo;t quite the cash cow councillors believe. </p>
  
    <p>Still, it appears to be a losing battle. Last month the Supreme Court of Canada refused to hear an appeal by the outdoor advertising industry to strike down Toronto&rsquo;s 2009 billboard tax. The industry had argued it is an indirect tax not permitted under the City of Toronto Act. The city estimates it will bring in more than $10 million a year in added revenue, which the industry contends would be more than the pro&#64257;ts of the billboards themselves.  </p>
  
    <p>South of the border, cities are also eyeing billboard taxes as an alternative to property tax hikes. Baltimore councillors have called for a tax, complaining that Clear Channel, the &ldquo;multi-billion-dollar conglomerate&rdquo; that owns most of the city&rsquo;s billboards, boosted profits despite the recession. Last month, Pittsburgh unanimously approved a 10 per cent tax on billboard revenue, even as a state senator warned it could infringe on the right to free speech. </p>
  
    <p>So far just six jurisdictions in North America have imposed such a tax. But given the amount of money at stake, it won&rsquo;t be long before those roadside ads start looking less like annoying distractions and more like dollar signs.</p>
    
    <byline>Tamsin McMahon</byline>
  
  
  </body.content>
  
   
  
  
  
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>International</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Mali</slug>
  
   <hedline>Al-Qaeda rising </hedline>
  
    <abstract>Islamist terrorists spread chaos and  fear in Africa while  the West dithers</abstract>
  
        <byline>Michael Petrou</byline>

  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_AL_QAEDA78.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Resurgent insurgents: Mali, Niger, Algeria and Mauritania all face al-Qaeda threats</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Luis De Vega/POLARIS</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
    <p>When Robert Fowler, who spent 130 days as an al-Qaeda hostage in the Sahara Desert, is asked how he&rsquo;s doing, he often says he&rsquo;s doing fine, then adds: &ldquo;So are my former captors.&rdquo; In December 2008, Fowler, then the UN Secretary General&rsquo;s special envoy for Niger, was kidnapped along with his colleague, Louis Guay, in Niger and spirited to northern Mali. The two Canadian diplomats lived in punishing conditions and under the threat of execution for more than four months, until their freedom was negotiated&mdash;in exchange, it seems, for a ransom and the release of al-Qaeda terror suspects.  </p>
  
    <p>Fowler is now safely back in the embrace of his family in Ottawa, and he sometimes has the bizarre experience of watching YouTube videos of Omar, one of the men who kidnapped him, brandishing a Kalashnikov and issuing hyperbolic threats against France, the United States and all the countries in NATO.  </p>
  
    <p>Omar has a lot to gloat about these days. Al-Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb (AQIM), along with affiliated Islamist groups, controls the northern two-thirds of Mali, an area roughly the size of France. Their territory consists mostly of desert, but also contains several cities, including fabled Timbuktu, whose ancient Muslim shrines and monuments al-Qaeda has destroyed because of the supposed affront they present to its rigid interpretation of Islam. While American drone strikes have decimated al-Qaeda&rsquo;s leadership in Pakistan, it is comparatively unmolested, and flourishing, in Africa.  </p>
  
    <p>The group has been in the region for years, operating in ungoverned swaths of the Sahara and the Sahel deserts. It grew out of the Algerian Salafist Group for Preaching and Combat, which formally joined forces with al-Qaeda in 2006 and changed its name to al-Qaeda in the Islamic Maghreb the following year. It carried out numerous attacks, mostly against Algerian targets, and swelled its coffers with the proceeds of drug smuggling and kidnapping.  </p>
  
    <p>Al-Qaeda&rsquo;s fortunes then rose with the war in Libya and the weaponry that flowed out of the country when Moammar Gadhafi&rsquo;s regime collapsed last summer. Hundreds of nomadic Malian Tuaregs had fought for the Libyan dictator and fled home when he was beaten. Ever adaptable, al-Qaeda formed a temporary alliance with the Tuaregs, separatists who were waging their own rebellion against the Malian government. Mali&rsquo;s weak and underfunded military couldn&rsquo;t beat them. The military mutinied and then launched a coup. Al-Qaeda surged into the vacuum, turned against the Tuaregs, and took over most of the country.  </p>
  
    <p>AQIM has long had links with other Islamist extremists in the African Sahel. One of Fowler&rsquo;s captors was from Kano, Nigeria. Lately there have been reports that some 300 members of the Nigerian Islamist group Boko Haram have been trained in the AQIM-controlled Malian town of Gao. Boko Haram has killed hundreds in Nigeria, including in several Christian church bombings. According to Gen. Carter Ham, head of the U.S. military&rsquo;s Africa Command, AQIM also co-operates with al-Shabaab, an al-Qaeda affiliate in Somalia, extending the group&rsquo;s potential reach across the continent.  </p>
  
    <p>All this is rattling governments in the region and in the West. There are sputtering plans for a UN-backed West African intervention force, likely supported by Western nations. France has reportedly sent surveillance drones to Mali already. Canada says it is not contemplating a military mission but &ldquo;stands ready with its international partners&rdquo; to assist in resolving the crisis.  </p>
  
    <p>The fear in Western capitals is that AQIM poses a global threat. While its primary target remains the Algerian government, its ambitions appear broader. It has been blamed for the September attack on the U.S. consulate in Benghazi, Libya, that killed U.S. Ambassador J. Christopher Stevens and three other Americans.  </p>
  
    <p>Omar repeatedly told Fowler the group despises the UN&mdash;which was already evident given its 2007 attack on the UN headquarters in Algiers that killed 37. In a recent Internet video, Omar vowed to raise the flag of Islam from where the sun rises to where it sets. </p>
  
    <p>Fowler, who says he would &ldquo;love to see Canada being part&rdquo; of an intervention in Mali, argues there are other reasons to challenge al-Qaeda&rsquo;s gains there. &ldquo;We have an awful lot to protect. In the last few years we&rsquo;ve had an aid program in excess of $100 million.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;If AQIM and their clones succeed in their vision,&rdquo; adds Fowler, &ldquo;it&rsquo;s going to create a humanitarian crisis of the likes we haven&rsquo;t seen before across the widest part of Africa. Can anybody pretend that Canada, along with other rich countries in the world, wouldn&rsquo;t have to deal with such a humanitarian crisis? So it probably makes sense not to have it.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>There is substantial support for intervention among Malians. Hundreds of thousands have fled the north, and poorly organized and armed civilian militias are pledging to go on the offensive against al-Qaeda themselves. &ldquo;They have extremely little support from the local population,&rdquo; says Corrine Dufka, senior researcher at the Africa division of Human Rights Watch, who recently returned from Mali. &ldquo;Life is miserable for people in the north. As if the humanitarian difficulties and challenges weren&rsquo;t enough, they also have to tolerate this extremely abusive behaviour being meted out by the Islamists, who have, in the words of many of my witnesses, taken all the joie de vivre out of life.&rdquo; They have also engaged in a campaign of floggings, amputations and murder. This summer, two alleged adulterers were forced into holes with just their heads protruding, and were stoned to death.  </p>
  
    <p>Sufism, a moderate strain of Islam, has deep roots in Mali, making many Malians unreceptive to the fundamentalist and unbending interpretation of their faith propagated by al-Qaeda. &ldquo;Most Malians certainly think of it as foreign, both the ideology and the fighters and operatives,&rdquo; says Gregory Mann, an associate professor of history at Columbia University, speaking about AQIM. &ldquo;They see them as criminals, as armed bandits. They want to see them chased out. They want to see them gone.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>But tackling al-Qaeda in northern Mali would not be easy. No Western nation wants its soldiers doing the actual fighting on the ground. Malian soldiers are not up to the job. And the country&rsquo;s post-coup government&mdash;led by interim president Dioncounda Traor&eacute;, who has not yet faced voters&mdash;is weak and fragile. Prime Minister Cheikh Modibo Diarra resigned this week, hours after he was forcibly detained by Malian soldiers&mdash;underlying the military&rsquo;s ongoing control of the country, despite formally handing over power to a civilian government.  </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;You can&rsquo;t rebuild a military unless you give it a government that it&rsquo;s willing to fight and die for, and nobody&rsquo;s going to fight and die for the sad lot that&rsquo;s sitting in Bamako right now,&rdquo; says J. Peter Pham, director of the Africa Program at the Atlantic Council.  </p>
  
    <p>The Economic Community of West Africa States (ECOWAS) has proposed sending a force of 3,300 soldiers to Mali. Pham is skeptical about what they might accomplish.  </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;The idea that 3,300 troops are going to go into the desert and dislodge heavily armed Islamists who&rsquo;ve had time to dig themselves in, who are from the area, know every nook and cranny, is a sick joke. And the joke unfortunately is on the 3,300 who would be swallowed whole by the desert. So ECOWAS squawks a great deal about wanting action, but the numbers they&rsquo;re offering don&rsquo;t add up to a credible operation,&rdquo; says Pham.  </p>
  
    <p>To have much hope against al-Qaeda, any African intervention force will need significant Western help, something everyone involved would prefer to limit to low-profile assistance in areas like intelligence, training, logistics, and maybe air power.  </p>
  
    <p>Even then, the mission&rsquo;s goals would be less than the complete elimination of al-Qaeda from Mali. Afghanistan and Iraq have shrunk the ambitions of Western nations intervening in predominantly Muslim ones.  </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Seriously degraded would be good enough,&rdquo; says Fowler. &ldquo;And then Malians could be trained and equipped well enough to keep them at bay. We&rsquo;re not talking about total victory or unconditional surrender.&rdquo;  </p>
  
  
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>International</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Canada-U.S. Relations</slug>
  
   <hedline>Fighting cybercrime </hedline>
  
    <abstract>As the U.S. attempts to bolster its cybersecurity legislation, will Canada be called on to take part? </abstract>
  
  <byline>Luiza Ch. Savage</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_CYBERWAR01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Prevention: Is a &lsquo;cyberNORAD&rsquo; needed to protect North America&rsquo;s intertwined infrastructure? </photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Carolyn Kaster/AP</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>The revelation that Iranian nuclear centrifuges were sabotaged by the computer worm Stuxnet&mdash;reportedly a covert U.S.-Israeli intelligence operation&mdash;is unnerving Western security policy-makers who say it is only a matter of time before cyberwar is turned against North America. Will hackers shut down the electrical grid, sending millions into darkness? Could a foreign agent remotely sabotage a pipeline carrying natural gas or crude oil, causing an environmental disaster?  </p>
  
    <p>American lawmakers want to encourage U.S. government agencies to share intelligence about potential threats with private sector companies (who own and operate most of America&rsquo;s critical infrastructure), and to compel these firms to be more forthcoming about their own vulnerabilities. The issues are complicated: government regulations could prove onerous and costly, and could become quickly obsolete. Companies worry that identifying vulnerabilities could lead to legal liability and higher insurance costs. Civil libertarians also worry that allowing government greater leeway to monitor Internet traffic in search of malicious software could lead to privacy violations. Earlier this year Republicans blocked proposed legislation in the Senate that would have created merely voluntary standards (House Republicans are now talking about drafting their own bill next year, but plans remain vague). Meanwhile, there is speculation that President Barack Obama will weigh in with an executive order this month, in an attempt to fill the void left by congressional paralysis.  </p>
  
    <p>But as Americans struggle to work out a plan for their cyberdefence, a former Homeland Security official is urging that the effort include Canada, arguing that the critical infrastructure of both countries is so intertwined that a &ldquo;cyberNORAD&rdquo; (the North American Aerospace Defense Command) is needed to protect it. &ldquo;There is no border in cyberland,&rdquo; says Paul Rosenzweig, a deputy secretary for policy in the Department of Homeland security in the administration of George W. Bush. &ldquo;It makes almost no sense for U.S. government efforts not to include Canada.&rdquo; Rosenzweig, who heads a security consulting firm, Red Branch Law and Consulting, recently presented his ideas at the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, a think tank in Washington, and plans to publish them in a forthcoming issue of the <em>Canada-United States Law Journal</em>.  </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Whatever form U.S. cybersecurity efforts take, they won&rsquo;t be effective without Canadian co-operation,&rdquo; Rosenzweig told the Washington audience. &ldquo;There is no value in developing intrusive cybersecurity standards and putting industry to the expense if the same is not true for Canada. The reality is, Canada and the U.S. have to go down the same road.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Consider the electrical grid. The great Northeast blackout of 2003 demonstrated its interconnectedness: blackouts began in Ohio, rolled into Pennsylvania, then into Ontario, and back across the border into Michigan. Other examples of intertwined infrastructure include water, oil and gas pipelines, the rail network, linked stock exchanges, and the Internet itself.  </p>
  
    <p>Prime Minister Stephen Harper and President Obama devoted a section of their 2011 &ldquo;Beyond the Border&rdquo; bilateral agreement on border management to cybersecurity. But the vague statements simply addressed joint briefings, not deep information-sharing. &ldquo;Pablum,&rdquo; says Rosenzweig, grading the effort a &ldquo;D-.&rdquo; He argues that the leaders should begin by ordering up a joint assessment of cyberrisks to critical infrastructure, as well as a comparison of the respective legal authorities for assessing and managing the risks. </p>
  
    <p>The two militaries already work together on cybersecurity. But new co-operation could go as far as a joint cyberinformation sharing centre, or even common standards for industry. But many sensitive questions arise: what offensive and defensive steps should law enforcement take to protect networks? What should be the role of military in defending civilian networks? Proposals such as mass-sifting of emails in search of malware &ldquo;would raise even more hackles in Canada,&rdquo; he predicts, where various attempts at cross-border information sharing have repeatedly collided with Canadian privacy concerns. And then there is the financial cost.  </p>
  
    <p>But Rosenzweig points to the success of NORAD, in which Canadians and Americans sit in the same room, share a common operations system, and use joint forces for air and space defence. &ldquo;The authority is unified completely because our airspace is seamless. The missile coming to hit U.S. would come over Canada,&rdquo; says Rosenzweig. &ldquo;That is a good metaphor for cyberspace.&rdquo;     </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Letter from Europe</slug>
  
   <hedline>Hugh to  the rescue </hedline>
  
    <abstract>The romcom star is  now a crusader  for regulation of Britain&rsquo;s rowdy press</abstract>
  
      <byline>Leah McLaren</byline>

  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_EUROPE01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Hugh Grant: Pitting himself against the press</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Andrew Winning/Reuters</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>During the months of political caterwauling and public outrage over the U.K.&rsquo;s phone-hacking affair&mdash;in which reporters intercepted the cellphone calls and voicemails of celebrities, politicians and even a missing girl&mdash;and its buttoned-down cousin, the Leveson inquiry, which looked into the scandal, a dazzling new activist has stepped onto the public stage. His name is Hugh Grant and he wants you to know that just because he&rsquo;s taken up a cause, he&rsquo;s not political. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m often asked why I keep banging on about the press,&rdquo; he said in a recent article for <em>The Spectator</em>. &ldquo;Am I a lefty? I&rsquo;m not. I&rsquo;m not a righty, either. I drift.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Indeed, the film star&rsquo;s involvement is more personal. He wants press regulation and he wants it now. Like most British celebrities, he has been repeatedly doorstepped and harassed by the tabloid press. (Last fall, the mother of his child, Tinglan Hong, was forced to take out an injunction against paparazzi after she and Grant&rsquo;s baby were reportedly besieged by photographers and phone calls at home.) But unlike most celebrities, Grant is willing to exert the entire force of his charisma and fame to get it. He&rsquo;s done so, not just by testifying at the Leveson inquiry, as many other celebrities did&mdash;singer Charlotte Church, actors Sienna Miller, Jude Law and Steve Coogan, to name a few&mdash;but by attending party conferences and going on TV and radio. He&rsquo;s also written editorials for whomever will publish him on the subject about which he is suddenly so passionate: the need for British media to &ldquo;put right its past wrongs&rdquo; by submitting to regulation by an independent body underpinned by government authority. </p>
  
    <p>This last issue has become the sticking point in a debate currently raging in the U.K. Parliament, where a draft bill on the matter is now under way. The 2,000-page Leveson report, released last month, recommends the creation of such a body to govern press standards in the U.K. Among its powers would be setting fines and mandating more prominent apologies or corrections. </p>
  
    <p>The same day the report was released, Prime Minister David Cameron stood up in the Commons to say he was &ldquo;not convinced&rdquo; that statutory regulation was necessary. </p>
  
    <p>The media, on virtually all sides, agreed with him. The opposition, equally predictably, did not.  </p>
  
    <p>Editors of Britain&rsquo;s major newspapers banded together last week in the hope of launching a reformed media watchdog without statutory underpinning&mdash;but the opposition Labour Party  is expected to produce a draft bill shortly that sets out a plan for just the opposite. The opposition is supported by the watchdog group Hacked Off, which has submitted a petition for statutory regulation with more than 143,000 signatories, including authors J.K. Rowling and Salman Rushdie. </p>
  
    <p>But their loudest and most convincing spokesman is the romantic-comedy actor best known for his floppy haircut and posh stutter. </p>
  
    <p>Grant appeared for the second time in several weeks on the BBC&rsquo;s flagship Sunday TV news program, <em>The</em> <em>Andrew Marr Show</em>, to make the point that, after seven inquiries in 70 years, the British press should no longer &ldquo;be allowed to mark its own homework.&rdquo; His crusade, he insists, is not on behalf of the rich and famous, but of people such as the parents of murdered teen Milly Dowler, whom he terms &ldquo;the real, non-celebrity victims of phone hacking.&rdquo; To this extent, he casts himself as a reluctant spokesman. &ldquo;It certainly isn&rsquo;t a craving for attention,&rdquo; he said in a speech to the Tory Reform Group of his new line of work. &ldquo;I trudge on to <em>Newsnight</em> or <em>Question Time,</em> like Saddam to the scaffold. We beg them to use our professors or our lawyers, but they won&rsquo;t.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Grant has even produced and presented a 60-minute documentary, <em>Taking on the Tabloids,</em> for Channel 4, which aired to disappointing ratings. (It lost out to a docu-soap about a moving company, called <em>The Removal Men</em>, proving that even Grant&rsquo;s box-office appeal isn&rsquo;t enough to get the public excited about the never-ending debate on press regulation.) </p>
  
    <p>Pitting himself against the press is a risky position to take. His fight&mdash;which Grant won&rsquo;t win unless Cameron changes his position&mdash;is an uphill battle, and while his view is still favoured by the British public (a recent YouGov poll found 60 per cent support for the idea of statutory regulation), his popularity with the powerful right-wing press is currently less than zero. Rupert Murdoch has called him a &ldquo;scumbag.&rdquo; Grant replied in<em> The Spectator</em>: &ldquo;Harsh, but I see where he&rsquo;s coming from.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>The feeling does appear to be mutual. When Grant allowed himself to be profiled for the <em>Guardian</em> magazine early this year, it was only the third interview he&rsquo;d given a British news publication in 16 years. He was, by the interviewer&rsquo;s description, deeply on edge, though on the subject of Leveson, he perked up: &ldquo;I love getting into a taxi and saying &lsquo;House of Lords&rsquo; instead of &lsquo;Soho&rsquo;&mdash;again.&rdquo; Don&rsquo;t let the jocularity fool you. Grant is deadly serious about his new-found cause. On <em>The Andrew Marr Show</em> this weekend, he recounted the story of reading the Leveson report in a locked room along with other victims of phone hacking, such as the parents of murdered and missing children Milly Dowler and Madeleine McCann. Later, as they watched the prime minister&rsquo;s speech in the Commons, Grant said, &ldquo;The feeling was one of astonishment and betrayal.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>These days, Grant looks tired and haunted, with dark bags under his glittering blue eyes. Asked on a news program about the specifics of the draft bill, he sighed and almost reluctantly summoned his self-deprecating wit and deft comic timing: &ldquo;When it comes to the intricacies of drafting legislation,&rdquo; he said, &ldquo;please remember you are now talking to a romantic-comedy actor.&rdquo;</p>
  
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>International</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Mozambique</slug>
  
  <hedline>Sorghum suds</hedline>
 
  </body.head>
  

  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_WORLDNOTES01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Healthy alternative: Impala beer, made from cassava, is aimed at drinkers of illegal alcohol</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Johannes Myburgh/AFP/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
  
  
  
    <p>The era of home brew in Africa may be coming to an end. SABMiller, the world&rsquo;s second-largest brewer, is wooing the continent&rsquo;s illegal drinkers with dirt-cheap beer. In Mozambique, the brewer has released Impala, a beer made from cassava, the milky root used to make tapioca. At 70 cents a bottle, Impala is significantly cheaper than its malty cousins, priced at a dollar, making it affordable for the country&rsquo;s rising middle class. </p>
  
    <p>Zsuzsa Szilagyi, an alcohol analyst for Euromonitor International, says companies like SABMiller are looking for niche markets. &ldquo;The African beer market is highly consolidated,&rdquo; she says, so there&rsquo;s a &ldquo;big fight&rdquo; for new markets.  </p>
  
    <p>SABMiller, founded in Johannesburg in the late 1800s, is battling with other beverage companies such as Heineken and Diageo for Africa&rsquo;s growing population of beer drinkers. Impala was pitched as a healthy alternative to illegal alcohol made from sorghum&mdash;a starchy grain&mdash;and corn. (Methanol and battery acid have reportedly been included in the moonshine recipes.) The Mozambique government is giving the beer a break on taxes, seen as a way to give the economy a boost by employing farmers to produce raw cassava. One year after its 2011 launch, nine million bottles of the brew have been sold. In Uganda, the company has had tax breaks for years with Eagle beer, made from sorghum. </p>
  
    <p>The beers have a different taste profile from Canadian brands. Take Chibuku, an opaque beer with the consistency of a milkshake. It&rsquo;s made from sorghum and corn, and the &#64258;avour ranges from sour to sweet, depending on the region. Packaged in cheerful white, blue and red one-litre cartons, the beer ferments in the store, going from 0.5 per cent alcohol to four per cent over a period of five days, at which point it expires and must be tossed. </p>
  
    <p>SABMiller is planning to use the Impala formula in Zimbabwe, Tanzania and Zambia. &ldquo;We hope to extend the use of cassava as a brewing ingredient beyond Mozambique,&rdquo; says Andy Wales, SABMiller&rsquo;s vice-president of sustainable development. There are other unconventional beer crops being considered too, he says, but can&rsquo;t &ldquo;disclose specifics, for obvious reasons.&rdquo;</p>
    
    <byline>Stephanie Findlay</byline>
    
    
    
    
  
  <slug>Mexico</slug>
  
  <hedline>Wrap it up </hedline>
  
    <abstract>Photos of Mexico&rsquo;s 25,000 missing  now appear on tortilla wrappers</abstract>
 
  
    <p>In the U.S., milk cartons carrying smiling images of missing children once served as grim reminders of the unimaginable each morning around the breakfast table. Mexicans eat tortillas the way Americans drink milk; now tortilla wrappers are being used to drum up information on Mexico&rsquo;s missing men, women and children. This month, three dozen tortilla mills in Ciudad Ju&aacute;rez&rsquo;s bad barrios began wrapping their hot tortillas in paper ads pleading for information on the missing. Over the course of the drug wars, the border city has become notorious for brutal murders and disappearances. &ldquo;The disappearances in Ju&aacute;rez have to disappear,&rdquo; read the government-sponsored wrappers. </p>
  
    <p>The scourge of disappearances there&mdash;once the murder capital of the hemisphere, but now calm enough to have recorded its first murder-free weekend in five years&mdash;dates back two decades, and has included hundreds of young women, whose cases have gone mostly unsolved. The tortilla industry seems anxious to be of assistance. &ldquo;A friend of mine has been unable to find her daughter for a few years,&rdquo; Esperanza Lozoya, a shop owner, told media. &ldquo;We have to help out.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>The problem of missing persons in Mexico goes beyond Ciudad Ju&aacute;rez. New government data estimates a staggering 25,000 Mexicans have gone missing in the last six years. The government list, obtained by <em>Maclean&rsquo;s</em>, collates physical characteristics&mdash;nose shape, tattoos and piercings&mdash;but often gives little more information than the missing person&rsquo;s name, address and birthdate. &ldquo;Went out to buy cigarettes, but never returned,&rdquo; is the extent of information relating to a woman who went missing in the northeastern state of Tamaulipas. Her case remains unresolved, like so many in Mexico, where the country&rsquo;s human rights commission estimates that just one per cent of murders result in a conviction.  </p>
  
    <p>The missing-person problem is now the responsibility of new President Enrique Pe&ntilde;a Nieto. He promises to focus on kidnapping and extortion&mdash;not just nabbing cartel kingpins. Analysts urge him not to forget the missing. &ldquo;No one is looking for them,&rdquo; says Alberto Islas, CEO of Risk Evaluation in Mexico City. &ldquo;Most could be dead or in mass graves.&rdquo; But, he adds, police need to start looking.</p>
    
     <byline>David Agren</byline>
  

 
  
  <slug>France</slug>
  
  <hedline>Rise of gay mosques</hedline>
  
 
  
    <p>France&rsquo;s first gay-friendly mosque recently opened in Paris to widespread criticism from Muslim groups. A local Islamic leader, rector of the city&rsquo;s Grand Mosque, said it goes against Islam. A Facebook post labelled its members&rsquo; sexuality a &ldquo;disease.&rdquo; Founder Ludovic-Mohamed Zahed is ignoring the hateful comments: &ldquo;We don&rsquo;t care.&rdquo; Rather, he points to the praise he has received, including an email from a lesbian Muslim, who told him he was &ldquo;opening the doors of the Islam of tomorrow.&rdquo; Zahed, a gay Muslim married to a man, opened the mosque in a donated room on the outskirts of the city, but plans to reopen next year with a library and office in central Paris. He is part of a growing global movement promoting a more progressive reading of the Quran. The Paris mosque is a member of Muslims for Progressive Values (MPV), a U.S.-based organization with chapters in Ottawa, Toronto and five U.S. cities (and plans for a Danish chapter). The movement focuses on inclusivity, says MPV&rsquo;s L.A.-based founder Ani Zonneveld, a singer-songwriter. &ldquo;In 20 years it will be the norm for women to be leading prayers,&rdquo; she says, and for gays and lesbians &ldquo;to be included as equals.&rdquo; She asks, &ldquo;How can you say Islam is a religion of peace, when you discriminate, when you are unjust? Justice is the foundation of peace.&rdquo;</p>
    
     <byline>Rosemary Westwood</byline>
  



 
  
  <slug>United States</slug>
  
  <hedline>Trouble at  the Tea Party</hedline>
  
 
    <p>Is the Tea Party disbanding in the wake of the 2012 election? Maybe not, but the movement has begun losing some of its most powerful supporters. Last week, FreedomWorks, the conservative advocacy group that helped create the Tea Party movement, parted ways with its chairman. Dick Armey, the former House majority leader said he left due to &ldquo;serious concerns about the ethical and moral behaviour&rdquo; of FreedomWorks president Matt Kibbe. Kibbe had allegedly used staff resources to help write his book, <em>Give Us Liberty: A Tea Party Manifesto</em>, leaving the group little time for actual Tea Party organizing. </p>
  
    <p>The Tea Party also lost its key player in government last week. South Carolina Sen. Jim DeMint, a powerful conservative who raised money for many anti-establishment candidates and wrote an article this year for The American Spectator called &ldquo;Tea Party is the new reality,&rdquo; announced he was giving up his Senate seat. He had accepted a position to head the Heritage Foundation, a 40-year-old conservative think tank. </p>
  
    <p>Tea Party supporters argue that the movement maintains power in Washington. The Tea Party caucus of the House of Representatives still has 47 members; many candidates DeMint endorsed are in the Senate, including Marco Rubio, a rising Republican star from Florida. But the Tea Party, which was formed to energize the Republican base, may have outlived some of its usefulness. DeMint told the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> that Republicans must reach beyond the base and convince people who don&rsquo;t already agree with them: &ldquo;This is an urgent time because we saw in the last election we were not able to communicate conservative ideas that win elections.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>That means working to popularize these ideas among the groups who voted for Obama in 2012, but it may also mean making way for a new Republican establishment. DeMint is reportedly lobbying for representative Tim Scott to become his replacement in the Senate. Scott&rsquo;s appointment would give Republicans their first black Southern senator since Reconstruction. Maybe the Tea Party will stage a comeback&mdash;but with a younger, more diverse membership.</p>
    
     <byline> Jaime J. Weinman</byline>




  



  
 
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Business</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Media</slug>
  
   <hedline>Does Wii have  a problem? </hedline>
  
    <abstract>Nintendo, Sony and Microsoft are struggling to reinvent video games as touchscreens and tablets  take over the living room</abstract>
  
  <byline>Chris Sorensen</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_XBOX01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Moving on: iPads topped most Chistmas wishlists in 2012, not game consoles </photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>PHOTO ILLUSTRATION BY ANDREW TOLSON</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Nintendo&rsquo;s 2006 launch of the Wii console marked a new era for video games. With its innovative motion-sensing controllers, used to mimic the swing of a tennis racquet or golf club, the $250 Wii immediately struck a chord with gamers and non-gamers alike. Amazon sold out of its initial stock of sleek, white Wii consoles in just seven minutes. </p>
  
    <p>The Wii&rsquo;s unexpected success catapulted third-ranked Nintendo to the top of the video game industry, ahead of Microsoft&rsquo;s Xbox 360 and Sony&rsquo;s PlayStation 3&mdash;both of which are more powerful (and more expensive) machines. More importantly, it suggested a much wider potential market for game consoles beyond basement-dwelling teenagers.  </p>
  
    <p>But the renaissance has proved short-lived. Console sales have declined dramatically in recent years as existing systems grow long in the tooth. Nintendo posted a loss of $530 million this year, its first since 1981. And competition from tablets and smartphones, with their cheap, downloadable games, threatens to steal away millions of casual gamers. &ldquo;Tablets and smartphones are the black hole of the consumer electronics industry right now, sucking the growth out of everything else,&rdquo; says Kaan Yigit, the president of Toronto&rsquo;s Solutions Research Group, a consumer research firm. &ldquo;The growth rates we saw after Wii first came out are but a distant memory.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>It&rsquo;s into this maw of uncertainty that Nintendo recently launched its Wii successor: the Wii U. With its tablet-like GamePad controller, Wii U promises to once again rethink the video game experience by adding a second screen to the action. Yet, despite strong initial sales, few expect a repeat performance. Critics say the Wii U&rsquo;s attempt to mix tablets and television is actually more confusing than engaging, and is not nearly as innovative as the original Wii. Nor is there any reason to believe Sony and Microsoft will fare any better when they roll out their own next-generation systems over the next few years.  </p>
  
    <p>Video game consoles, for a brief time, seemed like the future of household electronics. They married video games with online services like Xbox Live and the PlayStation Network, as well as Netflix. But these days everyone from Apple and Google to local cable and satellite providers are racing to bridge the Internet-TV divide. Mario, in other words, may have finally met his match. </p>
  
    <p>Nintendo&rsquo;s immediate challenge is convincing consumers the Wii U actually represents a step up from its predecessor&mdash;one that&rsquo;s worth the $300 sticker price ($350 if you buy the &ldquo;deluxe&rdquo; set, which includes the game <em>Nintendo Land</em>). &ldquo;What was great about Wii is that someone else could watch you playing and understand exactly what you were doing,&rdquo; says Matt Ryan, a spokesperson for Nintendo Canada. &ldquo;They knew the Wii remote controller was your tennis racquet, golf club or sword.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Not so with the Wii U. Although the GamePad also acts as a motion controller, a big bulky one that&rsquo;s festooned with buttons and joysticks, the real innovation comes from the tablet&rsquo;s six-inch touchscreen. &ldquo;The core essence of what the Wii U GamePad offers is a second window, or perspective, into the gaming world on the TV screen,&rdquo; Ryan says. For example, sometimes the GamePad&rsquo;s screen will display information that might normally be available only by pushing a button&mdash;say, an overhead map of the world being explored by Mario and his brother, Luigi. Other times, it might be used to keep certain information secret from other players, or to give one player the ability to influence the game through the touchscreen. It&rsquo;s called asymmetrical gaming, and while it sounds complex, it&rsquo;s not new. Most card games are based on the concept that some information&mdash;like a poker player&rsquo;s hand&mdash; is kept secret from other players.  </p>
  
    <p>The reviews have so far been mixed. &ldquo;I&rsquo;ve played <em>Nintendo Land</em>, I&rsquo;ve played <em>ZombiU</em>, and they&rsquo;re good,&rdquo; Peter Molyneux, a game designer and former Microsoft executive, told the website <em>Games Industry</em>, referring to two of the Wii U&rsquo;s hottest titles. &ldquo;But I find holding the device in my hand&mdash;looking up at the screen and looking down at the device&mdash;slightly confusing.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>Nintendo says it has sold about 400,000 Wii U units in North America since they went on sale Nov. 18. But what happens once all of the game enthusiasts get their hands on the first brand-new console in six years? One recent report by media research firm IHS predicted the Wii U would sell on par with its predecessor initially, but that sales would soon slow. IHS estimated 56.7 million units sold during the first four years, compared with 76 million for the original Wii. </p>
  
    <p>Not surprisingly, game consoles in general are losing their top-of-mind status among young buyers. A recent survey by media research firm Neilsen found that the iPad was the must-have gadget on the holiday wish lists of children aged 6 to 12. Wii U was second, followed by three more Apple products: the iPod Touch, iPad Mini and iPhone. The Xbox 360 and PS3 were even further down the list.  </p>
  
    <p>Others, however, say it may be too soon to declare &ldquo;game over&rdquo; for the industry. Lewis Ward, a Boston-based analyst with research firm IDC, blames slowing sales on the sluggish U.S. economy and the fact that all three platforms had reached the end of their life cycle. &ldquo;There are a lot of dour predictions about where consoles are going,&rdquo; says Ward, who predicts a successor to the Xbox 360 will be unveiled by the end of 2013 with an all-new PlayStation coming shortly after. &ldquo;But I do expect a rebound over the next several years, assuming that we don&rsquo;t have another massive macro-economic downturn.&rdquo; Buoyed by the new hardware, Ward forecasts North American sales of game consoles hitting 20 million units by 2014, compared to just under 16 million this year. That&rsquo;s up nearly 25 per cent, although still off the peak of 25 million units sold in 2008. As for the threat from tablets, Ward says hand-held game devices like Nintendo&rsquo;s 3DS and Sony&rsquo;s PS Vita are most at risk. &ldquo;The console experience is different for a number of reasons&mdash;particularly among the hard-core crowd who play shooters,&rdquo; he says, using the video game slang for trigger-happy first-person games like <em>Halo</em> and <em>Call of Duty</em>. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s the graphics and surround sound. If you&rsquo;re going to be playing for hours, you don&rsquo;t want to be playing on a touchscreen.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Console makers may have another ace up their sleeve as they attempt to build their market beyond teens and other hard-core gamers. Though it&rsquo;s not currently their main focus, Microsoft, Sony and Nintendo are all well positioned to capitalize on the growing trend toward streamed television. All three consoles already offer families an easy way to get Netflix on their TV sets (Sony claims the PS3 is the most-used Netflix device) while some Xbox and PS3 users have access to live sports content through ESPN and MLB TV apps. Nintendo will be offering a TVii app on the Wii U that allows users to combine television content from multiple sources, ranging from Netflix to traditional cable, and access it through a single interface: the GamePad. &ldquo;The game consoles are trying to co-opt all the TV stuff,&rdquo; Ward says, adding that the future of TV watching will be highly interactive, with tablets and other &ldquo;smart&rdquo; devices all thrown into the mix. (Microsoft already has an application called Xbox SmartGlass that allows users to use their smartphones and tablets as a second screen for some games, as well as remote controls.) </p>
  
    <p>Ironically, it&rsquo;s in the midst of this jumble of technology that the Wii U, as muddled as it initially seems, actually makes the most sense. &ldquo;The Wii U GamePad forces players to confront one of the strangest features of the contemporary media ecosystem: the tension between the television and the hand-held computer,&rdquo; Ian Bogost, a video game designer and professor at the Georgia Institute of Technology, wrote in an essay published on the website <em>Gamasutra</em>. Playing the Wii U feels awkward, he says, because having our attention divided between the TV and the Internet is awkward. But given this is where the living room is headed&mdash;most TV viewers already surf the web and check Facebook while watching their favourite sitcoms&mdash;Nintendo appears to be wholeheartedly embracing the shift, rather than fighting it.  </p>
  
    <p>Ultimately, that could prove far more innovative than a game controller you waggle over your head.     </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Business</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Economy</slug>
  
   <hedline>Worse than Greece? </hedline>
  
    <abstract>While eurozone nations tighten their belts, America may face the bleaker future as its debt troubles pile up</abstract>
  
  <byline>Tamsin McMahon</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_ECONOMY01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>In stride: Austerity pays off in Greece</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Jin Lee/Bloomberg/Getty Images</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>With the international community warning again that European debt woes could knock the wind out of the U.S. recovery&mdash;and by extension Canada&rsquo;s economy&mdash;and spark a global recession, there was a rare bit of good news coming out of the Continent. A new study by the Lisbon Council and Berenberg Bank suggests that it&rsquo;s Europe, not the United States, that is on the more stable path toward long-term economic prosperity. </p>
  
    <p>Since 2009, the eurozone&rsquo;s most troubled countries have been making significant gains in slashing their deficits, overhauling their civil service, cutting labour costs and fixing their trade balances. Far from showing evidence of &ldquo;moral hazard,&rdquo; the authors say countries that were bailed out by the European Union and the International Monetary Fund &ldquo;are working hard to make sure that they deserve such support and can get back onto their own feet again fast.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>The same, the report warns, can&rsquo;t be said of the United States, which faces a $1-trillion deficit for the fourth year in a row and where its lawmakers are deadlocked over how to handle the prospect of $600 billion in tax hikes and spending cuts set to automatically take effect at the end of the year, known as the fiscal cliff. Economists are predicting that once again Congress will be forced to raise the debt ceiling by February and that the country may need a fourth round of quantitative easing (in which the Federal Reserve pumps money into the economy by buying Treasury bonds). </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Many eurozone members are going through a wave of sweeping structural and fiscal reforms while the region as a whole is strengthening its governance structure,&rdquo; the authors wrote. &ldquo;At the same time, other even more heavily indebted major economies such as the U.S. and Japan are not.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>An IMF report last month confirmed much of the same. In the past three years, Greece, Portugal, Ireland and Spain have collectively slashed their budget deficits by the equivalent of 11 per cent of their GDP. Greece raised its retirement age by two years and cut its deficit from 15 per cent of GDP in 2009 to 7.5 per cent this year. Spain has introduced public sector wage cuts and a pension freeze and even managed to eke out a small trade surplus for the first time since 1998. Portugal has already cut its deficit in half since 2009. The eurozone is expected to post a collective budget deficit of 2.6 per cent of GDP next year, the organization said, compared to 7.3 per cent in the U.S. (Canada&rsquo;s is expected to be three per cent.)  </p>
  
    <p>Granted, much of the progress has more to do with the dire economic circumstances facing Europe&rsquo;s most troubled countries than it does good governance. Skyrocketing unemployment, which tops 25 per cent in Greece and Spain, has helped drive down labour costs. Trade imbalances have improved not because countries are exporting more, but because they are importing less thanks to collapsing housing markets that have sapped consumer demand. Even as some eurozone countries have overhauled their economies, their debts have soared. The study&rsquo;s authors warned that an &ldquo;overdose of austerity&rdquo; could reverse many of the hard-won gains. </p>
  
    <p>Still, they note that in the long run America will require more belt tightening than Greece if both countries are to slash their debt-to-GDP ratios to 60 per cent by 2030, a key measure of economic health. That, they said, would mean that Europe, not the U.S., may emerge from recession &ldquo;as the most dynamic of the major Western economies.&rdquo;     </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Business</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <slug>Technology</slug>
  
   <hedline>Mind games </hedline>
  
    <abstract>How a Canadian start-up plans to make thought-controlled smartphones the next consumer craze</abstract>
  
  <byline>Jason McBride</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_MIND_CONTROL01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>It can read your mind: InteraXon&rsquo;s Trevor Coleman allows the Muse to surf his brainwaves</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>photograph by Jessica darmanin</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
    <p>Having trouble focusing on that 30-page contract? Just got chewed out by your boss and wish you had reacted more calmly? Trying to stay relaxed before a life-or-death job interview? Not only will there soon be an app for all that, but it&rsquo;ll be one that you control with your mind. </p>
  
    <p>This spring, the Toronto-based tech company InteraXon will release a product called Muse, a wearable brainwave reader that connects wirelessly to any smartphone or tablet device. Much like a heart monitor can measure physical exertion, Muse gauges levels of concentration, stress and relaxation. Through an app and various games that come bundled with the device, users will be able to strengthen those parts of their brains responsible for working memory and focus. </p>
  
    <p>Using software originally created by the renowned University of Toronto engineer and cyberneticist Steve Mann (often dubbed &ldquo;the world&rsquo;s first cyborg&rdquo;), thought-controlled computing technology translates brainwaves into digital signals recognizable by a computer&mdash;be it the chip in a video game, espresso maker or automobile. In other words, the brain&rsquo;s electrical activity, which can be trained just like any muscle, is converted by an interface into binary code. </p>
  
    <p>In 2007, a trio of young Mann disciples formed InteraXon to develop commercial applications for the technology. The company first entered the public consciousness with a trippy demo during the 2010 Winter Olympics that allowed headset-equipped visitors in Vancouver to mentally control light shows at the CN Tower and Niagara Falls.  </p>
  
    <p>Muse is the company&rsquo;s first consumer product, a device that is, according to co-founder and CEO Ariel Garten, &ldquo;a jumping-off point for an entire future of interacting with content and objects directly with our minds.&rdquo; While brain-computer interface (BCI) technology has been available for several decades&mdash;everyone from Mattel to the Australian electronics firm Emotiv has developed various BCI-enabled toys and assistive devices&mdash;InteraXon is the only significant Canadian player in the field. And it has concentrated its efforts on trying to make the technology as affordable, stylish and unobtrusive as possible. Muse is a thin, lightweight, sensor-equipped headband hardly more ostentatious than the average Bluetooth headset. It&rsquo;s designed to be worn round-the-clock so that users can build a comprehensive profile of their brain activity, store the data in their phones, and track their progress over time.  </p>
  
    <p>Muse will retail for $199 at mainstream electronics stores (Garten won&rsquo;t reveal specific dealers yet), coupled with the brain-fitness application and a software development kit so users can build their own apps. Funding for the product&mdash;Garten estimates it has cost millions in research and development&mdash;has come from a variety of sources, primarily government grants, angel investors and venture capital. A crowd-funding campaign has raised more than $200,000. (For donations of $8,500 or more, InteraXon will show up at your house or party with their thought-controlled beer tap.) </p>
  
    <p>A Muse prototype was unveiled last year in conjunction with a 3D TV &ldquo;environment,&rdquo; a whimsical and eerily tactile winterscape created by Toronto artist Alex McLeod. Using the Muse, viewers can manipulate elements of the environment&mdash;a flock of birds, say, or a boat in the water&mdash;by relaxing (thereby amping up alpha waves) or grinding their teeth. McLeod was mesmerized by the result. &ldquo;I couldn&rsquo;t believe it,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;Being able to control things with my mind, it felt like it was right in front of me.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Avianna Chao, a software engineer and a member of the Canadian national pistol team, will begin training with the Muse next year, leading up to the 2015 Pan Am games. &ldquo;Our sport is all about precision,&rdquo; she says. &ldquo;You have to be able to focus when you need to focus and relax when you need to relax. This is like a gateway to your brain.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Muse&rsquo;s potential uses seem limited only by the imagination, and Garten says that various medical devices employing the same basic technology are also in the works. Working with the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health and Toronto Western Hospital, InteraXon is developing an ADHD trainer for children and a system to warn epileptics and their caregivers of an impending seizure. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Our initial idea was: how to control the world with your mind?&rdquo; Garten says. &ldquo;Now it&rsquo;s more important to us to have a world that understands and adapts to your needs. It&rsquo;s about helping people become better at doing what they want to do.&rdquo;   </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Business</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>Econowatch </hedline>
  
    <abstract>A monthly scorecard on the state of the economy in North America and beyond</abstract>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>In approving the $15-billion takeover of Nexen Energy by China&rsquo;s CNOOC, Stephen Harper cautioned that the sale was &ldquo;the end of a trend.&rdquo; Foreign ownership in the oil sands is okay, <em>this time,</em> but in the future, state-owned enterprises (SOEs) must be kept at bay, Ottawa ruled. The move was politically astute, but may prove economically dangerous. While attention has focused on whether we should fear SOEs like CNOOC and Malaysia&rsquo;s Petronas (which also won approval to buy Progress Energy), the really scary question is: what will become of Canada&rsquo;s oil sands without them?</p>
    
   <p>As investors go, SOEs might not seem ideal. Critics argue they open the door to foreign governments dictating where our oil is sold and at what price. But Canada holds the trump card in the relationship through its ability to dictate royalty and tax rates, as well as labour and environmental laws that SOEs have to follow just like anyone else. Even if they decided to sell oil to China at less than market prices, the loss would be theirs, not ours. </p>
   
   <p>The fact is that SOEs, not just in China but across Asia and the Middle East, rank among the few with the kind of money needed to fuel Alberta&rsquo;s oil sands, where capital spending alone is expected to climb to more than $200 billion by 2025. They control 70 per cent of the word&rsquo;s oil reserves, and 13 of the 20 biggest oil companies are state-run. This week, Natural Resources Minister Joe Oliver told the oil sands industry that investment will still flow into Alberta despite the recent ruling. Yet SOEs have been providing the bulk of the funding recently. Chinese SOEs have now sunk more than $25 billion into Canada&rsquo;s energy sector since 2009. Ottawa is stressing that investment by SOEs is still welcome, just not ownership&mdash;not exactly an arms-open invitation. </p>
   
   <p>Putting up any kind of barrier to investment is probably the worst thing Ottawa could do. &ldquo;We have an ideology that says a free-market economy must also have a democratic government behind it,&rdquo; explains David Detomasi, a professor of international business at Queen&rsquo;s University. &ldquo;A big chunk of the world doesn&rsquo;t believe that. And they&rsquo;re the ones with the cash.&rdquo;</p>
  
    <byline>Colin Campbell</byline>
  
 
  
  <hedline>The good news</hedline>
  
  <p>Starbucks expects to open 1,500 new caf&eacute;s in the U.S. over the next five years, a strong bet that Americans will be in better shape to fork over $7 for its newly launched Costa Rica Finca Palmilera brew.</p>
  
  <p>&rsquo;Tis the season to raise a glass . . . or three. Sales of beer, wine and spirits are on track to set a record this holiday, with $85 being spent by the average Canadian.</p>
  
  <p>Bonuses for employees at Canadian banks were up 7.5 per cent this year. That&rsquo;s in stark contrast to New York and London, where pay cuts remain the norm.</p>
  
  <p>Canada has moved to eighth place, up three spots, in an annual ranking of the most tax-friendly places for companies to do business. It&rsquo;s our first time in the top 10.</p>
  
  <p>The Canadian and U.S. economies added jobs in November: 59,300 and 146,000, respectively. The jobless rate fell to 7.2  per cent in Canada and 7.7 in the U.S. (the lowest level  in years).</p>
  
  <p>Canada&rsquo;s auto parts sector has been running full tilt. Production is forecast to be up over 22 per cent this year, says the Conference Board of Canada&mdash;the best output since 2007. </p>
  
  <p>China&rsquo;s industrial output rose 10 per cent in November, the biggest jump since March, thanks to more big infrastructure projects. They include six brand new subway systems in Chinese cities.</p>
  
  <p>The bad news</p>
  
  <p>Canadians are working two years longer than they did in the &rsquo;90s, says Statistics Canada. Less-educated workers have it worst: their life expectancy after retirement is shorter than university-trained workers. </p>
  
  <p>Economists at CIBC are concerned about  a chronic mismatch in the Canadian job  market: not enough qualified people to  fill high-demand jobs, and a glut of people seeking unskilled positions. </p>
  
  <p>The NHL lockout delivered a body check to GDP growth in the third quarter. Spending on entertainment, including hockey games, was down 2.6 per cent.</p>
  
  <p>Japan&rsquo;s economy officially fell into recession after GDP shrank 0.9 per cent in the third quarter. It could soon be joined by Germany, another export nation, as the eurozone crisis deepens.</p>
  
  <p>Food prices will rise by as much as 3.5 per cent next year, according to University of Guelph researchers. Meat products are expected to lead the way, thanks to droughts in the U.S. last year that raised feed prices.</p>
  
  <p>The ultimate engine of the U.S. economy, consumer spending, is weakening. One key measure of consumer sentiment fell to its lowest level in four months last week. </p>
  
  <p>The Bank of Canada warned last week that a Toronto condo market correction could rock the entire economy. Housing sales in Toronto were down 16 per cent in November compared to last year. </p>
  
  
  
  <slug>Signs of the Times</slug>
  
  <hedline> Moving mountains</hedline>
  
    <p>Netflix CEO Reed Hastings has a lot to boast about lately, including a recent blockbuster deal to stream Disney movies. But Hastings had better be careful where he does his bragging. He&rsquo;s now in hot water after posting on Facebook that Netflix users streamed over a billion hours of video in June. U.S. regulators called it &ldquo;selective disclosure,&rdquo; given that he only has about 200,000 followers.</p>
    
   <p>In a historic first, a liquified natural gas tanker sailed from Norway to Japan through the normally ice-choked Arctic. Due to global warming, the specially reinforced ship is hoping to shave three weeks off a trip that normally goes through the Suez Canal. Whether it&rsquo;s a feat to be celebrated is another question entirely.</p>
   
   <p>A Chinese developer is embarking on a bold project to flatten 700 small &ldquo;mountains,&rdquo; or barren hills, as part of a $11.2-billion plan to expand the desert city of Lanzhou in northwestern China, population 3.2 million. The entire controversial project involves 806 sq. km. Critics are concerned about a lack of sufficient water resources and the city&rsquo;s already dubious reputation as one of China&rsquo;s most polluted. </p>
   
   <p>Under scrutiny over working conditions in its Asian factories, Apple is joining a small but growing number of U.S. companies who are &ldquo;re-shoring&rdquo; jobs. CEO Tim Cook promised to spend $100 million to build Mac computers in the United States. A baby step to be sure, but there&rsquo;s hope other U.S. executives will be lining up to do the same&mdash;just like they did to buy iPhones.</p>
  
 
  
  <p><em>&lsquo;The U.S. GDP growth rate that we have become accustomed to for  over 100 years&mdash;in excess of three per cent a year. It is gone forever.&rsquo;</em></p>
  
  <p>&mdash;Influential U.S. investor Jeremy Grantham is known for his bearish views, but in his latest newsletter, his pessimism hit a new low, with a prediction that economic growth in the U.S. will be stuck at just one per cent indefinitely.  </p>
  


  <hedline>By the numbers</hedline>


    <p>25 per cent The number of Canadians expecting a year-end bonus, says a BMO poll.</p>
   <p>11,000 The number of jobs Citigroup is cutting&mdash;four per cent of its workforce.</p>
   <p>4.9 million The number of unemployed people in Spain in November. The jobless rate is 25 per cent.</p>
   <p>$1 billion The amount of Apple stock bought by a rogue ex-trader at Rochdale Securities. He was charged with wire fraud last week.</p>
   <p>$1.9 billion The biggest antitrust penalty ever, imposed by the European Commission on six electronics firms accused of fixing prices. </p>
  
    <p>$11 billion The amount the head of Norway&rsquo;s Government Pension Fund says the fund plans to invest in the U.S. real estate market.</p>
   <p>$2.8 trillion Total U.S. consumer debt, a record. Americans borrowed big in October for cars and student loans. </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Year in Pictures</sections>
  
 <body.head>
 
  <hedline>2012</hedline>
  
  <abstract> A sweep at the Grammys. A Diamond Jubilee. A devastating hurricane. All that, plus spectacular moments in politics, sports and world news, captured in this special section.</abstract>
  
  </body.head>
  
 <body.content>
 
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JAN06.jpg"></photo>

  
  <photo.caption><em>JANUARY  Giglio Island,  Italy</em> The wreck of the Costa Concordia cruise ship, which ran aground on a reef and finally came to rest near shore on Jan. 14, killing 32 and  injuring more than 60 <em>(Reuters) </em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JAN02.jpg"></photo>
   
    <photo.caption><em>JANUARY Frankfurt,  Germany</em> A penguin  goes for a swim in a zoo <em>(Michael Probst/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
 <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_FEB01.jpg"></photo>
 
   <photo.caption><em>FEBRUARY Pittsburg</em>h  The Penguins&rsquo; Evgeni Malkin stretches before an NHL game against the Tampa Bay Lightning <em>(Gene J. Puskar/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_FEB03.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption><em>FEBRUARY Los Angeles</em> Singer Adele at the 54th Grammy Awards, winning in each of six categories she was nominated <em>(Lucy Nicholson/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_FEB06.jpg"></photo>
    
  <photo.caption><em>Karachi, Pakistan</em> A labourer works at a small foundry, earning about $5.15 a day <em>(Fareed Khan/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_MAR99.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption><em>MARCH Harrison, Tenn.</em> Tornadoes cut through the Midwest from Texas up through the Great Lakes <em>(Billy Weeks/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_MAR02.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>March New Delhi</em> A Tibetan exile protests a visit from Chinese President Hu Jintao to India <em>(reuters)</em> </photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_MAR04.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>London</em> Catherine, duchess of Cambridge, plays hockey with Team GB at the Riverside Arena in the Olympic Park <em>(Chris Jackson/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_APR08.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>APRIL Pyongyang, North Korea</em> A choir sings during a concert to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the birth of Kim Il Sung <em>(david guttenfelder/ap)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_APR01.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>APRIL Pakistan</em> A group of men in the Malakand district, northwest of Islamabad,  use rope to right a supply truck overloaded with straw <em>(mian khursheed/reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_MAY01.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>MAY Kandahar, Afghanistan</em>  A U.S. Army private takes cover during a controlled detonation  to clear an area to set up a checkpoint <em>(Shamil Zhumatov/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_MAY09.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>MAY Vietnam</em> Ducks on their way to a market in Ha Nam province, outside Hanoi <em>(nguyen huy kham/ reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_MAY06.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>Somalia</em> African Union soldiers before they advance on a town west of Mogadishu to fight al-Shabaab militants <em>(stuart price/reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JUN04.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>JUNE London</em> Prince William  and his wife, Kate, board a ship to watch a Diamond Jubilee flotilla of more than 1,000  vessels on the Thames River,  the largest such event in 350  years <em>(uK Press/KEYSTONE Press)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JUN02.jpg"></photo>


  <photo.caption><em>JUNE Niagara Falls, Ont.</em> Daredevil Nik Wallenda, the &lsquo;King of the Wire,&rsquo; halfway through his 25-minute tightrope walk over the Falls <em>(Frank Gunn/CP)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JUN01.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>Sicamous, B.C.</em> A local state of emergency is called after the area is inundated by heavy rain, flooding and mudslides <em>(JONATHAN HAYWARD/CP)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JUL01.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>JULY Pamplona, Spain</em>  A participant is tossed  during the running of the bulls of the San Fermin festival  <em>(Daniel Ochoa de Olza/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JUL07.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>JULY Glen Allen, Va.</em> Barack Obama steps up his campaigning as polls showed a tight presidential race with Republican Mitt Romney <em>(JASON REED/REUTERS)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_JUL06.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>Ottawa</em> Prime Minister Stephen Harper at the Canada Day celebrations <em>(steve simon) </em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_AUG02.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>AUGUST New York City</em> Carly Rae Jepsen sings Call Me Maybe to young fans for NBC&rsquo;s Today show <em>(Brendan McDermid/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_AUG03.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>AUGUST Bucharest, Romania</em> A bride poses for the camera at the Arch of Triumph after being &lsquo;kidnapped&rsquo; on her wedding night <em>(Vadim Ghirda/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OLYMPICS01.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>London</em> Gabrielle Douglas of the U.S. on the balance beam during the women&rsquo;s individual gymnastics final at the North Greenwich Arena <em>(Dylan Martinez/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OLYMPICS05.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>AUGUST London</em> Canada&rsquo;s  Jennifer Abel and &Eacute;milie Heymans in mid-dive during the women&rsquo;s synchronized 3-m springboard final <em>(julia vynokurova/getty images)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OLYMPICS03.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>AUGUST London</em> Jamaica&rsquo;s Usain Bolt crosses the finish line ahead of the pack to  win gold in the men&rsquo;s 100-m final at the Olympic Stadium  <em>(david j. phillip/ap)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_SEP05.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>SEPTEMBER Democratic Republic of the Congo</em> The Lesula monkey is only the second new species of African monkey discovered in 28 years <em>(reuters) </em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_SEP06.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>SEPTEMBER Sivakasi, India</em> People run for cover as smoke rises from the site of a blaze at a fireworks factory, which killed 52 people <em>(ap)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_SEP03.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>Montreal</em> New Quebec Premier Pauline Marois is led off the stage during her victory speech, interrupted by a shooting in the building <em>(Paul chiasson/cp)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OCT02.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>OCTOBER Above  Roswell, N.M.</em> Austrian Felix Baumgartner, 43, became  the first skydiver to go faster than the speed of sound, reaching a velocity of 1,342 km/h when he jumped out  of a balloon 39 km above  New Mexico. He also smashed the record for the highest-ever freefall. <em>(UPPA)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OCT07.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>OCTOBER Hoboken, N.J.</em> Taxis sit in a flooded lot in the wake of hurricane Sandy <em>(Michael Bocchieri/Getty images)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OCT05.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>OCTOBER Union Beach, N.J.</em> A house damaged by hurricane Sandy, one of the most destructive natural disasters to ever hit the U.S. Northeast <em>(eric thayer/reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_OCT06.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>Seaside Heights, N.J.</em> Waves break against a crumpled roller coaster at an amusement park destroyed by the storm <em>(Mario Tama/GETTY IMAGES)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_NOV01.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>NOVEMBER Chicago</em> Michelle and Barack Obama celebrate the presidential victory with Vice President Joe Biden and his wife, Jill <em>(Chris Carlson/AP)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_NOV04.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>NOVEMBER Los Angeles</em> Jenny McCarthy kisses Justin Bieber as he accepts an award at the American Music Awards <em>(Danny Moloshok/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
   <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_DEC02.jpg"></photo>

 <photo.caption><em>DECEMBER Kenya</em> The nomadic Maasai people register to vote using biometric computer equipment to decrease chance of fraud <em>(CARL DE SOUZA/AFP/Getty Images)</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_DEC01.jpg"></photo>

  <photo.caption><em>The Philippines</em> Rescuers evacuate survivors of typhoon flooding that killed 332 people and left hundreds more missing <em>(Erik de Castro/Reuters)</em></photo.caption>
  
    <photo href="file://images/MAC_YIP_DEC77.jpg"></photo>

<photo.caption><em>DECEMBER Glasgow,  Scotland</em> More than 1,000 people take part in the annual five-kilometre Glasgow Santa Dash <em>(jeff j. mitchell/getty)</em></photo.caption>

</body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Music</sections>
  
  <body.head>
    <hedline>The key to survival</hedline>
  
    <abstract>A new wave of young musicians is promoting the pipe organ&mdash;no hymns, no religious baggage</abstract>
  
  <byline>Joanne Latimer</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_ORGANMUSIC01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Organized Crime Duo: Changing the image of organists as blue-haired church marms, using stilettos and sequins</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Adrian Boxall</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Pipe organ music is often associated with two unpleasant events: a vampire attack by Bela Lugosi&mdash;<em>da, da, da, dahhhhhh</em>&mdash;or an endless Sunday liturgy. Its reputation has been tarnished by pianists banging out hymns on unfamiliar instruments, like tourists driving badly in a foreign country. And the popularity of pipe organ music has also been hampered by, well, organists themselves. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;We&rsquo;re the geeky outcasts playing an eccentric instrument,&rdquo; notes John Terauds, an organist and classical music blogger for the website <em>Musical Toronto</em>. &ldquo;When I tell people I&rsquo;m an organist, I&rsquo;m met with dead air.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Sarah Svendsen is a 23-year-old, award-winning organist who recently formed a group called Organized Crime Duo with colleague Rachel Mahon. &ldquo;We don&rsquo;t have the best set of social skills,&rdquo; she admits, laughing. Their goal is to change the outdated image of organists as blue-haired church marms; their strategy involves stilettos, sequins, some theatrics and lots of mascara. For their debut in October 2011 at Toronto&rsquo;s Phantoms of the Organ concert at the Metropolitan United Church, they vamped it up, spoofing Bach&rsquo;s famous <em>Toccata and Fugue in D Minor</em>; this year, they played the <em>Star Wars</em> theme. &ldquo;What better to attract a 12-year-old boy than a 23-year-old girl in a sexy dress?&rdquo; asks Svendsen. &ldquo;And <em>Star Wars</em>?&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Gordon Mansell, co-founder of Toronto&rsquo;s Organix organ festival, where Organized Crime Duo will perform crowd-pleasers like James Bond themes and possibly some Beatles tunes next May, says it&rsquo;s a new day for the pipe instrument. &ldquo;There&rsquo;s a wave of young organists who want to promote the organ as a viable performance instrument. No hymns, no religious baggage.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>As church attendance dwindles, organists have had trouble finding future audiences, not to mention players. Anxious to broaden the image of the organ as more than a pious instrument, the Royal Canadian College of Organists (RCCO) is in the middle of a major rebranding. &ldquo;We&rsquo;re getting the organ out of the loft and into the theatre, where it can better build bridges to mainstream culture,&rdquo; reports RCCO national president Nicholas Fairbank. He points to Vancouver organist Michael Dirk, 30, who played an original 1927 Wurlitzer organ at the Orpheum Theatre&rsquo;s 85th anniversary this fall. Dirk performed a sold-out tribute to iconic organ showman Virgil Fox at Music Fest Vancouver last summer, when he also accompanied the silent Laurel and Hardy film <em>The Second Hundred Years</em> by playing songs by the Beach Boys, Elvis, the Rolling Stones and Faith Hill. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s the coolest instrument,&rdquo; says Dirk, a full-time music teacher. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s &lsquo;organ meets airplane cockpit,&rsquo; but half of my students at school ask, &lsquo;What&rsquo;s an organ?&rsquo; &rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>To fill the generation gap, a series of one-day workshops for kids called Pedals, Pipes and Pizza, sponsored by the RCCO and other arts organizations, takes place across the country. &ldquo;The future of the organ is no longer wedded to the church and we have to get creative,&rdquo; says Neil Cockburn, who teaches the organ at Mount Royal University in Alberta and runs the Calgary Organ Festival and Symposium each fall. Cockburn recently held a workshop for kids, filled to capacity. &ldquo;I strongly suspect two organists were born that day,&rdquo; he notes enthusiastically. </p>
  
    <p>McGill University&rsquo;s organ department recently received a boost with the arrival of new department chairman Hans-Ol&aring; Ericsson, a famed professor from Sweden. Ericsson&rsquo;s avant-garde organ music was included in the soundtrack of the Leonardo DiCaprio film <em>Shutter Island</em>, but that isn&rsquo;t his claim to fame. He is the project leader for the creation of a symphonic invention, the Studio Acusticum organ, built for a new concert hall in Pite&aring;, Sweden.  The pipe organ, which had its debut this fall, has a built-in lighting system and is about to be fitted with a processor.  &ldquo;There is the possibility it can be played by a remote keyboard over the Internet,&rdquo; explains Ericsson, who describes his evolving creation as &ldquo;open concept&rdquo; in order to accommodate styles of music that have yet to be invented. &ldquo;Progressive musicians like Benny Andersson from ABBA are thrilled.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>In early November, Ericsson performed at Montreal&rsquo;s thriving Rendez-vous des Grands pipe organ festival, where the audience was peppered with Ericsson&rsquo;s hip and tattooed graduate students. &ldquo;Young bands really like what an organ can bring to the overall sound,&rdquo; says masters pipe organ student Gwen Bergman, 22, who settles for using an electric organ in her Montreal folk band, Lakes of Canada. Rock band Arcade Fire used a large Montreal church pipe organ for several songs on their 2007 album<em> Neon Bible</em>, but obviously it is impossible for groups to haul around a pipe organ. This portability problem has  plagued the instrument from the start,</p>
  
    <p> which explains the creation of the electric organ, which became popular after it was introduced to the market in the 1930s. Designed to simulate the sound of a pipe organ, to some musicians it is a shabby compromise more suited to hockey arenas, not concert halls and churches. </p>
  
    <p>Certainly the most dazzling proponent of the pipe organ is Cameron Carpenter, a Berlin-based, Ziggy Stardust character with virtuoso talent that cannot be ignored. A TED talk that has yet to air makes his position clear. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m demanding organists learn to live and work within the commercial framework of society,&rdquo; says Carpenter, 31, who performed with the Edmonton Symphony Orchestra in November wearing a Chanel coat, Preen glitter pants and Latin dance shoes with sparkly heels. &ldquo;You need to use sexuality and court publicity. You need a personal identity. You don&rsquo;t go to hear Yo-Yo Ma&rsquo;s cello; you go to hear Yo-Yo Ma. Look at what Jake Shimabukuro did for the ukulele. That&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;m doing. There is no known name for organists until now, and I&rsquo;m known for reasons that have nothing to do with the pipe organ. People accuse me of having a big ego. Only in the world of classical music is ego a dirty word.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>There&rsquo;s another reason his colleagues take issue. He just invented a new instrument&mdash;a digital touring organ. It cost $300,000, a bargain compared with a standard pipe organ, which takes years to build and months to install. Carpenter thinks the cost of the average pipe organ is unconscionable&mdash;&ldquo;$5-million-dollar organs in concert halls are a late-blooming vanity.&rdquo; So he sent his team around the world to digitally record the best pipe organs making their best sounds for his organ, which works much like a synthesizer. It&rsquo;s portable, and breaks down to fit into a few cases, each weighing less than 75 pounds. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Organists are denied an ongoing relationship with one instrument. It&rsquo;s not like a guitar or a flute. I crave that intimate relationship. I want to spend hundreds of hours with one instrument, and be able to travel and perform on that one instrument,&rdquo; explains Carpenter, who was home-schooled in Meadville, Pa., before attending the Juilliard School in New York for his undergraduate and master&rsquo;s degrees. &ldquo;Every organ is wildly different. It can take me 20 hours of rehearsal before a concert to set the buttons. It&rsquo;s gruelling. My plan is to break out of that jail.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>His critics think he&rsquo;s trying to burn it down. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s the purists who think he&rsquo;s trouble,&rdquo; explains Mansell of the Organix festival. &ldquo;They see him as a Liberace-like threat to the integrity of the music and they don&rsquo;t like his agenda&mdash;pushing his own digital organ. Cameron showed up at the IdeaCity event [in Toronto] and played atrociously, as he does sometimes to make his point, then produced a picture of his digital organ, telling everyone that it sounds better. The purists get fed up with him. But I think it&rsquo;s no time to split hairs. We need him.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Carpenter doesn&rsquo;t care. &ldquo;They aren&rsquo;t my colleagues,&rdquo; he states flatly. &ldquo;Why would I put up with an instrument that&rsquo;s always out of tune, as pipe organs inevitably are? They break down. There are dead notes and there&rsquo;s a delay. Pipe organs, as they exist today, utterly fail me. There&rsquo;s always some kind of cockpit emergency. Digital organs don&rsquo;t ask you to put up with any of that uncertainty. I want to play my new digital organ in Las Vegas, which is no joke. Playing in Vegas is a great American honour.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>There are some who feel Carpenter is building an audience for himself, not necessarily for the instrument. He snorts at this accusation. &ldquo;Ha! Nobody would say that about a pianist. And my goal is to play in schools and prisons like Johnny Cash. Isn&rsquo;t that audience-building?&rdquo;     </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Fame</sections>
  
  <body.head>
    <hedline>Winston Churchill&rsquo;s finest hours </hedline>
  
    <abstract>The much-quoted British politician still makes headlines&mdash;47 years after his death</abstract>
  
   <byline>Katie Engelhart</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_CHURCHILL01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Perpetual relevance: <em>The online publication of Churchill&rsquo;s personal papers &lsquo;will become a landmark in 20th-century historical studies&rsquo;</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Central Press/HULTON ARCHIVE/GETTY IMAGES</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
    <p>When Winston Churchill was a young boy, he was convinced of his imminent importance. The late British prime minister &ldquo;had a very strong sense that he was going to make his mark on history,&rdquo; says Natalie Adams, an archivist at the Churchill Archives Centre in Cambridge, England. &ldquo;So he kept everything. And we have everything.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>That includes drafts of speeches and correspondence with monarchs&mdash;as well as damning school reports, letters to his mother, and a stern warning from the security service that Cuban cigars received as gifts could be poisoned or rigged with explosives. </p>
  
    <p>In October, Churchill&rsquo;s personal papers were made available on the Internet. The archive is &ldquo;the closest the U.K. has to a presidential library,&rdquo; said Jonathan Glasspool, managing director of the publisher Bloomsbury Academic. &ldquo;Its publication online will become a landmark in 20th-century historical studies.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Forty-seven years after his death, Churchill is still a regular newsmaker and a benchmark against which today&rsquo;s leaders are endlessly measured. &ldquo;Winston Churchill&rsquo;s legacy is as enormous and as powerful as ever,&rdquo; says U.S. historian David Woolner, who worked on the digitization. </p>
  
    <p>Case in point: every month for the past decade, between 15,000 and 45,000 people have passed through the doors of London&rsquo;s Churchill War Rooms, the underground complex that served as Britain&rsquo;s Second World War command centre. On a recent afternoon, tourists shuffled through the dim hallways, pausing to peer at Churchill&rsquo;s old nightshirt or listen to a re-enactment of a telephone call between Churchill and U.S. president Harry Truman. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;My father was a soldier in the Second World War,&rdquo; said John Wilkinson, a visitor from Australia. &ldquo;He met Churchill once and said he was a great leader.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>Churchill was born in 1874, when the British Empire was still vast and proud. As was the aristocratic way, he was shipped off to boarding school at a young age by socialite parents who often ignored his pleading letters home. First elected to Parliament in 1900, Churchill was twice prime minister. He was much beloved. On his 90th birthday, he received 300,000 cards. After he died, more than 320,000 Britons passed by his coffin. In 2002, Churchill&rsquo;s name was resurrected in a BBC poll that declared him &ldquo;the greatest Briton of all time.&rdquo; (Darwin was No. 4; Shakespeare, 5.) </p>
  
    <p>The obsession is un&#64258;agging. Networks churn out Churchill biopics like Channel 4&rsquo;s recent <em>The Churchills</em>, or BBC&rsquo;s <em>Churchill&rsquo;s Desert War</em>. Historical tomes about the leader are published by the handful. The children&rsquo;s book <em>War Dogs: Churchill &amp; Rufus</em> is among dozens slated for publication in 2013. </p>
  
    <p>And he still weasels his way into headlines. Among recent stories: a bust of Churchill was unveiled in Jerusalem; Churchill&rsquo;s old Land Rover sold for $206,000; a new Churchill library will open in Washington. </p>
  
    <p>Recently, U.S. pundits and candidates made use of the deceased PM. &ldquo;It tugs at the heartstrings to remember the kind of example [set] by Winston Churchill,&rdquo; Mitt Romney mused last summer. That doesn&rsquo;t surprise Richard Toye, a historian at the University of Exeter. &ldquo;If, as a politician, you want to suggest that you are brilliant, one way to do that is to imply that you are like Churchill [and] that your opponents are like Neville Chamberlain.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>In this way, the Churchill legacy is as much about myth-making as about the man himself. But Woolner insists that raw greatness lends Churchill his perpetual relevance. &ldquo;The spring of 1940 was the pivotal point of the 20th century,&rdquo; he says. &ldquo;Britain was standing alone against the onslaught of the Nazi movement. Churchill rallied the world.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>What would Churchill have made of all this ogling? At the online archive&rsquo;s opening ceremony, grandson Nicholas Soames recounted an early memory. As a small boy he snuck into his grandfather&rsquo;s bedroom and found him reading in bed. &ldquo;Is it true you&rsquo;re the greatest living man, granddad?&rdquo; Soames inquired. To which Churchill replied: &ldquo;Yes. Now bugger off and leave me in peace.&rdquo;    </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Film</sections>
  
  <body.head>
    <hedline>The year in moving pictures</hedline>
  
    <abstract>From M to Pi, there&rsquo;s plenty of Oscar fodder on this year&rsquo;s top 10 list</abstract>
  
  <byline>Brian D. Johnson</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_TOP_TENMERGE.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>The standouts: Phoenix in The Master, Skyfall, Life of Pi, Chastain in Zero Dark Thirty, Day-Lewis in Lincoln and Foxx in Django Unchained</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>photo illustration by taylor shute</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Oh what a lovely war it was at the movies. There were battles for all ages&mdash;against alien invaders, Islamic fundamentalists, Ma&#64257;a vampires, Middle Earth orcs, Southern slave owners and rising floodwaters. Masked men ruled the box office in <em>The Avengers, The Dark Knight Rises</em> and <em>The Amazing Spider-Man</em>. But 2012 was also an exceptional year for heroic women and children. Naomi Watts braved a tsunami in <em>The Impossible</em>, Jessica Chastain hunted Osama bin Laden in <em>Zero Dark Thirty</em>, and as the crypt finally closed on the <em>Twilight</em> saga, Jennifer Lawrence unleashed a sharper fan-girl franchise with the twang of a bow in <em>The Hunger Games</em>. Kids who had never acted dominated the drowned bayou of <em>Beasts of the Southern Wild</em>, the shipwreck adventure of <em>Life of Pi</em>, the African killing fields of <em>Rebelle</em>, and the pup-tent puppy love of <em>Moonrise Kingdom</em>&mdash;all less juvenile than the comic-book blockbusters. </p>
  
    <p>Old folks got to shine in <em>Amour, Quartet </em>and <em>The Best Exotic Marigold Hotel</em>. Even James Bond came of age, as Hollywood showed hot flashes of maturity. Narrative puzzles such as <em>Stories We Tell, The Master, Holy Motors</em> and <em>Cloud Atlas</em> rocked our intelligence. In a U.S. election year, <em>Lincoln, Argo</em>, and the bin Laden film made backroom politics thrilling. And now we&rsquo;re looking at an Academy Award race of unusually smart, provocative and flat-out entertaining movies. Here are my favourites of 2012, including Oscar-qualified films that won&rsquo;t be released in Canada until the new year. </p>
  
    <p>1. <em>Zero Dark Thirty</em> Kathryn Bigelow (<em>The Hurt Locker</em>) turns the 10-year hunt for bin Laden into an electrifying procedural. From gruelling CIA torture scenes that will rattle liberal ethics to the jackpot commando raid, it&rsquo;s a visceral ride. As the mission&rsquo;s CIA mastermind, Chastain creates a heroine for the ages. </p>
  
    <p>2. <em>Stories We Tell</em> Canada&rsquo;s Sarah Polley unravels the secret of her birth in a stunning documentary portrait of a family from the inside out. With a seamless mix of interviews, archival footage and re-enactment, she composes her own genre of home movie. </p>
  
    <p>3. <em>The Master</em> Mining the life of Scientology founder L. Ron Hubbard, Paul Thomas Anderson forges a rhapsodic head trip on luxurious 70-mm &#64257;lm. Philip Seymour Hoffman and Joaquin Phoenix give a mano-a-mano master class in acting. </p>
  
    <p>4. <em>Django Unchained</em> Quentin Tarantino&rsquo;s slave-liberation spaghetti western is exhilarating. Rewiring the revenge fantasy of <em>Inglourious Basterds</em>, he flips Christoph Waltz from Nazi villain to anti-racist hero in a mash-up of familiar genres that&rsquo;s unlike anything we&rsquo;ve seen before. A perfect antidote to <em>Lincoln</em>. </p>
  
    <p>5. <em>Skyfall</em> Right in time for 007&rsquo;s golden anniversary, it&rsquo;s the best Bond movie ever, and may be the first to get Oscar nods for acting (Judi Dench, Javier Bardem). After nine nominations, Roger Deakins deserves to win for his gorgeous cinematography. </p>
  
    <p>6. <em>Amour</em> Michael Haneke won the Palme d&rsquo;Or in Cannes for this note-perfect chamber piece, starring Jean-Louis Trintignant and Emmanuelle Riva as retired music teachers facing mortality in their Paris apartment. </p>
  
    <p>7. <em>Life of Pi</em> Adapting Canadian author Yann Martel&rsquo;s bestseller, Ang Lee uses 3D computer graphics to create old-fashioned spectacle. The tiger is ferociously convincing, as is the movie&rsquo;s novice star, Suraj Sharma. </p>
  
    <p>8. <em>Lincoln</em> Once you strip away the lacquer of Steven Spielberg&rsquo;s sentimental framing, Tony Kushner&rsquo;s intricate script and Daniel Day-Lewis&rsquo;s filigreed performance transport us to an enthralling 19th-century Situation Room. </p>
  
    <p>9. <em>Beasts of the Southern Wild</em> Novice director Benh Zeitlin serves up a gumbo of raw v&eacute;rit&eacute; and mythic fantasy through the wide eyes of an intrepid six-year-old (Quvenzhan&eacute; Wallis) as she navigates a flooded post-Katrina land. </p>
  
    <p>10. <em>Silver Linings Playbook</em> David O. Russell (<em>The Fighter</em>) directs a killer off-kilter romantic comedy that has Jennifer Lawrence acting circles around Bradley Cooper. </p>
  
    <p>Movies I loved almost as much: <em>Rust and Bone, Moonrise Kingdom, The Impossible, Frankenweenie, Ai Weiwei: Never Sorry</em>. </p>
  
    <p>Biggest clunker:<em> The Hobbit</em>. Yes, it&rsquo;s even worse than<em> John Carter</em>.    </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Taste</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>A real chip off the old cracker </hedline>
  
    <abstract>The hybrid snack is marketed as healthy, but its calories are empty</abstract>
  
       <byline>Rosemary Counter</byline>

  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_CRACKERS02.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>Snack brackets: A product that appealed to women&rsquo;s perceptions of health and men&rsquo;s expectations of taste would be a marketer&rsquo;s dream come true</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>photograph by Jenna Marie Wakani </photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>While a rumpled man in his pajamas sneaks an afternoon snack, a young woman surprises him in the kitchen. &ldquo;Man, I really didn&rsquo;t think you&rsquo;d like those,&rdquo; she says, &ldquo;because they&rsquo;re crackers and they&rsquo;re good for you.&rdquo; The man shovels handfuls into his mouth, saying, &ldquo;They taste like chips.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>This so-called hybrid of chips and crackers, which Pepperidge Farm dubs &ldquo;the best of both snacks,&rdquo; is appearing on shelves just in time for the holiday season. Though pegged as an innovative new product, Cracker Chips already has stiff competition: Special K Cracker Chips launched in May; Kashi&rsquo;s Original 7 Grain Snack Crackers came out last year; and Christie&rsquo;s Crispers, the grandfather of the group after 21 years on supermarket shelves, is still going strong. </p>
  
    <p>The difference is that Crispers were never marketed as a healthy snack. &ldquo;Once you do the serving-size conversions, Crispers are about the same as chips in terms of calories and fat,&rdquo; explains Maria Thomas, a registered dietitian and nutritionist for Vancouver&rsquo;s Urban Nutrition. </p>
  
    <p>The new cracker chips do meet many people&rsquo;s criteria for healthy snacks because, while high in carbohydrates, they&rsquo;re low in calories, fat, sugar and sodium. &ldquo;When you look at the nutrition label, they&rsquo;re relatively low in everything, including nutrients,&rdquo; says Thomas. They have virtually no vitamins, negligible iron and protein, and little fibre. Empty calories like these can be a portion controller&rsquo;s nightmare. &ldquo;As soon as a product is touted as healthy, people tend to overindulge,&rdquo; she says. </p>
  
    <p>For someone who wants to satisfy a salt craving, cracker chips&mdash;available in flavours like barbecue and cheddar&mdash;might hit the spot. But selling snack foods to health nuts isn&rsquo;t easy. </p>
  
    <p>The answer may lie in where they&rsquo;re found on grocery shelves. Cracker chips are sold in the crackers aisle, not with the chips. More importantly, explains Jordan LeBel, a food and marketing professor at Concordia University in Montreal, they have crossed a perceived divide between junk food and nutrition. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Categorization isn&rsquo;t just a marketing thing, it&rsquo;s a psychological thing,&rdquo; he says. Our purchases are linked to our identity, which is increasingly concerned with living well. </p>
  
    <p>Since women, pegged by marketers as more health-conscious than men, are the primary grocery shoppers in about 70 per cent of households, it&rsquo;s no surprise they are targeted in ads. If, as the commercial suggests, women like crackers whereas men prefer chips, then appealing to women&rsquo;s perceptions of health and men&rsquo;s expectations of taste would be a marketing dream come true. &ldquo;The notion of crossover categories is one that marketers have explored time and time again,&rdquo; says LeBel, citing drinkable yogourt and roller shoes as success stories. &ldquo;Exploring a crossover category, or creating one, comes with risks and challenges. You need a big brand muscle to inform and educate the customer, and make sure they can reconcile it within their own categorization scheme. Basically, is it healthy or is it not?&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>In this case, healthy is a relative term. &ldquo;They&rsquo;re lower in fat than chips, and lower in carbs than cookies,&rdquo; says Natasha Turner, a Toronto naturopathic doctor and author of <em>The Carb Sensitivity Program</em>. But cracker chips are loaded with what Turner calls &ldquo;weird, unpronounceable ingredients&rdquo; like hydrogenated soybean oil, glucose-fructose and sodium metabisulphite. Even Turner&rsquo;s healthiest pick&mdash;the Kashi snack crackers&mdash;contain evaporated cane juice crystals, which is code for sugar. </p>
  
    <p>A better choice is the rice chip. &ldquo;They don&rsquo;t have vitamins or anything&mdash;some are just rice, sunflower oil and sea salt&mdash;but you can eat them with other things,&rdquo; says Turner, who suggests pairing them with lean protein like ricotta cheese, bean dip or hummus. After all, a well-rounded snack combines both carbs and protein.  </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m struggling with their use of the word &lsquo;healthy,&rsquo; &rdquo; Thomas says about cracker chips. &ldquo;If you&rsquo;re really looking for a healthy snack, have an apple.&rdquo;</p>
    
   
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Books</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>A Chinese comic-tragic masterpiece</hedline>
  
    <abstract>Plus the life of Joseph P. Kennedy, the Nazis&rsquo; culture wars, the private lives  of pharaohs, a new novel by Peter H&oslash;eg and the killing of Osama bin Laden</abstract>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_BOOKS07.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>&lsquo;Lenin&rsquo;s Kisses&rsquo;: <em>A complex, captivating novel that&rsquo;s destined to be read allegorically, as a blistering satire of Chinese capitalism</em></photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Berthold Steinhilber/laif/Redux</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <em>LENIN&rsquo;S KISSES </em>
  
    <p>Yan Lianke </p>
  
    <p>Pity the person asked to summarize Yan Lianke&rsquo;s epic, comic-tragic, uncategorizable novel set in modern-day China. But here goes: a freak summer blizzard befalls Liven, a bucolic, remote Chinese village that exists mostly off the government radar. With crops ruined, Liven&rsquo;s intrepid residents, who soldier on despite some form of physical disability, fall prey to a local bureaucrat&rsquo;s wacky money-making scheme. Needing funds to travel to Russia to buy Lenin&rsquo;s rotting corpse, then to install it in a Chinese mountaintop mausoleum as a tourist attraction, he persuades the people they&rsquo;ll be rewarded with untold riches if they put their disabilities on show. Thus is born the Shuang-huai County Special-Skills Performance Troupe, featuring Deafman Ma&rsquo;s &ldquo;firecrackers in the ears&rdquo; and Blind Tonghua&rsquo;s &ldquo;acute listening.&rdquo; Hilarity and heartbreak ensue, often simultaneously. </p>
  
    <p>That&rsquo;s but one of the intertwined plots driving this complex, captivating masterpiece. Given Lianke&rsquo;s acclaim, the book is destined to be read allegorically, as a blistering satire of Chinese capitalism. Certainly satiric references abound. A time-shifting narrative and digressive chapters echo <em>Tristram Shandy</em>. And Lianke&rsquo;s reliance on footnotes makes David Foster Wallace seem like a piker. Lianke only uses odd numbers, considered inauspicious in China; they serve as constant reminders of the country&rsquo;s invidious censorship. And that&rsquo;s not even getting to allusions to Tom Robbins and Jonathan Swift. </p>
  
    <p>But Lianke&rsquo;s lyrical prose, translated by Carlos Rojas, delivers a more profound meditation on the rank imperfections shared by all humans, no matter their physical fitness. In Liven, healthy people are &ldquo;wholers,&rdquo; a stunted girl is celebrated as a &ldquo;little nin.&rdquo;   </p>
  
    <p>Because Lianke is human himself, <em>Lenin&rsquo;s Kisses</em> is far from perfect. It can be repetitive. It&rsquo;s demanding. And Lianke&rsquo;s fondness for ribald, scatological humour is destined to elicit groans. But in 500 pages, he summons rare wonder: he manages to create a wretched, absurd and beautiful universe both brand- new and newly eternal.</p>
    
     <byline>Anne Kingston</byline>
 
  
    <em>THE PATRIARCH: THE REMARKABLE LIFE AND TURBULENT TIMES  OF JOSEPH P. KENNEDY </em>
  
    <p>David Nasaw </p>
  
    <p>Should we care about Joe Kennedy beyond the fact that he was the father of more famous men? Nasaw thinks so, telling us that &ldquo;had Joseph P. Kennedy not been the patriarch of America&rsquo;s first family, his story would be worth telling.&rdquo; Having already written biographies of other wealthy Americans such as William Randolph Hearst and Andrew Carnegie, Nasaw turns his attention to the story of a lifelong outsider. Kennedy made a fortune in the movie business but, &ldquo;as an Irish Catholic studio executive in Hollywood,&rdquo; he was the odd man out. In the FDR administration, he became known as a rogue ambassador for his attempts to prevent America from entering the Second World War. Yet he managed to raise a family of consummate political insiders. </p>
  
    <p>The Kennedy family asked Nasaw to write the book and gave him access to their archive of letters. But despite the family imprimatur, Nasaw doesn&rsquo;t whitewash Kennedy&rsquo;s &ldquo;paranoiac rage&rdquo; against the Jews (whom he blamed for the fallout from his attempts to appease Hitler) or his decision to have his daughter Rosemary lobotomized. But he does have a generally positive outlook on Kennedy, especially as a father: though the collapse of his own political career made him extremely ambitious for his sons&rsquo; future, he comes off as a loving, proud father. </p>
  
    <p>Still, the book suggests that while Kennedy was there when history was made, his achievements themselves aren&rsquo;t always exceptional; in Hollywood, his fortune came mainly from &ldquo;feeding the small-theatre audiences&rsquo; endless appetite for &lsquo;B&rsquo; features&rdquo;; in the FDR administration, he was a failure. We can feel Kennedy&rsquo;s last gasp of energy and enthusiasm when he helps John overcome anti-Catholic prejudice and win the presidency, and we have to agree with Nasaw that he &ldquo;had finally, through his son, accomplished all he had hoped for.&rdquo;</p>
    
     <byline>Jaime J. Weinman</byline>
 
  
    <em>INHUMANITIES: NAZI INTERPRETATIONS  OF WESTERN CULTURE </em>
  
    <p>David B. Dennis </p>
  
    <p>Most people are aware of what the Nazis hated: modern Western culture in general, especially ideals of religious and racial equality, and Jews, seen as the bacillus most responsible for spreading those toxic concepts, in particular. Less well understood is what the Hitlerites admired. The Nazis, or at least the true believers among them, did not see themselves as the murderous nihilists they were, but as defenders of &ldquo;true&rdquo;&mdash;meaning mystically transmitted by race and blood&mdash;Western art and culture. They didn&rsquo;t just have their cultural enemies&mdash;Sigmund Freud, say, who combined Jewish ancestry with repulsive ideas&mdash;but their cultural heroes, too, most notably Hitler&rsquo;s idol, anti-Semitic composer Richard Wagner. </p>
  
    <p>Dennis, a historian at Loyola University in Chicago, examined two decades of cultural war as waged by Nazi theorists in their party&rsquo;s official newspaper, the <em>V&ouml;lkischer Beobachter</em>. A lot of what he found, were it the product of basement-dwelling Internet cranks rather than men about to unleash a tide of unparalleled barbarism, would be comic. </p>
  
    <p>Take the case of Beethoven, whom&mdash;to Hitler&rsquo;s disgust&mdash;the vast majority of Germans revered far more than Wagner. He was German, all right, but his father was a severe alcoholic and, according to Nazi social policy, should have been sterilized long before he begat Ludwig. Not to worry, Nazi Beethoven devotees, wrote Bonn professor Ludwig Schiedermair. If Johann van Beethoven &ldquo;gladly drank wine and punch and once in a while offered girls little kisses in jest,&rdquo; it was only because he was from the alcohol-loving Rhineland, where they understood that sort of zesty living. Foreigners, annoyingly enough, had to be admitted to the pantheon if enough Germans admired them. It helped, of course, if there was any record of anti-Semitic remarks on an outsider&rsquo;s part: <em>The Merchant of Venice</em>, far more than <em>Hamlet</em>, brought Shakespeare into the fold. </p>
  
    <p>In the end, though, what Dennis found was not comic at all: a long and depressingly successful campaign to convince Germans the Third Reich was the purification of Western civilization, not its antithesis.</p>
    
     <byline>Brian Bethune</byline>
  
  
    <em>THE PHARAOH: LIFE AT  COURT AND ON CAMPAIGN </em>
  
    <p>Garry Shaw </p>
  
    <p>Everyone knows about pharaohs, at least in their role as semi-divine icons of an ancient civilization. The subject of this thoroughly engaging tome, though, is their little-known daily lives&mdash;what Egypt&rsquo;s kings got up to when they weren&rsquo;t planning a new pyramid or chasing escaped slaves into the Red Sea. Official documents, often carved in stone, record: how the kings rose in the morning, and were ceremonially washed and dressed before attending meetings with officials; their role in law cases; and their evening entertainments. But where Shaw really charms is with the hints of private lives unearthed by two centuries of Egyptology. </p>
  
    <p>He starts at the beginning, describing the specially constructed birthing chambers where expectant royal mothers, surrounded by chanting priests and physicians, squatted on two bricks while drinking beer to ease their labour pains. Then there&rsquo;s life in the royal nursery, shared with numerous siblings, half-siblings and the children of royal servants, high and low. In some dynasties, princes were as liable to grow up with future fan-bearers as with future high priests: the practice maximized the opportunity to instill early bonds of loyalty in anyone who would later enjoy physical proximity to the pharaoh. </p>
  
    <p>Those ties could last a lifetime. Pharaoh Amenhotep II (1424 to 1398 BCE) sent a letter to his childhood friend, Useratet, now stationed far to the south as viceroy of Kush, telling him how much he had missed him during that day&rsquo;s festival, when everyone at court had been &ldquo;eating, drinking and making holiday.&rdquo; Or so scholars believe Amenhotep is trying to say; the text is so difficult to follow, some think the king was actually drunk when he wrote it. That would be a lovely human touch, colouring a life so remote from our own. It&rsquo;s matched only by a greyhound, Abutiu, dead for over 4,000 years, whose name is preserved only because of the tomb built for him by his master, an unidentified pharaoh. Not so god-like after all: guys who loved their beer and their dogs.</p>
    
     <byline>Brian Bethune</byline>
  
  
    <em>THE ELEPHANT  KEEPERS&rsquo; CHILDREN  </em>
  
    <p>Peter H&oslash;eg </p>
  
    <p>The narrator of this rollicking novel by the author of <em>Smilla&rsquo;s Sense of Snow</em> opens the book with a promise. &ldquo;I have found a door out of the prison,&rdquo; declares 14-year-old Peter Fin&oslash;. &ldquo;I am writing this to show you that door.&rdquo; He speaks of escaping our hidden desires, the &ldquo;elephants&rdquo; we carry around that we keep secret from others&mdash;a yearning to be the world&rsquo;s best soccer player, to never have anyone in your family change. Before revealing the path to the door, Peter recounts a lengthy caper in which he and his older sister, Tilte, are chased around their idyllic (and fictional) island home of Fin&oslash; and through the streets of Copenhagen by a stern bishop and a wayward psychologist who want to place them in state custody: their father, a God-doubting vicar, and mother, a mechanics-obsessed organist, have disappeared.  </p>
  
    <p>Along the way, Peter and Tilte reach out to friends with such names as Polly Pigonia and Leonora Ticklepalate and trick their meddling principal into believing he sees the dead.  </p>
  
    <p>The plot takes unnecessary detours and there are too many characters to count, but Peter is delightful. His worship of Tilte is near total&mdash;though he hasn&rsquo;t quite forgiven her for helping his nemesis, Karl Marauder, lure him onstage for a soccer trophy, only to find himself a half-naked contestant in the island&rsquo;s annual &ldquo;Mr. Fin&oslash; contest.&rdquo; And what an eye for detail: when a pursuer is able to gain ground after being hit in the face with a layer cake, Peter surmises the base &ldquo;must have involved some kind of walnut meringue.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Existential, farcical, slapstick&mdash;whatever the word for H&oslash;eg&rsquo;s latest offering, it captures a truth adults often forget: life is at once ridiculous and beautiful, full of meaning and so much nonsense. </p>
    
    <byline>Dafna Izenberg</byline>
 
  
    <em>THE FINISH: THE KILLING  OF OSAMA BIN LADEN </em>
  
    <p>Mark Bowden </p>
  
    <p>The killing of bin Laden by an American Navy SEAL commando team seems like a topic well-suited for author Mark Bowden, whose previous books have tackled the 1993 &ldquo;Black Hawk Down&rdquo; gunfight in Somalia, and the Iran hostage crisis. But while Bowden&rsquo;s Somalia story bursts with action, and his book on Iran is rich and detailed, this one feels thin. Part of this can&rsquo;t be blamed on Bowden. Members of the SEAL team on the raid wouldn&rsquo;t talk to him, which gives Bowden&rsquo;s account of the final assault on bin Laden&rsquo;s compound in Pakistan a dull gloss. It also forces Bowden to focus the bulk of his attention on the long hunt for bin Laden, and the political decisions surrounding the raid, and here Bowden is stronger. </p>
  
    <p>He opens his narrative in Iraq. A special-forces unit hitting a suspected al-Qaeda target found a treasure load of information: names, photos, travel documents, even expense reports for phone cards. This wasn&rsquo;t the breakthrough that directly led to bin Laden&rsquo;s discovery. But Bowden uses it to illustrate how America&rsquo;s counterterrorism capacities have evolved since 9/11. Every scrap of data is stored on supercomputers that can find links between fragments that would otherwise go undetected. </p>
  
    <p>American military and security agencies have learned to respond to this intelligence with speed and force. Bill McRaven, then-commander of Joint Special Operations Command, was unfazed when told where bin Laden might be hiding. His men had perfected their skills on thousands of similar missions. </p>
  
    <p>The administration of President Barack Obama claims torture wasn&rsquo;t a factor in finding bin Laden. Bowden says this isn&rsquo;t true. Bin Laden&rsquo;s courier, a man known by the pseudonym Abu Ahmed al-Kuwaiti, was a key figure in the hunt. He was first mentioned by two al-Qaeda operatives subjected to coercive interrogation methods. Bowden says one was &ldquo;probably&rdquo; tortured; the other suffered treatment at Guant&aacute;namo that &ldquo;would be described as torture by any disinterested person.&rdquo; The third person to mention Kuwaiti was 9/11 architect Khalid Sheikh Mohammed. He was waterboarded 183 times.</p>
    
     <byline>Michael Petrou</byline>
  
 
 
 
    <hedline>MACLEAN&rsquo;S BESTSELLERS</hedline>
    
   <em>Compiled by Brian Bethune</em>
 
    <em>		FICTION </em>
    <p>	1.	DEAR LIFE&#8197;<em>Alice Munro</em> 	2 (9)  </p>
  
    <p>	2.	419&#8197;<em>Will Ferguson</em>	1 (8) </p>
  
    <p>	3.	THE PURCHASE3 (6) 		<em>Linda Spalding</em>
    </p>
   <p>	4.	A WEEK IN WINTER4 (4) 		<em>Maeve Binchy</em>
    </p>
   <p>	5.	THE CASUAL VACANCY 6 (11) 		<em>J.K. Rowling</em> </p>
   <p>	6.	SWEET TOOTH&#8197;<em>Ian McEwan</em>10 (15) </p>
  
    <p>	7.	FLIGHT BEHAVIOR8 (3) 		<em>Barbara Kingsolver</em>
    </p>
   	<p>8.	REVENGE OF THE VINYL CAFE7 (9) 		<em>Stuart McLean</em>
    </p>
   <p>	9.	THE BLACK BOX&#8197;<em>Michael Connelly</em>5 (2) </p>
  
    <p>	10.	THE RACKETEER&#8197;<em>John Grisham</em>9 (7) </p>
  
    <em>		NON-FICTION </em>
    <p>	1.	THE INCONVENIENT INDIAN1 (4) 		<em>Thomas King</em>
    </p>
   <p>	2.	ASSHOLES: A THEORY 9 (6) 		<em>Aaron James</em>
    </p>
   <p>	3.	I&rsquo;M YOUR MAN 2 (8) 		<em>Sylvie Simmons</em>
    </p>
   <p>	4.	WAGING HEAVY PEACE4 (11) 		<em>Neil Young</em>
    </p>
   <p>	5.	1982&#8197;<em>Jian Ghomeshi</em>3 (13) </p>
  
    <p>	6.	HALLUCINATIONS&#8197;<em>Oliver Sacks</em> (1) </p>
  
    <p>	7.	THE LAST LION5 (6) 		<em>William Manchester and Paul Reid</em>
    </p>
   <p>	8.	PATRICK LEIGH FERMOR6 (2) 		<em>Artemis Cooper</em>
    </p>
   <p>	9.	IRON CURTAIN(1) 		<em>Anne Applebaum</em> </p>
   <p>	10.	THE PATRIARCH&#8197;<em>David Nasaw</em>10 (3) </p>
  	<p>LAST WEEK (WEEKS ON LIST) </p>
  
    <em>ON THE WEB: Visit our Bookmarked blog for news and reviews on all things literary at macleans.ca/books</em>
    
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Bazaar</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
    <hedline>A lunch affair with shopping </hedline>
  
    <abstract>Female multitaskers are taking online buying to new office heights</abstract>
  
        <byline>Rebecca Eckler</byline>

  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_ONLINE_SHOPPING01.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>On your own time: Employees are more productive when bosses trust them with &lsquo;a little space&rsquo; in their day to shop online, says one HR consultant</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>photograph by Jessica Darmanin</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Technology hasn&rsquo;t just changed the way the world works&mdash;it has changed the way people lunch. Noon hour is no longer a time to get out of the office and grab a bite with friends, because it&rsquo;s now an excuse to stay in, eat at your desk&mdash;and shop. </p>
  
    <p>Janice Bereskin discovered lunchtime shopping a few years ago. &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t skip lunch, but I combine eating and shopping all within my lunch break,&rdquo; says the Toronto lawyer. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;I can shop for myself, the kids, and talk on the phone all at the same time. It&rsquo;s so much more efficient than walking to a mall and going store to store.&rdquo; Not only that, she avoids &ldquo;pushy salespeople,&rdquo; and says it gives her a boost. &ldquo;And you know there will be another boost when the package arrives. It feels like you&rsquo;ve received a present, even though you paid for it and knew it was coming.&rdquo; Recent purchases include a Smythe blazer and Rebecca Taylor top from<em> eLuxe.ca</em>. </p>
  
    <p>A little more than a year after it launched, eLuxe is a fashionistas&rsquo; go-to for its deals on designer clothes. Founder Joanna Track thought the site would be busy at night when people have more downtime, so she was &ldquo;surprised that there was so much activity at lunch time.&rdquo; She noticed a spike in traffic between noon and 2 p.m. Now online retailers like her offer two-hour &ldquo;stop, drop and shop&rdquo; promotions during that early-afternoon window. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s been tremendously successful,&rdquo; says Track, who rarely shops at conventional retail stores anymore. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Everyone&rsquo;s time is so stretched these days. Online shopping allows women to get their retail therapy in without leaving their desk,&rdquo; Track notes. Being able to eat your lunch at the same time is a bonus. &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t try that in a store,&rdquo; Track says, laughing. </p>
  
    <p>Don&rsquo;t have an office? You can shop from your smartphone or tablet, although most companies don&rsquo;t frown on an online buying spree as long as it&rsquo;s on your own time, says Sari Friedman, a Toronto human-resources consultant and career coach. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;Most companies are not shutting down even Facebook because they realize that this is a social-media world and that can actually help their business, as long as their productivity isn&rsquo;t going down.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Besides, businesses should have a corporate climate that radiates trust, not suspicion. &ldquo;I&rsquo;m not saying everyone should be trusted, but if they are on their lunch hour and are shopping it can actually be beneficial. They are not leaving work early, let&rsquo;s say, to line up in a parking lot just before Christmas so they can shop.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Since it is indeed that most wonderful time of the year, shopping during work hours is attractive to people who want to avoid the inevitable crowds, parking madness, and huge queues at the cash register. Friedman believes employees are more productive when they have &ldquo;a little space&rdquo; to go online. &ldquo;If it&rsquo;s their lunch hour, it&rsquo;s their time. I still think that people should go out and get some air.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>The lunchtime shopper has to be focused, however. &ldquo;There is no time for distractions,&rdquo; says Nancy Pavela, marketing director at Jackman Reinvention Inc., a Toronto retail consulting firm. &ldquo;Who doesn&rsquo;t love the feeling of getting something for yourself or getting something done? It&rsquo;s kind of like that feeling you get when you go to the gym in the morning. And I don&rsquo;t have to put on a coat.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>The immediacy of the online deal can be problematic for those who are trying to rein in their spending, says Richard Dunwoody, executive director of Licensed Credit Professionals Canada, a non-pro&#64257;t organization focused on personal finance education. He suggests postponing your lunchtime order and reviewing later at home. &ldquo;This double-check allows you to rethink your purchase order and decide if you need it.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>But Dara Fleischer, who runs the blog <em>Fashion Junkie</em>, loves the instant gratification. She is so addicted to online shopping, she recently received something she swears she didn&rsquo;t mean to buy. &ldquo;I think it&rsquo;s like sleepwalking, but &lsquo;sleep-shopping.&rsquo; &rdquo; The New York shopaholic does the most damage on designer-clothing mecca <em>Shopbop.com</em>. &ldquo;They just make it so easy. And you can return anything in two seconds.&rdquo; </p>
  
 
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>Feschuk</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>The most popular jobs in Bethlehem</hedline>
  
  <abstract>And other truths revealed by the songs of the Christmas season</abstract>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <byline>Scott Feschuk</byline>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_FESCHUKMERGE1.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.caption>&lsquo;Christmas will never go away&rsquo;: Bryan Adams&rsquo; terrible tune keeps coming back every year, like a Christmas zombie sent to devour our good cheer</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Photo illustration by Taylor Shute</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>To aid in your enjoyment of the holidays, please consult this second volume of answers to frequently asked questions about the songs of the season&mdash;all from someone who, until he was 17, thought<em> Silent Night</em> described Mary as a &ldquo;round young virgin.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>Q: I need closure. Does that pushy fellow wind up scoring with the woman in <em>Baby, It&rsquo;s Cold Outside?</em> </p>
  
    <p>A: Ask anyone who&rsquo;s listened closely to the lyrics of this song: nothing captures the spirit of the holiday season like a man pressuring a pretty lady to get drunk enough to make out with him. As any lawyer will tell you, it&rsquo;s not sexual harassment if it rhymes. To get a sense of how the song&rsquo;s conflict is resolved, one must refer to its long-lost concluding verses: </p>
  
    <p>I&rsquo;m leaving this place </p>
  
    <p><em>Baby, you&rsquo;ll take my heart </em></p>
  
    <p>Stop licking my face </p>
  
    <p><em>Baby, you&rsquo;ll break my heart </em></p>
  
    <p>I wish I knew where you hid my boots </p>
  
    <p><em>Here&rsquo;s one more shot of Absolut! </em></p>
  
 
  
    <p>I&rsquo;m asking you to give it a rest </p>
  
    <p><em>Can I put my hand on your breast? </em></p>
  
    <p>Did I tell you that my brother&rsquo;s a cop? </p>
  
    <p><em>Let me walk you to your bus stop! </em></p>
  
    <p><em>And give you a handshake</em> </p>
  
    <p>Baby, it&rsquo;s cold outside! </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Which are the most popular reindeer games?</em> </p>
  
    <p>A: In order: Rutting, herding females and Scattergories. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: Whatever happened to that kid who saw his mother kissing Santa Claus?</em> </p>
  
    <p>A: He sends an update: &ldquo;You want to know about that night? It scarred me, man. Sure, I wrote a jaunty carol about it, but I know now that I was in shock at the time. I mean&mdash;that&rsquo;s my mother we&rsquo;re talking about, okay? Let&rsquo;s just say there were a lot of con&#64258;icting emotions. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;On one hand, I was so excited to finally see him&mdash;Santa Claus in the flesh! And he&rsquo;d brought me the two-wheeler I&rsquo;d asked for! But then&mdash;oh, God, I can still picture their tongues. I was young at the time, so part of me was like, &lsquo;How does Santa have time for this? Doesn&rsquo;t he need to get to my friend Gary&rsquo;s house?&rsquo; But then it sank in: my mother was making it with a magical man from the North. Mommy, the Christmas floozy. I could never bring myself to ride that bike. I ended up trading it for my first pack of cigarettes. </p>
  
    <p>&ldquo;The following Christmas, my mother insisted on taking me to the mall to see Santa. I remember climbing on his lap. I remember the rage coursing through my body. Next thing I know, three mall cops are dragging me off Saint Nick, my hands still tightly gripping thick tufts of white beard hair. So, yeah, I guess I&rsquo;m still getting over having seen Mommy kissing Santa Claus. And that&rsquo;s just the beginning: I haven&rsquo;t even begun to process what I saw her doing to the Easter Bunny.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: To judge from carols, what were the most popular jobs in Bethlehem of yore? </em></p>
  
    <p>A: 1) Shepherd. 2) Bell ringer. 3) Cow. 4) Drummer (boys only). 5) Messiah. </p>
  
    <p><em>Q: If I could travel back in time just once, would it be wrong for me to eschew killing Hitler in favour of tying Bryan Adams to a chair until he loses the urge to record the song that goes &ldquo;Something about Christmas time&rdquo;? </em></p>
  
    <p>A: I&rsquo;ll allow it. Most terrible songs have the decency to vanish to the obscurity of classic-rock radio and vans with a wizard painted on the side. But this tune keeps coming back every year, like a Christmas zombie sent to devour our good cheer. Besides which, having Christmas every day would devastate corporate profits, plunge our country into recession and render us a nation of gravy-swilling fatties. So thanks for trying to destroy Canada with your stupid wish, Bryan Adams. Here&rsquo;s a true story: I heard this song in a grocery store on Nov. 14. I was alone in the soda aisle apart from one employee, who was stocking shelves. Our eyes met. He gestured upward, to the speakers, and just as the chorus began for roughly the 47th time he said: &ldquo;This song makes me want to hang myself with tinsel.&rdquo; Happy holidays, everyone!</p>
  
  
    <p>My new ebook, <em>Feschuk on the Holidays</em> &mdash;which features the first volume of Christmas song FAQs and much more&mdash;is now on iTunes and is also available for the Kobo and the Kindle</p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <body.head>
  
  <hedline>Now Available:  Feschuk on the holidays</hedline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>How exactly does Santa  	know when you&rsquo;re sleeping? Who was that clattering on  	the roof in &rsquo;Twas the Night  	Before Thursday? And what&rsquo;s  	with the brightness of these  	stars? (A bit garish, really.)  </p>
  
    <p>Our inimitable columnist on the songs, the rituals, the secrets and scandals of  	the Retail Festival Formerly Known as Christmas</p>
    
   <em>Get it wherever ebooks  	are sold </em> 
   
   </body.content>
  
</body>
<body>
 
  <sections>The end</sections>
  
  <body.head>
  
   <hedline>Albert Lisacek, 1933-2012</hedline>
  
    <abstract>Canada&rsquo;s &lsquo;toughest cop,&rsquo; he took on some of Montreal&rsquo;s most  notorious thugs, once shooting the testicles off a thief</abstract>
  
  <byline>Emily Senger with Kate Lunau</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file://images/MAC52_THE_ENDMERGE.jpg"></photo>
  
  <photo.byline>Illustration by Team Macho</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
  
    <p>Albert Lisacek was born on July 13, 1933, in Montreal&rsquo;s multicultural Mile End neighbourhood, in a two-bedroom rental apartment. His parents, Mary and Joseph, had immigrated to Canada from the former Czechoslovakia in 1927. Albert&rsquo;s five-foot-eleven mother gave birth to three more boys&mdash;all of them at home. His father, who had been a strongman in a Slovenian circus, later worked in Montreal&rsquo;s shipyards and as a night watchman.  </p>
  
    <p>Albert, a serious child who loved western novels, had to fight off bullies in their tough immigrant neighbourhood. When he was 15, five teens confronted him on a Mount Royal trail. He took off, the teens in hot pursuit. Running down Park Avenue, he pounded on the door of an elderly woman who let him hide out until the teens went away. Albert never wanted to feel so helpless again. That day, he decided he would become a police officer. He began spending hours in a basement gym. By age 20, he stood six foot two, weighed 250 lb. and was a formidable force as a part-time bouncer at a Saint Catherine Street nightclub.  </p>
  
    <p>When he was 23, Albert applied to the S&ucirc;ret&eacute; du Qu&eacute;bec (SQ). The hulking young man was hired on the spot, assigned to a post guarding cells at SQ headquarters. When an inmate in a cell of eight hurled an insult at him, Albert entered and locked the door, smacking three men with his big hand before the fourth in line identified the culprit. Criminals began calling the new hire &ldquo;Dirty Albert&rdquo; and &ldquo;<em>le chien</em>&rdquo; (the dog). To co-workers, he was &ldquo;Little Albert,&rdquo; and later, when he shaved his head, &ldquo;Kojak,&rdquo; after TV&rsquo;s tough and incorruptible cop.  </p>
  
    <p>He married Claudia in 1960. They didn&rsquo;t have children, but rarely took out their pink-finned Cadillac without their three dogs: Teppy, a schnauzer, Cheetah, a 160-lb. mastiff, and Radar, a mutt.  </p>
  
    <p>In 1961, Albert was promoted to detective. &ldquo;I was good at getting rid of the bad people,&rdquo; he told journalist Warren Perley. The SQ&rsquo;s so-called &ldquo;holdup squad&rdquo; came calling&mdash;the team that responded to armed robberies. He was soon breaking down doors, his Thompson submachine gun always in hand. Before a raid, Albert would pray: &ldquo;I hope to hell this isn&rsquo;t my last time.&rdquo; </p>
  
    <p>By then, death threats had grown routine. Albert took on some of Montreal&rsquo;s most notorious gangsters and thugs, including Richard &ldquo;the Cat&rdquo; Blass, who&rsquo;d survived four assassination attempts and escaped prison three times. In 1969, Blass was arrested for a bank robbery in Sherbrooke, Que. Albert was assigned to escort him to court. During the drive to the courthouse, Blass bragged that his buddies were planning to hold up the police van to bust him out. &ldquo;First thing I&rsquo;ll do is blow your head off,&rdquo; Albert shot back. During a break in the trial, a man leaned too far over the defendant&rsquo;s table. Albert, fearing he might pass Blass a gun, pulled him from the room and smashed his face into an elevator door, breaking his nose in a bloody mess. </p>
  
    <p>On March 19, 1972,<em> The Canadian Magazin</em>e named him &ldquo;Canada&rsquo;s toughest cop.&rdquo; If ever there were a doubt, Albert proved it six months later, when he shot the testicles off a thief who was fleeing a robbery in the Montreal suburb of Verdun.  </p>
  
    <p>Albert&rsquo;s next run-in with Blass came on Jan. 21, 1975. Blass, who had escaped from prison a &#64257;nal time, locked 13 people in a beer-storage room in Montreal&rsquo;s Gargantua Bar and lit it on fire. All 13 died. Three days later, Albert and a team of officers tailed Blass to Val-David, north of Montreal, and surrounded him. Albert and two other officers barged in; Blass, who was unarmed, was shot 27 times. Albert didn&rsquo;t shoot him. &ldquo;I would have preferred to bring Blass in alive,&rdquo; Albert told journalist Perley. </p>
  
    <p>SQ brass, tired of dealing with headlines and negative press surrounding Albert&rsquo;s exploits, moved him to a desk job. In 1981, at age 48, he took early retirement. Years of kicking down doors and chasing bad guys had taken their toll. His knees bothered him, and he had trouble getting around. Albert liked collecting John Wayne memorabilia and watching action movies on TV. Claudia died in 1999 and Albert married Jacqueline Richer, a cousin by marriage, calling her &ldquo;<em>mon ange</em>,&rdquo; and &ldquo;ma ch&eacute;rie.&rdquo; The couple moved to the country north of Montreal, where Albert&rsquo;s softer side emerged. &ldquo;He had a very tender heart,&rdquo; says Richer. &ldquo;When he saw there was no justice, he wanted to make justice.&rdquo;  </p>
  
    <p>On Nov. 1, Albert was diagnosed with colon cancer. Canada&rsquo;s toughest cop, who&rsquo;d hunted down some of the country&rsquo;s most dangerous criminals, passed away quietly three weeks later, on Nov. 20. He was 79.  </p>
  
  </body.content>
  
</body>

</catalog>