<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf
 SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN" change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" id="art-158632005"> <head><title></title>
 <meta name="Author" content="Nick Taylor-Vaisey"/>
 <meta name="Editor" content=""/>
<meta name="PublisherName" content="Maclean's"/>
 <meta name="Subject1" content="Putting a value on hockey loyalty "/>
 <meta name="Subject2" content="To woo fans back, some NHL teams dug a lot deeper than others"/>
 <meta name="Subject3" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject4" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject5" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <tobject/>
 <docdata>
 <correction/>
 <doc-id/>
 <date.issue norm="20130204" />
 <date.release norm= "20130123" />
 <date.expire/>
 <doc-scope/>
 <series/>
 <key-list/>
</docdata>
	 
 <pubdata date.publication="20130204" name="Maclean's" number="04" volume="126" edition.area="" position.section="National" position.sequence="22" />
 <revision-history/>
</head>
<body>
 <body.head>
 <slug>Hockey </slug>
 <hedline>Putting a value on hockey loyalty </hedline>
  <byline>Nick Taylor-Vaisey</byline>
 <abstract>To woo fans back, some NHL teams dug a lot deeper than others</abstract>
 </body.head>

 <body.content>
 <p>In the days after the NHL lockout ended, teams rushed to offer special deals to fans to make amends. If the euphoria on display last week was any indication, much has been forgiven. But if teams truly want to satisfy fans after the protracted dispute, opening night giveaways won’t go far enough, says a sports marketer and former hockey executive. Cary Kaplan, the president of Cosmos Sports and a former executive with the Hamilton Bulldogs hockey team, says the flurry of discounts were an important gesture, but won’t provide the “sustained change” fans deserve after so many months of being deprived of the game. </p>
 
 <p>Players should be front and centre in that effort, says Kaplan. They should call season-ticket holders to thank them for their loyalty, or do more for fans on game days. “Why doesn’t every player sign autographs after every game? Why isn’t that mandatory?” he asks. “Kids don’t want free popcorn. They want to meet Phil Kessel. That’s the power these players and leagues and teams have.” </p>
 
 <p>Still, Kaplan admits the discounts didn’t hurt. Of the teams that reportedly offered freebies, <em>Maclean’s</em> looked at how much they were potentially willing to put on the line for their first home game, relative to their team salaries (see graphic, right). For instance, if every Carolina Hurricanes fan took advantage of the savings offered on opening night—half off tickets and merchandise, cheap food and drink—the team would have given up an estimated $2 million in revenue. That amounts to about three times what it paid its players for the night’s work. Five of the 10 most generous teams were in Canadian cities, while Winnipeg and Toronto were further down the list. </p>
 
 <p>On the eve of the NHL’s shortened season, one in four Canadian hockey fans told a Harris-Decima poll they’d watch the pros less this year. It will take more than cheap hot dogs to win them all back.
 </p>
 </body.content>
</body></nitf>
