<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf
 SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN" change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" id="art-158632005"> <head><title></title>
 <meta name="Author" content="Luiza Ch. Savage"/>
 <meta name="Editor" content=""/>
<meta name="PublisherName" content="Maclean's"/>
 <meta name="Subject1" content="‘We are made for this moment, and we will seize it’ "/>
 <meta name="Subject2" content="Pomp, emotion and a day of celebration in Washington"/>
 <meta name="Subject3" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject4" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject5" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <tobject/>
 <docdata>
 <correction/>
 <doc-id/>
 <date.issue norm="20130204" />
 <date.release norm= "20130123" />
 <date.expire/>
 <doc-scope/>
 <series/>
 <key-list/>
</docdata>
	 
 <pubdata date.publication="20130204" name="Maclean's" number="04" volume="126" edition.area="" position.section="International" position.sequence="30" />
 <revision-history/>
</head>
<body>
 <sections>International</sections>
 <body.head>
 <slug>UNITED STATES </slug>
 <hedline>'We are made for this moment, and we will seize it' </hedline>
 <abstract>Pomp, emotion and a day of celebration in Washington</abstract>
 <byline>LUIZA CH. SAVAGE</byline>
 </body.head>
 <photo href="file://images/MAC04_PHOTOESSAY05.jpg"/>
 <photo.caption>Take a bow: The Obamas danced to Let’s Stay Together, performed by Jennifer Hudson</photo.caption>
 <photo.byline>Charles Dharapak/CP Images</photo.byline>
 <body.content>
 <p>As he was about to leave the Capitol podium after taking his oath for a second term as President of the United States this week, Barack Obama lingered. “I want to take a look, one more time,” he said, turning and gazing at the estimated 800,000 supporters crowded into the chill-swept National Mall. “I’m not going to see this again.” Roughly half as many people as four years ago endured hours in the cold to witness the ceremony that once again delivered a memorable mix of civics, prayer and celebrity—including an invocation delivered by the widow of a slain civil rights leader and an anthem by pop icon Beyoncé. </p>
 
 <p>But this time, jubilation gave way to determination. A battle-hardened Obama, facing a divided Congress, used his second inaugural address to rebuke an ideology of individualism and small government, and to press a liberal agenda. Bracing for budget battles with Republicans, Obama defended social programs: “They do not make us a nation of takers; they free us to take the risks that make this country great.” He pledged forcefully to “respond to the threat of climate change.” And, in an equality-themed speech, he placed the cause of same-sex marriage among the great American civil rights struggles. “For if we are truly created equal, then surely the love we commit to one another must be equal as well.” Yet he cautioned supporters not to be discouraged by “partial” victories. “We must act, knowing that our work will be imperfect,” he said. Later, it was off to a parade and star-studded balls, where he slow-danced with the first lady, clad in a ruby-red Jason Wu gown, while Jennifer Hudson crooned <em>Let’s Stay Together</em>, as if echoing the message of the day. 
 </p>
 </body.content>
</body></nitf>
