<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf
 SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN" change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" id="art-158632005"> <head><title></title>
 <meta name="Author" content=""/>
 <meta name="Editor" content=""/>
<meta name="PublisherName" content="Maclean's"/>
 <meta name="Subject1" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject2" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject3" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject4" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject5" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <tobject/>
 <docdata>
 <correction/>
 <doc-id/>
 <date.issue norm="20130204" />
 <date.release norm= "20130123" />
 <date.expire/>
 <doc-scope/>
 <series/>
 <key-list/>
</docdata>
	 
 <pubdata date.publication="20130204" name="Maclean's" number="04" volume="126" edition.area="" position.section="Business" position.sequence="44" />
 <revision-history/>
</head>
<body>

  <sections>Business</sections>
  <body.head>
   
  </body.head>
  

  <body.content>
    <p>Flu season is a miserable time of dizzying nausea and hacking coughs for millions across North America. But for some companies, it’s also an opportune time for sales. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>Kimberly-Clark, the maker of Kleenex brand tissues, has seen a net jump in its stock price in nine of the past 12 flu seasons (October-March), and is on pace to do it again this year. Its stock sits at $86.33 per share, up from $85.99 in October with peak flu season just around the corner. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>Kleenex controls roughly 45 per cent of the approximately $1.5-billion tissue market, but saw its share slip last year as store brands made small gains. Recently, Kleenex has made a marketing push for what it calls its “sneeze shield” tissues, which are coated to prevent mucus from getting to the hands, and its antiviral tissues. These anti-flu tissues don’t come cheap. Sneeze shield tissues cost $3.99 for a box of 120. The antiviral tissues are $4.29 for a box of 68, or an incredible 12 times the cost of a run-of-the-mill box of Royale tissues at $0.69 for a box of 132. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>While the fancy Kleenex packaging promises to reduce the spread of germs and kill up to 99.9 per cent of cold and flu viruses, it may not be worth the extra cost, say health experts. A 1988 study suggested that Kleenex may be taking advantage of consumers’ flu fears. Researchers found that antiviral tissues are only slightly more effective than standard tissues and about the same as handwashing with soap when it comes to preventing the spread of colds and flu. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>Some doctors are also concerned that the promises on the packaging can lead buyers to put off vaccinations, thinking they’re protected, when the product does more after the virus takes hold than it does for prevention. The U.S. Centers for Disease Control says that tissues can be helpful—if they catch the cough or sneeze—but that “vaccination and strong handwashing and hygiene practices” are still the best ways to prevent flu. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>So next time you’re at the pharmacy this flu season, it might be better to save your money and go with a bottle of soap instead. <byline>RYAN MALLOUGH</byline>
    </p>
    
    
     <slug>Real estate</slug> <p>Realtors get it wrong</p>

    <p>Everyone is watching Canada’s sputtering housing market these days. Is it the beginning of a crash, or a much-hoped-for soft landing? Every piece of new data is thrust under the microscope. But if you happen to live in Canada’s largest city, you should view the monthly sales figures served up by the Toronto Real Estate Board with an extra-critical eye.  </p>
    
    
    
    <p>Last week, the board issued a hopeful-sounding press release. After several months of falling sales—down 20 per cent in December—it said the first two weeks of January suggested a mood shift. Sales were up 2.4 per cent to 1,469, compared to the 1,435 reported a year earlier. Prices were up, too—by four per cent, to an average of $459,728 across the Greater Toronto Area, or GTA. “The new year started off on a positive note with residential sales slightly above last year’s levels,” Toronto Real Estate Board president Ann Hannah said in a statement. “I am cautiously optimistic about this result.” </p>
    
    
    
    <p>Just one problem: Garth Turner, a former MP and a vocal housing bear, noted on his blog that TREB actually reported a total of 1,506 sales during the first two weeks of January 2012—not 1,435. That’s 71 fewer homes sold this year than last, or a 2.5 per cent <em>decline</em>. Why the discrepancy? TREB spokesperson Mary Gallagher says some home sales end up falling through each month—perhaps because buyers get cold feet, or because their offers were conditional on financing or home inspections. “We’ve chosen in the past couple of years to revise our figures going forward,” Gallagher says, pointing to a tiny footnote that accompanies TREB’s market reports. “We’re not hiding it.” </p>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    <p>Even so, it’s not an apples-to-apples comparison. By measuring this year’s initial sales with last year’s finalized deals, TREB’s efforts to track the monthly performance of a key market—both sales and prices—is generally inflated by a percentage point or two, according to a review of its monthly releases. Gains look more impressive and slumps seem less serious. And during the first two weeks of 2013, it suggests a housing market stirring back to life when, in fact, the opposite is probably true. <byline>CHRIS SORENSEN</byline> </p>
    
    
     <slug>FAST FOOD</slug> <p>Baked expectations</p>


    <p>As social media-generated fast-food scandals go, the uproar over the length of Subway’s sandwiches is pretty tame stuff. Nobody was caught spitting on a pizza (Domino’s) or standing in a bucket of lettuce (Burger King). But a photo on Facebook that showed a “foot-long” sandwich measuring just 11 inches still managed to create a PR headache for the sandwich chain. A hundred thousand Facebook “likes” later, the story of the shrunken sub made it onto the <em>New York Post</em>’s front page. The tabloid found that four out of seven subs it tested in the Big Apple came up short. Subway told the Associated Press the small subs are unacceptable and blamed the discrepancy on inconsistent bread baking at its franchised locations, which it promised to try and fix. While some patrons appear to be getting shorted, it’s not all bad news: one Subway sub tested by <em>Maclean’s</em> measured in at a healthy 12.5 inches. <byline>CHRIS SORENSEN</byline>
    </p>
    

     <slug>AGRICULTURE</slug> <p>Hay! stop, thief!</p>

    <p>It’s hard to imagine hay bales being the focus of a crime spree. They are, after all, just piles of old grass. But in some parts of the United States, hay theft is emerging as a big problem. Long periods of severe drought and grass fires across much of the western U.S. have forced the price of hay and other livestock feeds to record highs. Some U.S. auctions reported 800-lb. hay bales, enough to feed the average cow for about 20 days,  fetching close to $350 each. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>“Oklahoma is screaming for hay,” Dale Leslein, manager of a hay auction in Iowa, told<em> Farm Progress America</em>. “Missouri is running short; Nebraska is very tight, as are Iowa, Wisconsin, Illinois, Indiana, Tennessee and Kentucky. They’re all running out of hay.”  </p>
    
    
    
    <p>Many thieves are stealing one bale at a time, hoping the farmer or rancher won’t notice. More brazen thieves have made off with truckloads of bales, worth thousands. Farmers have started branding their bales with distinctive twine or colouring. In Oklahoma, one sheriff reportedly inserted a GPS unit inside a bale located in a known hot spot. The trap worked and the thieves were caught. </p>
    
    
    
    <p>There is one upside: Canadian farmers and ranchers are scrambling to help fill the demand for hay in the U.S., where they’re getting $30 per tonne more for their product. <byline>TOBAN DYCK</byline>
    </p>

     <slug>Bright Idea</slug> 
   <p>Thumbs up</p>

    <p>Thumb-happy loyalists of BlackBerry maker Research In Motion might soon be tempted to defect: Silicon Valley has finally figured out how to stick real buttons on a touchscreen. The familiar frustration with typing on glass kept California entrepreneur Craig Ciesla faithful to his BlackBerry’s QWERTY keyboard. But it also inspired him to found Tactus Technology, a company devoted to fixing the touchscreen’s greatest shortcoming. Tactus has created a technology that can be applied to any smartphone or tablet display. It uses nanotechnology to inflate or deflate physical buttons by increasing or decreasing pressure on a transparent fluid beneath a layer of clear polymer. Users can call up a keyboard when they need one, and make it disappear when they don’t. The system, which Wired calls “downright magical,” will be used on devices on sale in mid-2013, according to Ciesla. Trouble, perhaps, for BlackBerry, but a welcome development for millions of frustrated texters. <byline>ERICA ALINI</byline>
    </p>
  
 </body.content>
</body></nitf>