<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf
 SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN" change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" id="art-158632005"> <head><title></title>
 <meta name="Author" content=""/>
 <meta name="Editor" content=""/>
<meta name="PublisherName" content="Maclean's"/>
 <meta name="Subject1" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject2" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject3" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject4" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject5" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <tobject/>
 <docdata>
 <correction/>
 <doc-id/>
 <date.issue norm="20130327" />
 <date.release norm= "20130415" />
 <date.expire/>
 <doc-scope/>
 <series/>
 <key-list/>
</docdata>
	 
 <pubdata date.publication="20130415" name="Maclean's" number="14" volume="126" edition.area="" position.section="" position.sequence="" />
 <revision-history/>
</head>
<body>
  <body.head>
    <slug>Ottawa</slug>
  
    <hedline>Location, location </hedline>
  
    <abstract>The new memorial to the War of 1812  may well prove just a bit too prominent</abstract>
  
  <byline>John Geddes</byline>
  
  </body.head>
  
  <photo href="file:///images/MAC14_181201.jpg"/>
  
  <photo.caption>Warriors: A sculpture by Adrienne Alison, featuring seven combatants in a circle, is one of two finalists in contention for the winning design</photo.caption>
  
  <photo.byline>Bruno Schlumberger/Ottawa Citizen</photo.byline>
  
  <body.content>
    <p>The two finalists in the competition to design a War of 1812 monument on Parliament Hill, who showed off models of their plans in Ottawa last week, faced a perhaps impossible task: respecting the Hill’s grand tradition for memorial sculptures while, at the same time, unavoidably breaking with it. </p>
    
    <p>The two-hour showcase in the offices of the National Capital Commission was the first time the public (and media) got a look at the designs since the government put out a “call to artists” last spring, seeking proposals for a monument to mark the 200th anniversary of the successful defence of Canada against American invaders. The plan is to unveil the completed work late next year, at the conclusion of the extensive War of 1812 commemorations mounted by the Conservatives. </p>
    
    <p>From a short list of six, just two designs, each featuring multiple life-sized bronze figures, were deemed to be in contention for the $787,000 job. Adrienne Alison, of Toronto, clusters seven 1812 combatants in a circle. Brian Cooley, of Calgary, has 20, ranging from First Nations warriors to British infantrymen to French Canadian voltigeurs, arrayed in two lines.  </p>
    
    <p>Neither of these conventional, realistic concepts is likely to prompt much public objection. Yet they are hardly in keeping with past practice on the Hill. The 15 bronze sculptures scattered around the Parliament buildings are mostly prime ministers, plus a couple of monarchs, and a few other select figures from Canadian political lore. The history of raising monuments around the heart of Canadian democracy began in 1873, when John A. Macdonald—so shaken by news of the death of George Étienne Cartier that he broke down in tears in the House—proposed a statue of his indispensable political partner. </p>
    
    <p>The international competition for that commission was won by a sculptor from Quebec, Louis-Philippe Hébert, who went on to a groundbreaking career in public art in Canada. Every statue erected on the Hill since then (apart from a row of plaques to fallen police officers) has fit with the theme of Canada’s evolution as a democracy. As for war’s place in the Canadian saga, the stirring, sombre National War Memorial, inaugurated in 1939, is just across Wellington Street in Confederation Square, a site familiar to millions from Remembrance Day broadcasts. </p>
    
    <p>The planned 1812 monument will look down on the war memorial from a patch of lawn sloping away from Parliament’s East Block. It is not a neutral location. The East Block is an imposing, High Victorian pile of stone, arguably rivalled only by the Library of Parliament as the most atmospheric of the Hill’s neo-gothic buildings. Explaining their design ideas at last week’s showing, both Alison and Cooley expressed deep respect for the East Block and proper concern not to seem to be competing with the National War Memorial. </p>
    
    <p>Still, the task set by the government—in its eagerness to permanently elevate 1812’s place in Canada’s patriotic mythology—creates an inevitable tension. Why a war monument on grounds given over, up to now, exclusively to celebrating political leadership? And why in such awkwardly close proximity to the revered national site for remembering miltary sacrifice? The government is pondering the aesthetics of the two contenders before announcing its final choice. But whether this commission was sensitively conceived from the outset is a question attentive visitors to Parliament Hill may be asking for decades to come.</p>
    
  </body.content>
  
</body></nitf>
