<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf
 SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN" change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" id="art-158632005"> <head><title></title>
 <meta name="Author" content=""/>
 <meta name="Editor" content=""/>
<meta name="PublisherName" content="Maclean's"/>
 <meta name="Subject1" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject2" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject3" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject4" content=""/>
 <meta name="Subject5" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <meta name="Industry" content=""/>
 <tobject/>
 <docdata>
 <correction/>
 <doc-id/>
 <date.issue norm="20130327" />
 <date.release norm= "20130415" />
 <date.expire/>
 <doc-scope/>
 <series/>
 <key-list/>
</docdata>
	 
 <pubdata date.publication="20130415" name="Maclean's" number="14" volume="126" edition.area="" position.section="" position.sequence="" />
 <revision-history/>
</head>
<body>
  <sections>Business</sections>
  
  <body.head>
    <hedline>Econowatch </hedline>
  
    <abstract>A monthly scorecard on the state of the economy in North America and beyond</abstract>
  
  <byline>Colin Campbell</byline>
  
  </body.head>
    
  <body.content>
  
    <p>In Ottawa, the leader of the NDP—<em>the NDP</em>—accused the Conservative finance minister, Jim Flaherty, of “banana republic behaviour” for his efforts to intervene in the economy and influence mortgage rates. Meanwhile, Flaherty’s one-time ally in his anti-debt fight, Bank of Canada governor Mark Carney, has declared the household debt problem solved—apparently, a debt-to-GDP ratio of 165 per cent is no longer anything to worry about. In Vancouver, a former prime minister, Kim Campbell, made headlines this month for filing a lawsuit in which she’s trying to get out of a 2007 condo purchase and recoup a $368,000 deposit. The Canadian housing market, it seems, has entered the twilight zone. It’s getting harder and harder to tell what’s sensical and what’s nonsensical. Even the Tory cabinet can’t seem to agree if it should be concerned about Canadians taking on big mortgages at discount rates, with the Tories’ Small Business Minister Maxime Bernier joining Thomas Mulcair in his criticism of Flaherty.   </p>
    
    <p>There is nothing encouraging in all this. The eternally upbeat Canadian Real Estate Association is now forecasting a bad year ahead, with only Manitoba and Alberta expected to see sales gains. More serious trouble can be seen in the Teranet-National Bank house price index, which recorded its sixth straight month-to-month decline in February. That has been blamed on Flaherty’s recent effort to tighten mortgage rules. Nevertheless, such price declines, coming after a long period of slumping sales, are a sign of a market that’s increasingly out of balance.  </p>
    
    <p>Flaherty helped create the housing bubble by relaxing mortgage rules early in his tenure and now seems intent on making sure he can at least say, “I told you so,” when trouble arrives along with rising interest rates. Campbell’s lawsuit alleges her unit was delayed by over a year. But anyone who has bought a condo in Vancouver can sympathize with her action. A study last week estimates that 15 per cent of condos in the downtown are empty. House prices have as much to do with human psychology as they do location, and when some of our best and brightest appear to lose faith, it doesn’t bode well for the rest of us.  </p>
 
  <p>The Good News</p>
  
  <p>Foreign investors bought $13.3 billion worth of Canadian securities in January. That included the largest purchase of corporate debt, $10.3 billion, since 2001.  </p>
  
  <p>The U.S. Conference Board’s index of economic indicators rose 0.5 per cent in February, more than expected, suggesting good times ahead for America. </p>
  
  <p>Saskatchewan is projecting a $65-million surplus in its latest budget thanks to rising revenues and spending restraint. Are you  taking notes, Ontario?   </p>
  
  <p>Ottawa pledged to do away with tariffs on hockey equipment and baby clothes. Now it’s up to retailers pass those savings onto hockey  parents. </p>
  
  <p>Retail sales in Canada were up one per cent in January, to $38.9 billion, after a 2.3 per cent drop the previous month. Shoppers were spending more in  all regions but the  Maritimes. </p>
  
  <p>It was a good week for aircraft makers: Ryanair ordered 175 new planes from  Boeing while Airbus signed a massive  deal with Indonesia’s Lion Air  for 234 jets.   </p>
  
  <p>A report prepared for the B.C. government says a proposed oil refinery in Kitimat would be a success. Premier Christie Clark called the project a potential  “game changer.”</p>
  
  <p>The Bad News</p>
  
  <p>A major survey last week found 57 per cent of U.S. workers have less than $25,000 in savings; 49 per cent don’t think they’ll have enough to retire comfortably.  </p>
  
  <p>Manufacturing sales in Canada slipped 0.2 per cent in January, to $48 billion. It was the fourth decline in five months. </p>
  
  <p>It’s game over for the CEO of Electronic Arts, John Riccitiello, who resigned last week over lacklustre results. Video game makers have been hit by the rise of free games on mobile devices. </p>
  
  <p>Britain may lose  its triple-A credit  rating again next month. Fitch Ratings warned it is reviewing the country’s rating. Moody’s already downgraded Britain last month. </p>
  
  <p>Fed Ex reported last week a 31 per cent drop  in its quarterly profit. Businesses are looking  to cut costs, and overnight delivery is no longer the priority it once was. </p>
  
  <p>Canada is not the only place with a teetering real estate market. Home prices in Hong Kong could drop 20 per cent in the next two years due to rising loan rates, says Deutsche Bank. </p>
  
  <p>Cyprus’s debt crisis shook confidence in the eurozone once again. A last-minute deal was reached this week, but it only served to highlight the deep divisions among EU members and the risks that still lie ahead.</p>



    <slug>Signs of the Times </slug>
  
    <hedline>Fast cars, funny money</hedline>
  
 
 
    <p>Profits trump national allegiances in today’s auto industry. For the first time in its 94-year history, Bentley Motors is considering building cars outside Britain. But it insists that cars made at a Slovenia factory would retain their Britishness. Swedish carmaker Volvo (now owned by Geely), meanwhile, is set to open a plant in China this year, after reportedly winning government approval for its plan last week. </p>
    
    <p>Italy may be a basket case, but commerce continues: Moleskin, the paper and notebook company billed as the choice of Ernest Hemingway, is going forward with an initial public offering on the Italian Stock Exchange. The company is aiming for a $722-million valuation, with a stock price between $2.60 to $3.40. Shares of another Italian luxury brand, cashmere-maker Brunello Cucinelli, have risen 100 per cent since listing a year ago, the <em>Financial Times</em> reports. </p>
    
    <p>Canada’s Wind Mobile may be up for sale. Its Dutch parent company, VimpelCom Ltd., is reportedly accepting bids for the discount wireless upstart. Launched in 2009 after a government auction of wireless spectrum designed to boost competition, Wind has struggled to win significant market share from the big three Canadian telecoms: Rogers (which owns <em>Maclean’s</em>), Bell and Telus. </p>
    
    <p>Money-laundering rules in the U.S. will soon apply to virtual currencies, amid growing fears that online cash is being used for illicit purposes, reports the <em>Wall Street Journal</em>. The move will bring new reporting requirements for users of currencies such as Bitcoin. Retail spinoffs, like Amazon Coins, may also be affected. </p>
    
 
  <p><em>‘We just want to reiterate  our commitment to being completely transparent’ </em></p>
  
    <p>—Christine Day, the CEO of Lululemon Athletica Inc., tried to reassure investors after the company announced it may  lose as much $67 million in revenue  this year due to a massive recall of  see-through yoga pants  </p>
    
  
  <p>By the Numbers</p>
  
 
    <p>$1 The annual salary hedge-fund manager Edward Lampert will collect for his role as CEO of Sears.  </p>
    
    <p>51 The percentage of new jobs created in Canada last year that went to workers aged 55 and over. </p>
    
    <p>$244 The cost to build Samsung’s new Galaxy S4 smartphone—17 per cent more than Apple’s iPhone 5, says tech research firm IHS. </p>
    
    <p>$187,500 The amount Ford is reportedly paying to each of the 4,000 workers who will lose their jobs at a Belgium plant being closed. </p>
    
    <p>$12.6 million Total compensation awarded to Royal Bank of Canada CEO Gordon Nixon in 2012. </p>
    
    <p>$78 million The BBC’s sale price for travel guide company Lonely Planet—sold at a loss of $124 million to NC2 Media.  </p>
    
    <p>$84 billion The amount spent so far on the F-35 fighter jet by the U.S. government, says <em>ProPublica</em>. </p>
    
  </body.content>
  
</body></nitf>
